[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Welcome to Stanford CS193P,
developing applications for
iOS.
It's winter of 2017.
This is lecture number 11 and
today we're gonna do
one gigantic demo.
Last time I made you suffer
through basically doing
all slides.
Now, you get to enjoy all
demo for the whole time.
And it's all gonna be about
Core Data and applying all
the things that we learned in
the last lecture into a demo.
And then we'll be coming
back to the slides, so
let me just give you a heads
up of what's happening here.
On Friday, we have this
other database mechanism for
storing data in iCloud.
I highly recommen this one,
at our Friday section,
normal place and time.
Monday's a holiday, so
don't show up here on
Monday cuz I won't be here.
And then next Wednesday,
I'll be going over the final
project requirements,
including the rubric, and
also we'll be doing the topic,
autolayout.
Now, your assignment
five has been
posted already,
and it's due one
week from today
before lecture.
So here's Smashtag
from last week.
Remember we have this one MVC
where we type in a search
string, #Stanford or
whatever else,
and it pulls down
a bunch of tweets.
Now we're just gonna
add another MVC,
a core data driven MVC.
And when this MVC is gonna
show all the Twitter users who
tweeted all the tweets that
are showing in this MVC
right here.
So, if you type a certain
search term like #Stanford,
Stanford gets
a bunch of tweets.
And then there's gonna
be a button on this MVC,
we're gonna put it
up in the title bar,
we're gonna show you
how to do that as well.
And you're gonna
click that button.
It's gonna bring a new MVC
with all the users, and
we'll also put in
there how many times,
how many tweets they tweeted.
When we do that, we're only
gonna be looking at the tweets
that are in this result,
this search result right here,
or that have ever come from
typing this search term.
All right, so this is
all gonna be core data.
So we need core
data in our app.
When we built Smashtag we
didn't click use core data, so
we're gonna have to go through
the procedures that I talked
about last time for
adding core data to our app.
And we're gonna do that
by creating a dummy
app right here.
Let's go to New > Project.
So we're gonna create
a dummy project,
you can call this project
anything you want.
I'm gonna call it Foo.
Just make sure that Use Core
Data is clicked right there.
We can put it anywhere we want
cuz we're just gonna turn
around and
delete it in a moment.
And you can see that it has
created this dummy project.
And all we're really
interested in here is
the code from the AppDelegate
that does core data.
You can see that this
AppDelegate imports CoreData.
Now we haven't talked about
the AppDelegate, and we will.
It's part of
the application lifecycle.
But, for now,
all we need to know is that
we're gonna go down here and
get this stuff or core data,
you recognize this
from the slides.
And notice also this
applicationWillTerminate calls
saveContext.
SaveContext is one of the Core
Data methods that you get for
So I'm actually gonna select
that as well as all the rest
free here.
of this stuff is marked
Core Data right there.
And I'm just gonna copy it.
I'm gonna close this project
cuz I don't need it.
And I'm gonna go over to
the AppDelegate in my Smashtag
right here.
And you can see it doesn't
import core data right there
at the top.
Nor does
applicationWillTerminate call
SaveContext, nor does it have
any of other stuff down there.
So I'm just gonna take that
code and paste in here.
And this code is generic,
it works in all applications.
The only thing that's specific
about it is this string right
here, which tells you the data
model, the thing that
describes the schema of your
object or in a database.
Now you notice we have
an error right here, that's
because it doesn't recognize
NSPeristentContainer.
Because NSPeristentContainer
is in a different framework
than UIKit, it's in CoreData.
So every time you're using
CoreData in a swift file,
you need to import CoreData or
it won't recognize in this
managed object or any of the
other symbols from core data.
So that's one thing we have
to do that we use Core Data
The other one is actually
create the data model itself.
button did.
And that we do with
File > New > File, so
I'm gonna go File
> New > File.
And we, normally we're picking
things up here but we're gonna
scroll down to where it says
Core Data and pick Data Model.
We don't want Mapping Model,
we want Data Model.
This is just gonna be that
thing where we describe all
our entities and attributes.
And we can call it
anything we want.
Just to be kind of different
I'm gonna call it Smash.
That's gonna be the name
of my Data Model.
And I'm not gonna put
in Supporting Files.
I'm gonna put it in
Smashtag in a higher,
this level up here and
click Create.
And here it is.
You can probably
recognize this, right?
This is our entities and
attributes.
We haven't put any
of them in there.
Now, since I call this
Smash and not Foo,
I've to go back to
my AppDelegate and
change this Foo string
in here to be Smash.
So I've pretty much now
reproduced everything that
the use core data
button would do.
The only difference would be
the use core data would have
called my xcdatamodeld file.
It would have
called it Smashtag,
cuz that's the name of my app,
but I like to call it Smash.
All right, so now that we have
this nice data model file,
let's go ahead and
create our schema.
Now, I'm gonna do this really
quick because I already showed
you how to do all this
which you can just watch it
happening real fast.
I'm not gonna show you
anything that I didn't show
you in the last lecture.
I'm gonna start by adding
an entity down here at
All right, this entity
I'm going to rename it.
the bottom.
And I'm gonna do tweets and
Twitter users cuz I'm gonna
have that table that
follows Twitter users.
But obviously those Twitter
users are determined by
a bunch of tweets, so
those are two entities I need.
So let's put Tweet here first,
and
we'll add attributes for
the tweet.
I'm gonna add them by clicking
this little plus right here.
So we have the Text Attribute
which is a String.
We have our tweets,
what if we search for
#Stanford twice in a row?
We might get
the same tweet back.
And we want our database
to have unique tweets,
we don't wanna every time we
search we're getting more and
more of the same
tweet in there.
So I need some sort of unique
attribute in my database
which is gonna a string.
Luckily, the Twitter info
that comes in the Twitter
framework, it has a unique
identifier in there for
tweets so it'll be
really easy to set that.
And I'm not gonna use this but
for
example, if I wanted a created
attribute it would be a date.
I would just click Date.
I'm putting this in here cuz
I just wanna show you what
it's like to set
a date in code.
This looks slightly tricky.
So I'm gonna add another, or
actually we could look
here in the Editor Style.
So this is the exact
same thing here in
the Editor Style.
When you're in Editor Style,
you're almost always
gonna have your inspector
open right here so that you
can click on things and
change their types and
things like that.
I'm gonna create another
entity here and it's going to
be our Twitter user, I'm
gonna call that Twitter user.
And notice when I
move these around,
it moves it around whatever
other entities there are.
And I'm gonna be
connecting these two and
creating a relationship, and
you're gonna see it's gonna
keep drawing it
as we draw there.
So let's add some
attributes here.
So I'm gonna click
Add Attribute.
Sorry.
It's not deleting, let's go
back to Editor Style here.
By the way, I do notice
sometimes that when selecting
things, it's not
always that great,
it doesn't do
that great a job.
I'm not sure what it is about
the data modeler that makes it
that way, but
you'll click on something,
and it doesn't click
on that thing,
it clicked the entity or
something else.
So there is an example where
I was clicking on that
attribute, but
it wouldn't let me delete it.
Here I have Twitter
user chosen,
hopefully add attribute.
Yes, it adds it to
the Twitter user.
The only attributes I'm gonna
have on my Twitter user
are the handle, that's your
@whatever, and then your name.
And those are both
going to be strings, so
we'll go over here and
make this be of type string.
And we'll also make
the handle be type string.
So that's it for
the attributes.
And the only thing we have
left to do is the relationship
between these two.
And I'm gonna hold
down Ctrl and
drag between
the two right here.
And you see it creates a new
relationship on both sides.
But we don't want that,
the Twitter user here, this
relationship is the tweets
that this Twitter
user has tweeted.
And for the tweet, this
relationship is the tweeter,
the person who tweeted it.
This tweets relationship right
here we know is a "too many"
relationship because a Twitter
user gonna have multiple
tweets.
That's why get the little
double arrow there.
That's our entire data
model that we need now.
For your homework assignment,
you're gonna need
more things in here.
This is not gonna be
sufficient to the task, so
you're gonna have to
add some more stuff.
But for our simple example,
this is all we need.
Now, we know that we wanna
access all this stuff,
not using value in for
key and set value for key.
We wanna have subclasses,
a subclass called
TwitterUser and a club,
subclass called Tweet.
And we want them to
have the vars for
all of these attributes and
relationships.
And so, we need that
code to be generated.
And the way we do that is we
just select the answer to,
you see I've selected Tweet
right here, entity Tweet.
And you go down here
to Codegen, and
this says, by default,
Class Definition.
That means that it's done it,
it has generated a class
called tweet, and
it's gonna work with all
the vars in relationship.
But that's not
actually what we want.
We want to pick this one,
where it only
creates an extension to tweet
that add to the vars stuff.
That's because we wanna
write the class tweet and
be able to put our
own code in there.
It's very common to one will
write the class herself
the main class.
But you still want
the var magic, so
you want those
extensions in there.
Another thing that I didn't
really mention in lecture, and
really, I don't think really
matters unless you're in
a workspace like we are,
you know, we have Twitter and
smash dot org space, is this
module name right here.
If you don't have
anything in here,
then it's gonna use a global
namespace for these classes,
like tweet, so it's gonna
call the class tweet.
But actually, we already
have a Twitter.tweet, and
now we're gonna have
Smashtag.tweet.
So we want to change this to
be current product module.
So don't forget this.
Wake up, if you're
not paying attention.
If you don't put
this right here,
you're likely to
get tons of errors.
All kinds of conflicting
class names,
and even if your app builds,
it won't run.
Terrible things will happen,
so
you definitely wanna do this.
I don't believe you need
to do this if you're not in
a workspace.
I think if you just
have an app by itself,
you can leave that unset,
and it'll work fine.
So that, we did that for
tweet right here, so
let's do it now for
Twitter user.
Twitter user is default
in class definition,
I want that to be extension
also, and of course,
I want current
product module there.
So that's all we need to do,
and behind the scenes,
Xcode has furiously written
out this extension to make
the vars work.
But we have said that we're
gonna write the class.
So let's do that,
let's create the class for
twitter user and for tweets.
So we're gonna go to
File > New > File,
it's just how we create any
class, it's no different than
any other class we've created,
Cocoa Touch Class.
It's not
a TableViewController,
it's an NSManagedObject, so we
go down here, it's in somewhat
alphabetical order, so, or
is it here, NSManagedObject.
We know that Twitter user and
tweet are representing
the database as
NSManagedObjects or
subclasses thereof,
which we're creating.
So we'll create the tweet
one first and we hit Next.
It says,
where do you wanna put it, and
we'll put it in the same
place as everything else.
And here it is, we know that
we're gonna have an error here
immediately once this thing
gets around to building that,
and that's
the NSManagedObject.
It's not gonna identify, it's
not gonna know what that is
until we say import CoreData.
Don't forget this little
piece in your subclass.
But now we can put anything
we want inside these curly
braces, and we're going
to put a method in there.
So let's do the same thing
here for Twitter user.
Twitter user, in the same way,
put everything in
the same place.
Here it is,
let's import CoreData.
Now when you're first
creating your model file and
you choose that
extension thing, and
hopefully you remember to do
current project model, and
all that stuff,
the first time you build, and
I'm gonna build here,
you might get some errors.
We didn't get any of the kind
of errors that you get from
things being out of whack, but
if things are out of whack,
one thing you can do is go
up to the product menu,
and clean,
just clean everything out.
That'll cause XCode to
regenerate those extensions,
for example.
You can even hold down Option
when you go to the Product
menu and
then Clean Build Folder.
And that will clean out
all your drive data and
rebuild absolutely everything.
So, those are options.
And sometimes those
are options just to do anytime
something's kinda not
really working right.
Now we do have some errors,
though, let's click and
see what this error
is right here.
What is this saying?
It's saying cannot convert
value tweet to specified
value tweet.
Can anyone see what might be
the problem with this line
of code right here?
>> Exactly.
Yes, this is saying tweet,
it doesn't know which one we
want, twitter.tweet or
the smashtag.tweet.
So we have to, in Swift, fully
specify which one we want.
So this one is
the twitter.tweet from our
old code.
And once we fix that,
then now it knows what we're
talking about and all is well.
All right, so
now we've really got our core
data stuff all ready to go.
We've got the classes, we've
got our data model explained,
all that stuff.
What we're gonna do next is
have our main MVC right here,
Every time it fetches tweets,
we're gonna have it put
that tweet in the database.
Once it loads up the database,
then we can build this other
MVC that will query
the database.
So this is gonna be kind
of the loading one.
That's gonna be
the querying one.
Now, I might be quite
tempted to add this code to
TweetTableViewController.sw-
ift.
Remember the thing we spent
the last lecture doing all
this wonderful stuff?
This would be an obvious
place, for example in search
for tweets where I'm
getting the tweets back,
this would be an obvious place
to load up the database.
However, I don't
wanna do that here.
And why don't I
wanna do that here?
Because I have
a perfectly good tweet
table view controller here,
an awesome MVC, very reusable.
You give it a search term,
it'll load up with tweets.
I don't really wanna
pollute it and
make it non-reusable by tying
it to my data model here,
by making it
a core data thing.
So how do I resolve that
conundrum where I wanna keep
this thing reusable,
but I still need to put
this stuff in the database?
The answer is, I'm gonna
subclass this controller.
I'm gonna make another MVC
that is going to inherit
all the capabilities of
this nice generic one, and
add the core data stuff.
So I'm just gonna
go File > New File.
Cocoa Touch class, I'm gonna
make it not a subclass of any
iOS class, but a subclass of
TweetTableViewController.
This is my nice
generic reusable one,
I'm gonna make this
a subclass of that.
I'm gonna call it
SmashTweetTableViewController.
Cuz it uses my
smash data model.
So I'm just gonna create that,
here we go,
put it in the same place
as always other things.
I mean we're gonna just delete
all these code out here.
Here it is,
I always do that just to make
it clearer to you what I'm
actually adding
in this things.
So I have this
SmashTweetTableViewController
and I can go to my story
board for example and
select this controller.
And go to Identity,
and instead of making it
a TweetTableViewController,
I'm gonna make it a
SmashTweetTableViewController.
So now, this is going to
do all the things that
TweetTableViewController does,
plus anything I put
in this sub class.
Now, unfortunately, we didn't
get all the way to designing
our generic reusable one,
so that it was really nice and
subclassable.
Specifically, it will be
really hard to subclass search
for tweets and then get inside
here, in this closure and
do something when
these tweets happen.
So I'm gonna make my generic
TweetTableViewController
a little more subclassable.
What I'm gonna do is take
this code right here and
make a little
method out of it,
insert tweets I'm
gonna call it.
Okay, I'm just gonna create a
new method called insertTweets
that's gonna do what that
code I just cut out there is,
we'll put it up here.
Func insertsTweets,
it can take some new tweets
which is gonna be in
array of Twitter.tweet.
It's gonna have that same code
in there, obviously I don't
need this weak self business
here, because I'm not inside
the closure here, and
it's going to do it.
I'm gonna leave this
essentially internal,
remember that in
default internal,
which means it can be
overwritten or called.
If I made that private,
subclasses would not be
able to overwrite it.
Unfortunately there's nothing
like protected in Swift where
it's like subclassers can
override it but people can't
call it, unfortunately there's
no such thing as that.
All right, so we have to leave
this internal and but now
I can take this method in my
subclass here and override it.
So I just put it here and
say override, so
Swift knows that I'm
overriding this thing.
Then I'm gonna let
Super do its work.
And then I'm going to
call a method on myself.
updateDatabase(with
newTweets), all right?
And that's going to update my
database, so I'm gonna have
a private func here called
updateDatabase (with tweets),
it's gonna be a Twitter.tweet.
Sorry, I keep hitting this
tiny button right there.
That's just going to put
these tweets into Core Data.
And of course it's complaining
because import Twitter and
I'm starting using
Twitter now.
I might as well put it now
import CoreData because this
By the way,
SmashTweetTableViewController
is obviously is
going to be doing a lot of
core data stuff as well.
Everyone see what I did there?
I just subclass this and
I'm putting all my smash tag,
smash core data stuff
into this subclass, so
that the super class
remains completely generic.
I just had to make my
super class a little
more subclassible.
Now, as with any MVC,
we want to think about
the model of this SmashTable,
SmashTweetTableViewController,
of course it's going to
inherit the model
of its super class.
But I'm also gonna
add a model here,
which is the database to use.
And I'm gonna do it by passing
in a PersistentContainer.
Now normally we probably want
this to be the app delegate
view, the app delegate
persistence container.
But I wanna allow people
who are using my MVC,
to use any database they want.
I don't wanna force them to
use that app delegate one.
Having said that, I am gonna
have the default value of
this, go ahead and be that.
So I'm gonna say
(UIApplication.shared.delegate
as?,
AppDelegate)?.persistentConta-
iner.
That's just
the default value but
this is a non-private var, so
I'm using this ViewController
could set the container and
cause it to show things
in a certain database.
That is essentially my model,
my model is this database.
All this class does though
is write to the database,
it's just updating
the database.
All its UI it inherits from
the super class which is non
database oriented.
So how do we update
this database?
What do we need to do?
Well, one thing is, I don't
really wanna update this thing
on the main queue, because,
I don't know if my super class
might fetch a thousand tweets.
And do I really wanna be
blocking the main queue while
I go write a thousand
tweets into my database?
No way, so I'm gonna take my
container right here, and
I'm going to ask it to perform
something on a background
thread.
A background queue, and you
can see, here's the argument,
it's a closure and
it takes one argument.
I double-clicked on it there,
I'm gonna use trailing
closure syntax even.
So this one argument
right here.
This is the manage object
context for that other queue,
the one that I'm allowed
to use inside here.
In order to update
my database.
So I'm just gonna use that
context and put these tweets,
these new tweets that
I got right here,
I'm gonna put them in
the database one by one.
I'm just gonna say for
twitterInfo in this tweets and
then add tweet.
So, how do I do
this piece of it.
How do I add a tweet?
And by tweet there, I mean
the tweet in our data model.
That's what I wanna do.
Add a tweet in our data model
that matches this Twitter info
that I got.
All right, so we're gonna
put the method in tweet in
our subclass of tweet that
we created right here,
that's currently empty.
We're gonna put a static
method in there to either go
out and find a tweet that
matches that twitter info or
to create one if
there's not one there.
So that way they'll keep being
unique, because if we get
the same tweet we'll find it
and just return the one that's
already there versus
creating a new one.
So I'm gonna call this thing,
it's gonna be static or
if its a class,
we can say class func
findOrCreatTweet, matching,
twitterInfo and that's going
to be a Twitter.tweet.
That's the info that's
gonna be passed into it.
And I need to know what
context to go look in, so
I'm gonna say, in context,
NSMan, I need some more space,
MSManagedObjectContext, right
there.
And it's just going
to return a tweet.
So this static method, class
method is just going to go and
look in the database and
find this thing and
if it can find it, then
it'll just create a new one.
So, we have to import Twitter,
(let's get rid of this), and
so how are we
going to do this?
Well this method,
pretty straight forward based
on all you know in Core Data.
First, I'm going to create
a fetch request to go find
this tweet.
Le's do that thats easy how
about let request equal and
remember I have to statically
type this actually so
this is going to be an NS.
Fetch request.
The fetch is what?
Tweets.
So I'm gonna use this
nice Tweet.fetchRequest
method to get one.
So that got me
a fetch request.
A fetch request
that's on tweets.
That's what I have there and
then I have to have
a predicate for this.
So I'm gonna say the request
predicate this is the thing
that gonna say which tweets
do you want in the database?
So predicate here, and
which tweets do we want?
Well, we want a tweet
where the unique key,
remember the unique key
is in our data model,
I'll be going back to
this data model often.
But see here's that
unique key right there.
We wanna know when that
unique key matches what
the person passed in here.
The twitter info of
what they passed in.
So that's %@", and
that's twitterInfo.identifier.
So it turns out identifier
that in our twitter
info dot tweet.
That's the thing that you need
for all time for a tweet.
It's always the same for
the tweet even if you
download it multiple times,
it's always the same.
Now what about our
sort predicate here, or
our sort descriptors rather?
We actually don't need
any sort descriptors
because this better match
exactly one or zero.
So you don't need to put zero
things or one thing in order.
So you don't need
a sort descriptor and
if you don't specify a sort
descriptor you'll get them
back in random order.
But again, we don't care
what that is because it
better be zero or one or
we've got problems.
So how do I fetch this thing?
Very easy, I'm just gonna
say let the matches in
the database equal
context.fetch(request).
Now the only thing about
this is it throws.
Cuz it might not be able
to access the database.
It could be all kinds
of problems, whatever.
So I'm gonna put this in
a do try, a do catch here.
So we'll do do and
put try here.
And we'll put catch, (I'll
talk about what we're gonna do
when we catch an error there).
All right, so
we got the matches.
So these matches what's
the type of this match.
We got an error here,
some error.
Context.
Sorry.
NSManageObjectContext.
So what is the type of
this matches right here?
Anyone wanna guess?
Let's look,
it's array of tweets.
Of course I dispatched.
I get it back
an array of Tweet.
Excellent.
And it should be that
the matches count
if it's greater that zero,
then I found my tweet.
In fact I can just return it.
Return matches(0).
So I found that unique tweet.
I'm actually gonna put
an assert here though
that if the matches.count
is greater than one,
then some kind of
database inconsistency,
because somehow in
that unique field
there's more than one of them
in there so that will be bad.
Maybe I'll put the name of
the method in here tweet dot
that database inconsistency or
something like that so,
I'm putting a little assert.
Now that should never happen
if I've written my code
properly, it should
never be possible for
two tweets to get in there.
There would have to be a bug
somewhere else in my code,
that's why I'm asserting here,
cuz I want it to crash if that
happens so that I notice it.
Things aren't being duplicated
without my knowledge.
Now what about this
catch right here?
What if we tried to do this
fetch to get those tweets and
it fails?
Some problem with
the database or something.
What should we do in here?
Well, we could fatal error and
crash.
That's what save context does,
by the way, in the App
Delegate, it just crash.
We could look at the error and
try to figure out what it is,
things like that.
But you know, I don't actually
know what the person who's
calling this find your
create tweet wants me to do
if there's a database error.
I'm not sure,
do they want me to ignore it?
Do they want me to crash?
Do they want me to try
again or something?
What do they want?
So when you don't really know
what your caller wants to do,
why not just
rethrow the error.
When you rethrow,
that means this method throws.
Everyone understand
what I did there?
I mean this method
findOrCreateTweet throw.
And the only where it throws
is a rethrows if this
generates an error.
So when we call this
findOrCreateTweet back in our
other class where we have to
be careful cuz it throws now.
So I like to use try.
But if we get down here,
then we made it passed here
without finding a match, so
here's what we need
to create the tweet.
So I'm gonna say let
tweet equal, and
how do we create a tweet?
We just say
TweetContext context.
So that creates a tweet
in the database.
Now I can just set the tweet
fields by setting the vars,
like the tweets, that's
actually do that unique first,
that's important one.
So that's
TwitterInfo.identifier.
We're gonna make sure we said
that, if we don't said that,
then we might start getting
problems here because every
body is unique is gonna be
the same zero or blank,
either or something.
How about the tweets text?
Let's set that to
the twitterInfo.text.
Here's created tweet.created.
That's twitterInfo.created and
then we'll return the tweet.
Now, this line over here
is gonna give us an error,
as soon as it catches up.
And this error's
kinda weird one.
It says cannot assign
a value of type 'Date' to
type 'NSDate?'.
And I mentioned on one of
the slides from last time,
that in the database,
dates are NS dates.
But I also mentioned that
you can automatically bridge
a date to an NS date.
And you can do that with as.
So I can say as NSDate.
And that will always work.
This as will always work as
long as this Is an NSDate,
then this as will always work,
it always can bridge across.
So this is kind of unfortunate
that you have to do this for
your dates, but you do, sorry.
Okay, there's one more
thing in tweet, though.
What's the missing
thing in tweet?
Tweet.tweeter.
I've got to set
my tweeter here.
I just created this tweet, I
gotta set who the tweeter is.
So to do the tweeter,
I'm gonna go do this exact
same method over
in TwitterUser.
So that I can create a Twitter
user the exact same way.
So we'll call it find or
create Twitter user.
I, kind of pre canned right
here cuz you're not gonna
learn anything from
me typing this,
basically this exact
same thing in again.
Gotta import twitter.
But it's exactly the same,
it has the same exact logic.
I'm doing exactly
the same thing.
I'm even rethrowing,
just creating the twitter
user if I can't find it.
And for a twitter user, it's
handle, the person's handle,
@ whatever,
is the unique identifier.
So now that we know how
to create a Twitter user
using that I can say Tweeter
equals Twitter user.
Find or there it is,
finally recognize it.
Okay, find or
create Twitter user, and
we wanna use the Tweets
user field, Twitter.
Lowercase Twitter info dot
user, that's the user.
Then we'll do it in
the same context of course.
Now this throws, so
we have to try this.
And if it can't do it,
I'm just going to fail again.
Here maybe I want to maybe
re-throw again, possibly.
I might even wanna crash or
something, I don't know.
It's not clear to me,
what to do if I can't
create the twitter.
If Tweeter is something
that has to be set for
a tweet to make any sense in
the database, then I probably
do wanna re-throw or
do something terrible here.
But by just saying try,
instead I'm just giving up,
okay I'm just not
setting the tweeter.
So, there could be tweets that
are created with
no tweeter there.
Twitter user, yeah,
twitter user doesn't need
to be an optional there.
Sorry, I made that
accidentally.
So It's just going to
return a twitter user.
And the try makes it into an
optional twitter user which is
okay because tweeter,
this relationship,
is an optional twitter user.
It comes out of
our data model.
So, that's it,
that's how we create a tweet.
We need to use this
method right here to put
those tweets in the database.
So, let's go back to here.
Let's go to our
SmashTweetTableViewController.
And here, where we wanna add
the tweets, we'll just say
Let a Tweet equal
Tweet.findOrCreateTweet.
We'll pass it,
the Twitter info.
That's this Twitter info right
here that was passed to us and
these Tweets.
And in context, we're gonna
use our containers context.
Sorry, we're not using
our container context.
We're using this
context right here.
So we use this little
Now of course we know this
thing throws right here.
So we'll just do try
question mark here.
Because here I do know
that when I'm updating
if I can't create that tweet,
I'm just gonna drop it.
the database,
It's not gonna hurt anything
if just not collecting
the data it needs too.
There's really nothing I
can do about it whatever
the database error is it's in
there maybe I could report
an error to the user and say
couldn't update data base but
a lot of times user are like
what the heck is that.
So here dropping it
is probably fine.
Now notice we have a warning
here, see this warning?
It says let tweet equals and
you never use tweet, and
in fact I don't
wanna use tweet.
So what do you do in this
case where I found and
create this tweet but
I actually don't want it.
I don't wanna do anything,
I just wanted it to get
created if it wasn't there.
Well here you can say,
"Under bar".
If you say _ =" something it
means I'm ignoring the return
value, which is fine.
I don't need the return value
I just want this thing created
in the database,
doesn't have to do anything.
Everybody following me so
far here?
So now we have loaded
up the database.
That's it.
That's all of the code we need
to load our database up
with all these tweets.
Now let's go ahead and print
some database statistics here
just to see if this is
working before we go off and
do our UI for a new MBC.
So I'm gonna say,
printDatabaseStatistics and
I'm gonna create a new
private func here called
printDatabaseStatistics.
Copy, paste.
And what I want this thing to
do is tell me how many tweets
and how many twitter users
are in the database.
That's all I
wanted to do here.
So if I wanna do anything
in the database, if
I wanna look in the database
I obviously need a context.
I have to have a context to
look inside the database or
whatever.
So what context
am I gonna use?
I'm gonna say, if I can let
my let context equal my
containers?.viewContext.
Now the viewContext Is
the mainqueue context for
this database.
So, I'm gonna have
printDatabaseStatistics.
It's not inside this closure,
so
it's not gonna
use this context.
We'll have it use
the main viewContext.
This is pretty much, unless
you had it perform background
tasks, this is pretty much
the only context you have, so
we'll have it do on
the main context.
So how am I gonna find out
how many tweets there are?
Okay, I'm gonna create
a request and do a fetch.
So NSFetchRequest.
And this one is a request for
tweets.
Equals Tweet.fetchRequest.
So now I got this request,
the fetch request
I need no predicate here
because I want all the tweets.
If you have no predicate
that means give me them all.
So that's what I want, and
so now I'm just going to
say here if I can let
the tweetCount equal
trying to access the context
to fetch this request.
Which it may or
not be able to do.
But if it can then you
understand what I did there?
Then I'm going to
get the count.
What's the type of
that expression?
Optional array of tweets.
Because this returns
an array of tweets if it
doesn't throw and
this turns into an optional.
So this is an optional
array of tweets.
Here I'm optional chaining.
So if that's not new then
I get to continue and
get the count.
This is just array's count,
this is a method count in
array a var for
the count in array.
Now I've got the tweetCount,
now I'm just gonna say print,
tweetCount, tweets,
and that's it.
I fetch them all.
I just fetched every tweet
in the entire database,
just to find out how
many there were.
What if there's a 100,000
Tweets in there?
I'm really gonna fetch and
that, of course we know that
it's only gonna fault sum of
min until I ask for the data.
So it's not that bad but
there's a better
way to do this.
By the way here's another,
before I show that.
See this request I made this
separate variable, right here.
That's not actually necessary.
I can just take this
request right here and
put it right in.
To here.
Watch this.
Cut, paste, and
get rid of that.
That's because
the fetch method takes
any kind of fetch request.
It takes anything whose type
is a fetchRequest result
basically, which
is a protocol.
And so I didn't have to
create that other variable.
And notice I don't have to
statically type this because
this would take anything
that returns a fetchRequest.
It'd return something.
So anyway, so
what's the better way to
do counting right here?
Is I'm gonna say if
let tweeterCount, so
I'll count the tweeters in
this better way, equals try
to get the context.count for:
TwitterUsers.fetchRequest,
okay, all twitter users.
Then I can print
the twitterCount.
Twitter users.
So this method count is
very much like fetch but
it doesn't is still kinda
evaluating this fetch request,
it's getting the same things.
In this case we're
counting users, but
it's really just
asking the data base.
If I were to fetch this,
how many would you give me?
So it's all done on
the database side,
nothing actually
has to get fetched.
So it's just another
method count.
But it does throw, as well,
in the same was as Fetch does.
So we still have to do try.
So this whole expression
right here, isn't option int.
So I'm unwrapping it with if
let, and printing it out.
Got all that?
Let's cross our
fingers here that this
all works that we've got
all this database learning.
And we gonna print
our database
statistics and
it all gonna work.
Here we go and this is just
some junk from IOS there so
we'll ignore that.
Right here let's search for
some.
Let's search for,
how about hash tag stan,
well let's do hash tag stan,
yeah, that's a good one.
All right, it wants to
use my Twitter account.
Sure, here it is, and.
Uh-oh, look on
the console there.
Zero tweets,
zero Twitter users.
Maybe let's pull some more.
No, it's still zero tweets,
zero Twitter user.
Well it's not working.
Anyone see anything
in this code for
why this is not working.?
Yeah, we're doing a good job
of loading up that database,
but we never save it.
So all that is just
waste of time,
we need to say try,
context, save.
Now again I'm ignoring
the error here.
In a demo a lot of the time I
use try, question mark because
I just don't have time
to do the due catch and
handle all the errors.
That's something you should
be looking at
the option of doing.
So here I'm just
gonna save and
ignore any errors, alright?
So that should fix it right?
Let's go see.
All right, here we go.
Hash tag Stanford.
No.
Zero tweet.
Zero Twitter users.
I put that save in there.
What is going on?
I had to pull again.
Look, I pulled and it worked.
What the heck is going on?
When I first loaded up
it said zero tweets and
then now it's saying 57th.
Something weird going on here.
What's happening?
Well, this is actually
a multi threading problem.
Can anyone see the
multi-threading problem here?
No?
I'm gonna put some print in,
so you can see it.
So watch this, print,
starting database load.
And then down here, when I'm
done with the save here,
I'm gonna just print,
done loading database.
And there, so
now let's run.
All right, hash tag Stanford.
Got a crash there, database
inconsistency, interesting.
So this is why we put
this inserts in here.
Asserts in here, so let's
see why do we think we have
a data basing
consistency here?
Yeah?
>> That's what it is.
Yes, my search is backwards,
there.
I'm inserting here that
matches.count == 1.
So that's why that's crashing,
okay.
Good.
Let's
go back.
Now let's try again,
hashtag Stanford.
Let's see what's
going on down here.
Starting database load,
it prints the statistics, and
then it's done loading.
That's bad.
You see, it's not waiting for
it to be done loading before
it prints the statistics.
You see?
Now why is that happening?
Because we're putting print
databaseStatistics here after
downloading.
So why isn't it saying
starting, done,
and then printing?
Because this right here,
happens on a different queue.
So the way that
this code goes is,
starting, this execute
returns immediately.
Because all it
does is put this
closure onto
the background task queue.
Then this happens.
Then, this closure starts
running on that background
queue, loads up these things.
And it prints.
Do you see what's
going on there?
Everyone understand
the multi-threading?
So the way to make this work
is to take print database
statistics, and
put it inside here.
All right, cuz now it's not
going to print the database
statistics until it's done.
Now this has a problem though.
Okay, this is very bad.
First of all, we're gonna have
to do, I'm not sure why it's
not complaining here,
there we go, now it is.
It wants to know,
it wants self dot here, so
I'm gonna do weak self to
break that memory cycle.
Hopefully everyone understands
that now, what's going on.
Okay.
But that's not
the problem here.
There's an even worse problem.
And in the interest of time,
I'm going to put a print down
in here to show you something.
If I'm gonna check
to see if this code
is running on the main thread.
So I'm gonna say IF,
and the way you do that is
you say thread.ismainthread.
Okay, if I'm in the main
thread it'll be true.
So I'm gonna say
on main thread.
And if it's not true,
I'm gonna say off main thread.
So let's see if this
statistics is happening
on the main thread or not.
I think many of you know
which one it's going to be.
By looking at the code here.
All right, here we go again,
hash tag Stanford.
Here we go.
Off main thread.
Okay, why is it off
the main thread?
Because I called print
database statistics inside
this closure, it happens on
a background thread thus this
entire method is happening
off the main thread.
Now, is that a problem?
That's a huge problem, because
what context am I using here?
The mainQueue context.
ViewContext is
the mainQueue context.
I cannot be using the
mainQueue context off the main
thread.
You see the problem here?
So it worked, but
could have easily crashed or
done something terrible.
So how do we fix that?
This is where we use
that method I was telling
you about in context
called perform.
I'm gonna say context perform
this code on your safe queue.
When I say context perform and
I put this code in there,
it says to that context,
do this block but
whatever you do, do it on
the right queue for you.
And since this is
the view context,
it's going to be back
on the main thread,
watch.
Hashtag Stanford.
Here we go back
on main thread.
So this perform right
here is something that
a lot of people would advise,
always use it unless you're
Inside one of these where it's
clearly using this context
in this background thing.
Any other time,
a lot of people say always
wrap your calls in this.
That way, you'll never have
a problem where some things
being executed on the wrong
thread, okay, wrong que.
Understood all that?
A little crash course in core
data thread safety there.
All right, so this is great.
We've got our database
loading up, so
we've got a database
full of tweets.
Now, we want to add some UI to
show all this data somehow.
So let's go back to our
storyboard and take a look,
what we got here.
And what kinda UI
we're gonna have?
Like I said, I'm just gonna
have another MVC over here
that I'm gonna segue to,
with a little bar button item.
So how many of you figured out
how to use a bar button item
as part of your homework
assignment I think?
But if you didn't you're gonna
see today how to do it, and
it's quite simple.
So this new MVC that I'm gonna
segue to, let's go ahead and
create an MVC for it,
Cocoa Touch Class.
It is just going
to be a sub class
of UITableViewController.
I'm gonna call it
SmashTweetersTableViewControl-
ler, so
this is showing tweeters.
Remember this table's gonna
show all the tweeters who
tweeted the tweets that
are in the other MVC.
We'll put it up at the,
not in the Twitter project,
that's for sure.
Let's put it down here, okay?
I always check this list,
this one here or
you end up with files
all in random places.
You don't want that.
Here it is.
Again,
I'm gonna delete
all this stuff.
See it's a tableView, so
it's got all this UITableView,
so we don't need any of this
stuff as you're
gonna see here.
This is our new
TableViewController.
Let's go ahead and
update our storyboard
to segue to this thing.
So we'll go over here.
Let's create our bar button
item to do the segue, so
I'm gonna search here for
button.
You never wanna put
a button in here,
it'll look like it's gonna
working, but it's not right.
Put a bar button in a bar.
So we'll call this Tweeter cuz
that's what it shows, it shows
the tweeters that tweeted all
the tweets in this table.
Let's get
a TableViewController out,
here it is.
TableViewController right
there.
Lets go ahead and
segue from this.
Ctrl + drag.
Show segue, we're inside
a navigation controller here.
Let's set this segue
identifier, we'll call this,
what did I?
I had a good name for this.
Yes, Tweeters
Mentioning Search Term.
Cuz that's what
this segue does.
It show the tweeters that
have mentioned this search
term right here.
Let's also have our little
cell here be a subtitle cell.
So we'll change
that to subtitle.
And we need a reuse identifier
for this cell right here.
We'll call this a TwitterUser
Cell, cuz that's what it is.
The Twitter user gonna be
shown in this cell right here.
All right, so that's it.
That's our entire UI.
Super simple.
All we need to do now is
implement the guts of
this controller right here.
So let's go back to that.
Here it is right here.
Let's talk about
the public API.
I just really want to get
in the habit of this.
Every time we introduce a new
MVC, let's talk about it,
its public API.
So this
SmashTweetersTableViewControl-
ler, really has two
parts in its model.
One is, it needs to know the
mention, the search term that
its supposed to be showing
the Tweeters for, so I'm gonna
have, I'll call it mention,
which is just a string.
So that's part of its
public model, and then,
what's the other
part of its model?
The database.
What it does is look
up in the database and
find tweeters who mention
this in their tweets.
So it's gotta have
an NSPersistentContainer here.
By the way, some people,
import CoreData.
Instead of having the database
represented in the public
model here as a container,
they might just pass
the context only.
If they pass the context
only here though,
you can't do any
background stuff.
So I like to pass,
pass the container here.
Plus, this whole thing
is a UI element,
so it wants to use
a view context.
No other context cuz it does
its stuff all on the main
queue, it's a UI.
So it's nice when you pass a
container cuz you're gonna ask
for the view context and
you know you're getting
a main queue context.
Where if someone passes
a context in here,
could be not be a main queue
context, that could be bad.
So I think a container is a
good wrapper when you want to
tell an MVC this is the
database to use to do what you
do, here it is.
And sure we'll do our little
trick here where we make
a default,
(UIApplication.shared.delegete
as?
AppDelegate)?.persistentConta-
iner.
You don't even really have
to do this but we'll do it.
So that's basically
our model and
anytime our model changes,
I'm gonna have a didSet
here that updates my UI.
We'll do the same thing.
If I can select it,
do the same thing with
this guy right here.
We need a private
func to do that.
So this is our model,
and it's UI updating.
Now before I go implement
this UI updating,
cuz it's pretty
straightforward,
I'm gonna back to my
SmashTweetTableViewController,
the one that's gathering
all the statistics,
because that's also
the one I'm segueing from.
This smash,
this one right here,
Smash Tweet Table
View Controller,
I'm segueing from this to
this using this button.
So that's where
the prepare needs to be.
So I'm gonna put the prepare
in here for that.
So let's put the prepare
down at the bottom here.
prepare (for segue:.
Here it is.
Now,
I'm gonna go through this
really fast because you guys
surely know prepare
(for segue: by now.
I mean to say if
the segue:identifier is what
I said which is,
and again I should make
a constant here but for speed,
so this is Tweeters
Mentioning Search Term,
that's what I
called that segue.
Then I'm going to
get the destination.
So that is a
TweetersTableViewController =
segues.destination as?
SmashTweetersTableViewControl-
ler.
And yeah, I could probably do
ContentViewController here,
because if I had that
extension in here, because
maybe I want to put this in
a split view someday and etc.
But first time
I won't do that.
So now I've got
the tweetersTVC.
This is my
TweetersTableViewController.
I'm just gonna set
its public API.
TweetersTVC.mention.
Mention equals my search term.
This is the MVC where
you type the text in so
it has search text.
And then the
tweetersTVC.container equals
my container.
I have the same one.
The tweeters MVC looking
in the same database I'm
looking in.
So here I am actually
setting this thing.
We got an error here,
what is it?
Tweeters, okay.
All right, so I'm just
setting my public model of
my Tweeters, not Tweet,
TweetersTableViewController.
SImple enough.
All right, now that we are all
ready to segue to this nice
SmashTableViewController, how
do we update its UI?
How do we get it to
look in CoreData,
find the Twitter users that
have tweeted something that
matches this mention and
show it?
Well, there's really,
we're gonna use NS Fetched
Results Controller, of course,
that's the main deal here.
And what are the pieces
we need to do?
This was the last slide
from the last lecture.
I hope you all remember it,
it was very recent.
First thing is we have to have
this table-view controller
be an
NS-fetched-result-controller
If you're going to use
a fetched results controller
delegate.
your table needs to be
the delegate of that fetched
controller, and I told you I
was going to help you out with
that and provide that code and
sure enough I am.
It's right here.
I'm gonna drag it in
somewhere, copy it in, yes.
All right, and let's take
a look at it, here it is,
FetchedResultsTableViewContro-
ller.
You can see that it
is a subclass of
UITableViewController that
implements the
NSFetchedResultsControllerDel-
egate protocol.
So these are the methods
right here in our protocol,
there are four of them.
You can see that it is just
using table view methods
to update the table.
These controller methods
get called whenever the NS
Fetched Result Controller
notices the database change
in a way that would affect
the NS Fetched Result.
So this is the magic
that makes your table
automatically update when
the database changes.
You don't have to do anything,
it just automatically updates.
It's because of this delegate.
Now, for our thing to work we
need to be a subclass of this,
so that we inherit
all this stuff.
we're just going to go back
to our smashTweeters here and
So that's easy,
instead of being
a UITableViewController,
I'm gonna be a
FetchedResultsTableViewContro-
ller, simple.
So, that's the easy
way to become
a FetchedResultsController
delegate.
Now, what was the next
thing we need to do?
We have to implement all of
our UITableViewDataSource
Methods using
a fetchedResultsController.
So there's two parts to that.
One is we need to
create a var, which is
a fetchedResultsController
controller.
It's going to be a type
NSFetchedResultsController.
It's FetchResultsController
that fetches tweeter users.
So FetchResultsController
is also generic type and
you have to say what kind
of thing does it fetch?
So I've got this var,
how do I implement all
those UI table of your data
source methods as well?
Well, I can type them all
in but you know what,
it's exactly the same in every
single to every single time
you implement one of these
the code is exactly the same
because
fetchedResultsController
always answers those questions
in exactly the same way.
So you could copy and
paste it from some other
half that you've done or
you could use this little
beauty that I've created for
you right here, another
little thing you can drag in,
which we'll take a look.
Copy that, and
this is an extension
that you can
extend your class.
So in this case,
it's our smash tweeters
tableviewController.
And in this extension,
it adds all the UI tableview
data source methods.
See.
And implements them
in terms of your
fetchresultscontroller.
Now, this extension will not
compile if you do not have
a fetch results controller
because extensions can't add
any storage themselves so you
have to have the storage be in
your class but this class does
have fetch result controller.
Now, the one thing it doesn't
implement here though is
cellForRowAt cuz cellForRowAt
add is specific to whatever
data you're showing
in the table but
even cellForRowAt, if we go
back here and do cellForRowAt,
let's do that so cellForRowAt
index path more with.
And, of course,
we know how to do that right,
let the cell equal to
tableView deque this one,
and the Identifier was
"TwitterUser Cell" I believe,
correct me if I'm wrong.
And we want IndexPath there,
so I got the cell, and
we return the cell.
And in between,
I need to load the cell up
with its various information.
Now we set our cell to be,
if you remember,
a Subtitle cell, right?
This is a Subtitle cell.
So we can set its TextLabel
and its detailTextLabel.
So let's just start with
just the TextLabel.
So I wanna set
the cell.textLabels Text,
basically equal to
the twitter uses handle.
But I have to get the twitter
user that's in this row.
Okay, how do I find
the twitter user
that's in the role?
I'm gonna ask my fetch
results controller.
Let the twitter
user in this role,
in this row, equal my
fetch results controller
which might be null
cuz it's an optional.
Object(at: indexPath).
And since this could be nil
because this could be nil
right here let's do if let,
then we will update our cell.
Now if we didn't have
a fetchedResultsController,
by the way, if this were nil,
our number of rows and
sections would be
zero all the time.
This would never be called.
So we can even put
an exclamation point here.
And maybe we should put
an exclamation point here
because this should never
be called if this is nil.
But anyway, so it's this very
simple method, object)at:,
is gonna return you
the thing of the type
that it's controlling,
which is Twitter user.
And if we look at
the type here,
you can see that's a Twitter
user that goes at this
index path.
So that row and that section.
So it could not be easier.
And now we can just, in here,
update whatever you or
I want, no matter how
complicated it is.
We've got the Twitter user
that's showing there, so
we can his handle,
his username, whatever else.
We wanna get on him and
put it in there.
Everybody got that?
Super simple, and
yes it is super simple that's
what's great about in fetch
results controller is that
really the amount of code we
actually had to write
here is absolutely tiny.
Now, there is one piece
left which is update UI so
when someone sets our
mention or sets our database,
we need to create a fetch
results controller, obviously.
Just can't be nil
all the time,
we actually have to create
one and we're just gonna say,
fetchResultsController = a new
NSFetchedResultsController,
which is for Twitter users.
And we will use this
constructor right here.
I'll go ahead and
separate this out so
you can see a little better
what the arguments are.
Let me see from
this slide as well.
So what are the four
things we need?
We need a request,
I'll make a request.
We need a context,
I'll make a context.
We need the name of
the var in TwitterUser,
that says this section title.
Well, we don't have any
sections all our Twitter users
are gonna be shown in
one big like long list,
so that's nil and
we won't cache our results.
Although we could, because
we're never gonna change this
request--well, actually
that's not true.
We could change this
because someone might
bring up this MVC and
then change the mention and
that would be changing the
request to look for different
twitter users so it's better
not to catch this beside
the results are hopefully
gonna be fairly small.
So I have to do a request
in context here.
Let's do context first.
I'm gonna say if I can let my
context equal my containers
View context.
Now, this is very
important right here to use
view context because
this is a Ui thing.
And this fetch results
controller is gonna be working
with our table view
controller, that's all UI so
we wanna do this all
in the main queue.
So, you have to
use view context.
You cannot do that
background thing
to create your
FetchResultController.
All right, so all that leaves
is this request here so
I'm gonna let the request
it's obviously going to
be an NSFetchRequest for
Twitter users.
And we use this nice
convenience thing here
TwitterUser.FetchRequest and
so what does our request need?
Well, our request needs
sort descriptors, so
we're gonna have to have some
array of sort descriptors.
Our request also
needs a predicate.
Predicate.
Whoops, gotta get format
right here, this one.
We're gonna have to have some
format string there, and
then some args for
the percent at signs.
So let's do this sort
descriptor first.
We're looking for all the
Twitter users who have tweeted
something that mentioned
that search for a minute.
Let's order them by their
handle, at sign whatever.
So all we need to do then is
say, NSSortDescriptor with and
we'll use the one
with the key.
It's not, it's going to
make me type it, arg.
So we'll do the key handle and
we'll do ascending true.
That's good enough, we'll just
have it sort however it sorts.
We'll come back to sorting
later and look at it.
We only need one sort
descriptor we're not gonna
sort by the a handle and
then subsort by something else
because the handle will be
sufficient sorting in there,
and what about our predicate?
What tweeter users
are we looking for here?
This is really the key to
making anything work and for
your homework by the way,
really this homework it's
not a lot of programming.
It's a lot of thinking.
Especially designing
your schema so
that this line of code right
here is really simple.
If you design your schema
properly you can make
this quite simple.
It's all about thinking about
what am I actually showing,
and how do I calculate
what those things are.
In this case I'm showing
all the Twitter users.
Any of the twitter users
here whose tweets,
the text in their tweets
actually, contains, and
we'll go case insensitively,
that search term.
Our mention.
Which is optional, so
we'd better unwrap.
And if I'm gonna
unwrap this forcibly,
I'm actually going to check
to make sure it's not nil.
Just to be careful there.
So this is
the predicate we want.
We want any Twitter user.
Because we're looking for
Twitter users,
any Twitter user who's tweets,
any of their tweets,
texts contains this mention.
This is actually,
I probably said that
a little bit wrong there.
We're looking for
any Twitter user who have any
of it's tweets text
contains this mention.
Off of any, means here,
anything, any of the tweets
texts contains this, then
show this twitter user here.
Everybody got all that?
So now, I got my fetch
request controller,
remember the only two things
I need to do now is to
try to have my fetched results
controller perform this fetch,
okay that can throw, so
that's why we're trying there.
And we've got to tell our
table view, time to go
call all of your UI table
view data source methods, and
we know whose going
to answer that,
that extension that
we have there.
And it's going to ask fetched
results controller for
all the information it needs.
By the way, notice I made this
public, (internal, basically).
That's because I put
that extension over here
in a different file and
it wouldn't be a receive
this otherwise.
So, if you wanna make
this var private,
which is not a bad idea,
actually.
In a MVC that is using
a fetchedResultsController,
making its controller
public is kinda opening up
the internal guts of it.
If you wanna make this
private, then you would just
put this extension at
the bottom of the file,
in the same file.
That way they you would
be able to see it.
Hopefully we've
remembered everything,
let's go give this a try.
Let's go here #stanford again.
Now I'm gonna press Tweeters.
And it's going to segue
to this new MVC that
will hopefully show us
a list of all the people who
have tweeted here.
And sure enough, there it is.
These are all the people
who have tweeted one of
the tweets that was found
by that search team.
Search term #stanford.
It even has that listed at
the top, which is kinda cool,
because that's the same
as the back button here.
Now, one thing I don't
like about this,
a couple of things,
one, subtitle.
Okay that's no good,
we could put something
better there like,
maybe we could put how many
tweets they've tweeted
that match that search term,
that'd be cool.
And then, the other thing
is the order its in,
look at this, all the capital
letter's first and
then all the lowercase
letters after it.
I want it all to be
alphabetical case insensitive,
And like that,
so let's fix those things.
So the case insensitive is
just a matter of sorting.
We're sorting there and
it's sorting by some default,
while the default is obviously
case sensitive search and
we don't want that.
So, this is where this
sorting selector comes in.
And we just say #selector and
it's gotta be an NSString
selector because this
is an NSString field.
And there's quite
a few of them,
if you type compare, you'll
get to see what they are.
So, there's
a localizedCaseInsensitive,
this kind of thing, so,
let's try CaseInsensitive.
Let's do localized case
insensitive compare.
So that's case insensitive,
and using the user's local
language to know what goes
where, what the ordering is.
So that's a pretty good one,
to use localized case
insensitive compare.
So that's all we need to
do to the case sensitivity,
that was really easy.
How about this thing of having
the cells detail text label?
Have the twitter account,
basically the account
of tweet.
So I'm gonna say this
equals twitter tweet count.
Tweet and let's even be nice
here and put an s if it's one.
Count equals one.
Then we'll put an s on the end
otherwise we're nothing.
Okay, every one see
what I did there?
So it will take one tweet.
What else do we
need to do here?
We'll do this.
All right, so I just want
to make it look nice.
One tweet, two tweets,
zero tweets.
How do I get this tweet
count right here and
let tweet count
equal something?
And to do this,
I'm going to do a little quick
fast type code, because we're
getting close to the end here.
I have a method here
called tweet count,
with mention by right here.
And let's look at this
method and how this works.
So this is gonna give
the tweetCountWithMentionBy
this twitterUser, the
twitterUser that we got from
our fetchResultsController.
It's gonna give us
the tweetCount.
And the way it's work is
it's gonna create a fetch
for tweet.
So here even in the middle
of my cellForRowAtIndexPath,
I'm making a request perfectly
valid to go to a fetch
request right in the middle
here to find some information.
So here I'm fetching for
Tweets this time,
cause I wanna count the number
of Tweets this Twitter user
has Tweeted with that so sure.
And the predicate is,
"tell me all the Tweets who's
text contains that mention".
And who's Tweeter is
this Twitter user?
Mention and a twitterUser.
And I'm gonna go ahead and
force unwrap that,
because, boy if I get all
the way down to here,
surely the mention is not nil.
And then I'm going to return,
I'm going to use the same
context the twitterUser is in,
hopefully that's
a view context.
And I'm going to count,
use that count thing for
that request.
And if that fails for
some reason,
I'm gonna say 0 tweets.
Have you got that?
So let's go
take a look.
Right, #stanford.
Right, here it is.
Tweeters, look at that, not 1
tweet, 37 tweets from MEC30.
Let's go see if we can
find MEC30 in here.
Sure, there's one my MEC30,
another one, sure enough.
Look at this ME, what the?
Okay, what if I decide I don't
want MEC30 in there anymore.
I don't like, this guy is
a spammer or something.
I don't know what
his problem is.
But I don't want him in there.
Well, I can go back here and
change my predicate right here
to say, I want all
the tweets that have that.
But I don't want ones where
the handle of that guy, let's
say it even begins with, just
to be kind of interesting MEC.
What was it?
MEC, we'll say.
And we can't put this
literal in here, so
we have to say %@ and then we
put the MEC on the outside.
So let's see
if that got rid
of Mr. MEC.
He gone!
Got that spammer out of there.
No questions?
Yes?
Question?
Yeah, so the question is, are
the tweets in the database,
do they stay in there for
run to run?
And the answer is absolutely,
that's one,
core data is kinda all about.
There's a permanent database.
So all those tweets, those
#stanford tweets in there,
if we go back and run again.
And search for #stanford.
If there have, you know,
been some tweets since
then they'll be added.
But every single tweet
we ever got is still
going to be in here.
So you can see this list
actually got slightly longer,
a few tweets were in there,
but they're all in there.
we're unique-ing them so it's
not adding them over and over.
And you gotta be careful to
do that on your homework.
Don't add them over and over.
But yeah, that CoreData
database is there.
By the way,
I'm gonna show you a trick.
We just enough time to show
you something's really cool.
What if you want to
delete your database?
Okay, now there's two
reasons you wanna,
might wanna delete
your database.
One, you wanna clear the data
out cuz you wanna get a fresh
set so you can see if
things are working.
And number two, you might
change your data model.
If I go back here and
I go to my data model here and
I add some attributes or
add an entity,
then my app will no longer
run on that device or
on the simulator cuz it'll say
your data model doesn't match
the data that's already
on this device.
So here's the magic to get rid
of, it's not very magical.
Is on your device, or
on the simulator, you go to
the home button right here and
you press and hold to
make the things jiggle.
You all know about that?
It's how you delete apps.
And just delete your app.
And when you delete your app,
your core data goes with it.
And now when you run the next
time, you're gonna run,
it's gonna be
a fresh database,
it will have the new
data model etc.
So I'm very glad
you asked that,
really important to know how
to clear out your database.
Now if we do #trump or
something,
see it's even asking me again,
do I wanna allow it?
And I do.
All right, that is it.
I will see you next Wednesday
after you turn in your
homework and
we'll learn all about the
final project in Autolayout.
For more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.