[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> All right, well,
welcome to Stanford CS193P,
that's Developing Applications
for iOS, winter of 2017.
So today, our topic is to talk
about custom views, okay,
specifically the drawing
side of having custom views.
And this is gonna be a more
typical lecture than last
time because I'll be
doing some slides and
explaining the concepts
to you, and
then I'll go into a demo that
shows you how we do it all.
So what is a view?
A view is a subclass
of UIView,
which is in UIKit in iOS.
And all it does
is carve out or
represent a rectangular
area on screen.
And that rectangular area
defines a coordinate space
that we're gonna draw in and
that we're gonna get
multi-touch events
like pinches and
swipes and all that stuff.
So today,
I'm just gonna focus on the
drawing side of that all and
then we'll start talking about
the gestures on Wednesday.
So these views,
these little rectangle areas
are put on screen in
this hierarchical way.
And that just means that
the views have subviews
inside of them.
Now any given view can
only have one superview,
that's the view that
it's contained in.
But it can have any
number of subviews,
so views made out of it.
So for example,
on the calculator, we had for
example, stack view, okay.
It had a lot of subviews,
all the buttons that
we stacked in it.
In fact, some of the stack
views had other stack views as
their subviews.
And then those stack
views had more subviews,
which were buttons or
whatever, okay.
So that's how we build our
UI is this hierarchical
collection of these
rectangular areas.
Now, at the very, very, very
top there's a special UIView
called UIWindow class, we
don't deal with that in iOS.
In fact, the only time you
would ever do anything with
the UIWindow is if you were
building an app that maybe
projected to a projector.
So that you had two screens,
your device and
then maybe some
external projector or
something, then you might
care about UIWindow.
But otherwise,
it's all about UIView, okay?
All of our arrangement of
the screen is all about how we
arrange the UIViews.
Now this hierarchy, okay,
these rectangular areas inside
of rectangular areas,
is almost always built
in Interface Builder,
inside Xcode, okay?
That's how we built
the stack view stuff.
We dragged out a bunch
of buttons and
then we selected them and
said,
"Embed in Stack View." Well,
that wrapped it in there.
But we can also build that
hierarchy by dragging views
out of the utilities,
bottom of the utilities window
there, inside other views.
So you can drag,
do it by dragging-dropping
inside of other views.
It is possible to
do it in code but
usually we're doing
it graphically.
If you're doing it in code,
the two main methods
involved in building and
destroying this hierarchy,
are addSubview, okay,
addSubview, takes
a view as an argument.
You send it to the
"soon-to-be" superview of that
In other words,
you ask another view,
view.
please add this other view
as subview of yourself.
Now when you're doing the
opposite, taking some view out
of the hierarchy, you don't
send it to the superview.
You send it to
the actual view itself,
basically remove yourself
from this view hierarchy.
So you send
removeFromSuperview
to the actual view
you want removed.
Now where does this
hierarchy start?
I guess you could say
it starts in UIWindow.
But for our purposes, we don't
even pay attention to that.
It starts at
the top level view
in that scene in
Interface Builder.
The scene that's controlled by
our view controller, right?
That rectangular area
that we work in.
There's a top,
top level view that covers
the whole space up there.
And there is an important
instance variable,
property, in UIViewController.
Okay, so all subclasses
of UIViewController get
this property.
It's called view and it's
a UIView and a top level view.
And it's very important to
understand that in an MVC,
the controller has this,
always has this var which
points to the very top of that
view hierarchy in its scene.
This top level view is
important because for example,
when you rotate, it's the
thing whose bounds changes,
that top level view.
And you're gonna learn
a little later that when
the bounds of a view changes,
there's a mechanism for
offering all of its subviews
an opportunity to change.
So that's why when
we rotate device,
that top level view changes
from being tall and
thin to being wide and
less tall.
And that causes all
those stack views and
everything else to start
getting resized as well,
because they're all subviews
of this top level view, okay?
If you were going to add
views to the view hierarchy
programmatically rather
than dragging and
dropping them, then you would
need this view because it's
the top of the entire
view hierarchy.
And you would kinda
work your way down
to find out where you
want to put that view.
But we don't otherwise
actually look at this view
much because we usually
have outlets, rights?
IBOutlets--like the display
that points to the label--that
gives us access to that label.
That's all we want, so
we don't have to go looking
at the top level view and
looking all down the views,
okay?
So this is important
to know about but
surprisingly you don't
access it that much, okay.
This view is automatically
hooked up for you in
Interface Builder when you
drag out a View Controller.
It's just all
magically hooked up,
you don't have to
worry about that.
Okay, let's talk about
initialization of the UIView.
As usual, when you saw
the lecture from last time,
you probably realize, whoa,
initialization has a lot of
caveats when you're talking
about initializing a class,
Remember all those rules
I was going through?
right?
Required convenience and its
inheritance, all this stuff.
So we try to avoid
initializers generally as much
as we can by doing all
the things I talked
about on Wednesday,
like setting things equal or
even using lazy or
something like that.
But if you can't avoid it,
UIView has an interesting
initializer situation.
It has two initializers
that you have to deal with.
Okay, one of them, init, with
the frame is the argument, is
the one that you would call if
you're trying to create a view
in code, which you'll probably
never do in this class, okay?
Because you're
always gonna use or
do it in Interface Builder
with Xcode.
But, so that's the kind
of in-code one.
And init with
this coder thing,
which I'll talk about
right at the end of class,
but it's not important
to know early on.
That's the init that gets
called when your stuff come
outs of Interface Builder,
right?
When it comes from,
when you built in Xcode.
All the stuff that you're
building in Interface Builder
essentially gets coded,
that's what this coder
business is about.
Gets coded into an XML file,
kind of freeze dried.
And then when you run your
program, that XML file gets
loaded in and it's kind
of the instructions for
how to create all
those objects, okay?
And init with coder is
the initializer it uses
to recreate the view.
So if you have any code that
needs to go in an initializer,
like you need to initialize
some var in your UIView,
you have to do it like this.
Override both of these inits,
one of them is a required
init, the coder one.
And we create some other
method like this green setup
method I have.
And just call that method
from both of them.
That way you're guaranteed
that whether your custom view
is created in code or
created in Interface Builder,
it will get
initialized properly.
If you have vars that have to
be initialized, you may not be
able to use this mechanism
of course because you can't
call methods in yourself
until you're initialized.
So you might have to have
that var initialization be
somewhat duplicated there.
There's another alternative to
initialization though and this
is for any other object that
comes out of Interface Builder
which is called awakeFromNib.
Okay, awakeFromNib.
This is sent to every single
object that ever comes out
of Interface Builder file,
okay, that you edit
in the story board there
including views and
your View Controller for
that matter.
And so
the "Your object must be
completely initialized."
Those restrictions are not
satisfied by this.
But still you can put code in
there, you get, get going.
And we're gonna learn
all kinds of ways to do
initialization throughout
our system down the road,
but that's basically how
you initialize UIViews.
Okay so we're gonna
talk now about UIView
as this rectangular area
in which we're gonna draw.
And so to do that we need
talk about some types.
They're some very important
types that you need to know.
One of them is CGFloat.
So CGFloat is
a floating point value.
All of your coordinates that
you're gonna be drawing in
are all floating point values,
but they're not doubles,
they're not floats,
they're CGFloats.
So this is a type,
a real type that you
have to use all the time
when you're doing anything
with the drawing, okay?
CG stands for Core Graphics,
this is the "graphics
float" right here, okay?
There's also a CGPoint which
is just a struct with two
things in it, x and y,
they're both CGFloats, CGPoint
represents a point in your
coordinate system somewhere.
Again, floating
point coordinates.
There's also CGSize,
which represents an extent.
You know, a width and
a height, okay?
Only, it's just the struct,
with two CGFloats, width and
height, simple.
And there's CGRect, of course,
which is a rectangle.
It's a struct that has an
origin, which is CGPoint, and
an extent, which is a size.
So a rectangle
represents a size, okay?
So creating a CGRect--there's
actually quite a few
initializers for it.
You can create an origin and
size,
you can do an x y with height,
things like that.
And CGRect also has
a lot of really cool,
little convenience vars and
funcs and thing like that.
maxY, midY, those'll tell you
thing like where's the left
Like minX,
edge of your rect to the top
to the left or the bottom.
The middle points, etc.
There's also nice functions
like intersects other rect
will return whether the two
rectangles cross over.
And there's even
contains whether a point
is inside the rectangle, etc.
So there's quite
a few of these.
I can't put them all
on the slide, so
you're gonna wanna familiarize
yourselves with CGRect.
Because it probably has a lot
of things in there that
you would otherwise be
writing your own code to do.
Okay, so
now that we have those types,
those four types, we can start
talking about this coordinate
system that we're gonna
be doing our drawing in.
Now, the most important
thing to understand,
the simplest thing, is that
the origin of this coordinate
system is in the upper
left of the screen.
It's not Cartesian coordinates
which the origin would be in
the lower left of the screen
because in Cartesian
coordinates increasing
y means up, but
in this coordinate system
increasing y means going down,
down the screen, okay?
So very important
to understand that.
So you can see that point I
have up there, 500,35 that's
500 over and 35 down from
the origin upper left, okay?
Now, the units in here that
we're drawing are points.
Okay, be very careful that
you understand the unit
terminology here, okay?
It's in points, not pixels.
A pixel is like the smallest
possible little light
that can be turned
on on your screen.
Okay, now some devices
have a lot of pixels
per point--they're very dense.
And that's really great,
because if you're drawing
smooth curves--like
fonts are just
smooth curves being drawn--you
don't get jaggy edges,
because there's so
many tiny little points, okay?
But we can't make it, so that
we draw in the pixel space,
otherwise, on a very
dense pixel screen,
our image would
be really small.
And then, in an undense one,
it'd be really big,
because the pixels
are really big.
So we instead of
drawing in pixels,
we draw in points, okay?
This is the same point by
the way that is like the point
size of a font.
A 12 point font, same word
there, same point, okay?
So, you can find out though
how many pixels there are per
point, in other words how high
resolution your screen is,
with this var in UIView
called contentScaleFactor.
It's a CGFloat, it's either
gonna be one, two, or
three currently.
Like, the iPhone
7 Plus is three.
Three pixels per point
in each direction.
And the older like
iPhone 4s maybe?
Maybe all the way back
to the 4 would be one.
Okay, some of the older
iPads would be one.
The newer iPads would be two.
So, If you're doing anything
where you have to pay
Okay?
attention to the number
of pixels of points,
this is what you need.
Now the great thing is, most
of the time you don't care
because when you're using
iOS to draw with a font,
it's automatically gonna
do super smooth turns, and
you don't even have to know
what the scale factor is.
Even if you're just
drawing an arc,
it'll make sure you do as
little jaggies as possible.
So, you rarely
have to know this.
But actually, wake up.
You do need to know for
assignment three, okay?
So assignment three,
you will have to know this.
Alright, now.
The most important var in all
of UIView is this one: bounds.
And even in that
really important var,
really what you care
about is the size.
This is, in your drawing
coordinate system,
the space you have to draw in.
This is basically the size of
your view in your own drawing
coordinate system.
So any time you're
doing any drawing and
you wanna draw something
that's as wide as your view,
you're gonna use
bounds.size.width here.
And you're almost always gonna
have your bounds' origin be
(0, 0) so if you want put
something in upper left you're
gonna put it at (0,
0) or close to (0, 0).
So this rect, bounds,
is describing the area
have to draw in.
Now it's important because
you obviously want to,
depending on your size,
draw yourself appropriately.
And it's also important
because there are two other
vars that often get confused
by students with bounds, and
which are quite different:
that is frame and center.
So frame and
center have nothing to do
with where you're drawing,
that's bounds.
Frame and center is where
you are in your super view.
So here's a picture of
that frame and center.
So center is where your
center is in your superview's
coordinate system and frame is
a rectangle that completely
encases you in your
superview's coordinate system.
And you might think, well the
size of my frame is gonna be
exactly the same size as
my bounds size, right?
And the answer is no,
because views can be rotated.
And if you have ever rotated
a view like this green one,
Inside the code that's drawing
in View B, its bounds just
View B.
looks like a normal rectangle,
the fact that it's rotated,
it doesn't even
know it's rotated.
But if you look at the center
of it, or if you look at
the frame that encloses it,
look, it's not the same size.
It has to be bigger because,
to the superview, View A,
It's bigger.
View B kinda looks
like a diamond, right?
So it has to be bigger.
So the bottom line here, never
use frame or center to draw.
Frame and center are only
used to position you
in your super view.
Okay, you can use either one.
If you set the center,
it'll move the frame,
if you set the frame,
it'll adjust the center, okay.
They're tied together.
Okay.
How do we create views?
Okay, because I already told
you we don't really use
the initializer,
we don't, you know,
create them in code very much.
What we usually do
is we drag them out
Okay?
from the Object Palette in the
bottom of the utilities window
in Interface Builder.
But if I built a custom view,
Paul's view or
something, it's not going
to be in the palette, okay.
Xcode didn't ship with
my view in the palette.
So instead, there's a generic
view, just plain UIView, and
you're gonna drag that in.
But then, you're gonna inspect
it using the top half of
the utilities pane
on the right, right?
You're gonna inspect it and
change its class
to not be UIView.
It's gonna be your subclass
of UIView, so Paul view or
whatever, okay?
And this is a very
important step to remember.
When you create a custom view
and you drag it into your UI,
you have to change its class
to be your custom class.
And we'll see that in
the demo, how it works.
When you create it in code,
of course,
you're just doing
UIView(frame:),
and you provide the frame,
okay?
And that frame, remember,
what does it describe?
Describes where this view is
gonna be in its super view
when it gets added, that's
all the frame is doing, okay?
And you can create it with
UIView(), no arguments.
Then it will be zero width,
zero height, and
it'll be at zero, zero, so
you won't even see it, so.
But you could come
along later and
change its frame and/or its
center to move it around.
Here, it's a really
quick example,
how to create a view in code.
I'm gonna create a UILabel.
UILabel is just
a subclass of UIView.
And notice that on
the second line there,
I'm just saying label =
UILabel(frame:) of whatever.
So I'm giving it this frame,
20, 20, 150, right?
And then I'm setting
the text to "Hello".
Well, if I was doing this
code in a UIViewController,
then I could put it at
that top level view,
it'd look like that,
view.addSubview, okay?
And it would add the subview.
Custom views, so why do I
ever need a custom view?
Either I need to do
custom drawing or
I need to do custom
multi-touch input, okay?
Those are the reasons
that you're gonna
create a custom view.
And so we're gonna focus
on the drawing, and
the drawing is very,
very simple, okay?
There's this one method
that's called draw.
And it takes one argument,
which is a rect.
For historical reasons,
we sometimes call it drawrect,
but it's not actually
called drawrect anymore.
It's called draw, and
the argument is called rect.
And this draw is gonna be
sent to you by the system.
It's sent to your
UIView subclass,
you override it, and it gets
sent to you by the system when
the system wants you
to draw yourself.
This is the only way you
can draw in your view,
is to be asked by
the system to draw.
There is no other
way to draw in iOS.
So what's that
rectangle about?
That rectangle is some
sub-area in your bounds
that it wants you to draw.
Now, that's a performance
enhancement, because you can
ignore that and draw your
whole view, if you'd like.
But like in your assignment
three, you're probably gonna
wanna pay attention to
this rectangle because
your assignment three's draw
is gonna be pretty expensive,
so you wanna draw as
little as possible.
So that's what this draw is,
very simple,
it's just called by the
system, time for you to draw.
It's the only way to draw.
So it's really,
really easy to understand.
Never call this method, ever.
If you ever call this method,
it's wrong.
The system calls this method,
the system's the only one
who calls this method.
So what happens if
you need to draw?
Something changed,
and you wanna redraw.
You call one of these two
methods, setNeedsDisplay or
setNeedsDisplay with
the argument of a rect.
And that's telling the system,
hey, system,
my view needs to be redrawn.
Please ask me to redraw it.
And at some appropriate
time in the future,
it will ask you to redraw it.
But it knows better than you
when the best time to draw is,
believe me.
And the rect that you can
pass, that's just the rect
that's gonna be passed
onto your draw.
So setNeedsDisplay with
a rect is like an optimized
setNeedsDisplay.
It's like,
I need to be redrawn, but
only this part of me.
And you can send this to any
UIView, say, redraw this view.
Usually, views send it to
themselves though because
they're the ones who know best
when they need to be redrawn,
okay?
Alright.
So, how do I implement
this drawrect,
draw, draw with
a CGRect argument guy?
And the answer is,
you're gonna do it with paths.
You're gonna create paths, and
then you're going to stroke
them and fill them to make
shapes and things like that.
And then you're also gonna
use text and images.
So that's the primary way
that you're going to draw
in there, okay?
So we'll talk about text and
images in a minute.
Let's talk about the drawing
with the paths first.
There's really two
ways to do it.
One is, you can get
what's called a context,
a drawing context, and
I'll show you how to get it.
And then you can send messages
to that context like, move to
this point, draw a line to
here, add an arc over here,
put some text over here,
things like that, okay?
Actually, the text we're
gonna do in a different way,
but, so that's one way.
And then the other way is,
you can create a path object,
okay, using UIBezierPath, and
it's the same kind of thing.
But you're gonna create this
object that you're gonna tell
that object, okay, I want this
path to be moving to here, and
then a line here, and then
an arc over to here, okay?
So you create this path, and
then you send a message to
that path saying, okay,
stroke it.
So it's a subtle difference,
but you'll see.
We're gonna focus mainly
on the UIBezierPath way,
because it's kind of
a little simpler.
So let's understand
the concepts here of
Core Graphics, that's what the
CG is that you're seeing in
all the places here.
And the number one thing
about Core Graphics is,
we need a context.
And that context might be a
drawing context for on-screen,
it might be a printing
context if we're printing,
might be a context of drawing
to an off-screen bitmap, etc.
The one you care about is
obviously the context to
draw in your drawrect.
And you get that by
calling this function.
This is just a Swift function,
it's not on a class or
anything.
UIGraphicsGetCurrentContext(),
and
that's going to get you
a context that you can then
tell it to create a path by
moving and all that stuff.
Which is what you do then,
you create these paths out of
lines and arcs and
things like that.
Then you set drawing
attributes in the context,
like the colors you wanna use,
the fonts if you're doing
text, line widths,
those kinds of things.
You set those all up, and
then you stroke and fill.
And that's it, stroking and
filling are actually the only
two directives that actually
cause something to
happen on screen.
But keep in mind that, like,
a font is basically just a
really exquisite path filled,
okay, or stroked and filled.
So you can do a lot with
stroking and filling.
So UIBezierPath kinda
encapsulates all of those
Core Graphics concepts
into an object.
And so I have an example here
to show you how I would use
UIBezierPath to draw
a triangle on screen.
First, I'm gonna create
the path by just saying,
path = UIBezierPath().
There are other
initializers for it,
which we'll see in the demo.
But this one just creates
a blank path to start.
Then, you move around
with the path.
So like I can say,
move to, which (80,
50) is like halfway across
this, this little screen.
This is small screen,
let's say, 160 points wide.
80 and then 50 down, okay?
Then I'm gonna add a line down
to 140, 50, see that, okay?
Then I'm gonna add
another line over to 10,
off to the left,
I'm still 150 down.
Then I'm gonna close the path,
okay, using close, and
that just closes it
back to the start.
So look, I made a triangle,
okay, really easy.
Now, the only thing is,
all this code right here would
actually draw, instead of
that triangle right there,
would draw this: nothing.
You would see no drawing with
that code because we haven't
stroked or filled it.
The stroking and
filling is what draws.
So how do we do
the stroking and fill?
Well, we need to set the
colors that we wanna fill and
stroke with.
But here, I'm taking green and
sending it
the message setFill.
So you actually set
your color to fill with
by sending a message
to a color.
You get a color, and
you send it a message,
set that as my fill color.
And the same thing
with a stroke,
set it as a stroke color.
So I set my stroke color to
red, my fill color to green.
But when I'm talking about
attributes like line width,
I send that to the path,
to the UIBezierPath.
Set your line width to three,
okay, so I do that.
Now, if I say path.fill,
now I get a green triangle.
Because my fill
color was green,
and it takes that path and
it fills it in.
That's what fill does.
And similarly,
if I say path.stroke,
I get a red line around.
Because the path that I took
to get around there gets
stroked with a three-point
wide red line.
So that's it,
that's quite simple actually.
That's how we draw.
And, UIBezierPath also knows
how to draw a lot of common
Okay?
shapes, like rounded
rectangles, and ovals, and
things like that, so you
should familiarize yourself
with UIBezierPath's API,
of course.
Another cool thing you can
do with UIBezierPath is you
create a path like
that triangle, and
you can clip all your
drawings to that path.
So you could draw this
elaborate picture that only
show the part that shows
through that triangle,
if you take that triangle
path that we just created and
say add clip to it.
Because after that,
all drawing is only gonna
show up inside that triangle,
you can make some pretty
cool effects by doing it.
which is kinda cool,
The UIBezierPath
also knows how to,
it has this method
contains that will,
tell you whether a point
is inside the path.
So that's good if you want to
do some touch thing or people
are touching on something and
you wanna do hit detection,
basically, what
they're touching on.
All right, and there's tons of
other stuff in UIBezierPath,
don't have time to cover it,
you should look it up.
Okay, UIColor.
So UIColor, really simple.
Okay, there's some common
colors like green, red,
yellow, purple.
Those have type
methods on UIColor.
Remember, type methods,
static methods?
They're on the type.
You don't need
an instance of it.
So that's like UIColor.green.
But there's also initializers
that let you create colors
from RGB, red, green, blue, or
HSB, that's hue, saturation,
You can even create a color
that's made from a pattern.
brightness.
So that when you draw
with that color,
it's drawing in a pattern.
Okay, like a really
thick line,
we'd actually be showing
the details of a pattern,
which is kind of fun,
using UIImage,
which I'll talk about
in a little bit.
Of course, all UIViews
have a background color.
We saw this when we did our
buttons in the calculator,
we made the background color
of a lot of our buttons be
light gray, and I'm sure in
the homework assignments
you made it other colors.
Okay, that's just
a var on UIView,
that button inherited
from UIView.
And you can set it to
any UIColor you want.
Now, an interesting thing
about colors though is that
they can be transparent, or
even semi-transparent, okay?
And they are done,
you specify that with alpha.
How many people here
know what alpha
is when it comes to graphics?
Okay, so hardly anybody.
So alpha is just a value
between 0 and 1, where 0 means
fully transparent and
1 is fully opaque.
So if you have a color
like a triangle and
you fill it with green,
then if it's fully opaque,
you can't see anything
behind that triangle.
But if it were 50%, 0.5 alpha,
then you'd be able
to see the green but
you'd also be able to see the
things behind it a little bit.
50% kinda, okay?
If it was zero,
you wouldn't see any
green because it would
be fully transparent.
You'd be looking all
the way through it, so
you wouldn't see any green,
okay?
So, all that you can put
anywhere in that range, and
the way you create a
transparent color is by taking
a opaque color and saying,
withAlphaComponent,
whatever alpha you
want between 0 and 1.
Okay?
And that gives you
a transparent or
semi-transparent version
of the color.
And you can draw with that.
However, if you draw with
transparency in your UIView,
you must set this
var on your UIView.
This is just a var
in UIView to false.
Okay?
Because views assume that
they're fully opaque, okay?
And that's performance
enhancement.
It turns out drawing
with transparency,
as you might imagine, takes
a little bit of CPU power
to figure out which pixels
show through and all that.
So, by default, it assumes
you're drawing fully opaque.
So if you wanna draw
with transparency,
don't forget to set
opaque here to false.
By the way, you can make your
entire view semi-transparent
by setting its alpha.
So this is a var,
not in color,
this is a var in UIView.
You can say, alpha 0.5,
in your entire view will
be 50% see-through.
And that would work
with a button or
anything because those
are just UIViews.
Alright?
What happens when
views overlap and
we have transparency
in the views?
Well, then that subviews
that we're talking about,
all the subviews of a view
starts to matter in the order.
So the first thing
in the subview,
subview sub zero, that's
all the way in the back.
And then everything else
is in the order in front of
it, okay?
And so, any transparency
that's going on is things
stacked up in that order, and
you're looking down through
the transparency, all
the way up to subview zero,
so which is in the back, okay?
You can also completely
hide a view.
This is very similar--almost
identical to--saying
alpha equals zero.
Which will just make the view
not even appear, but
it will be still in
the view hierarchy.
It will be still in
its superview and
its subviews will still
be subviews of it, but
it all will be
completely hidden.
And why would you
wanna do this?
Maybe you have some UI where
you don't wanna show a button
until the user has entered
some other field or
something like that.
But you wanna make room for
the button.
You want it to be
ready to appear, so
you leave it in the view
hierarchy, but hidden.
Okay?
Alright,
let's talk about drawing text.
How do we draw text?
Well, one way to draw text
you already know is UILabel.
You could just create a
UILabel and make it a subview
of your view and bingo, you
got some text in your view.
And now,
the only problem with that is,
you're drawing in your draw,
your drawRect thing,
you're drawing in there.
And you have to make sure you
drew, if you're drawing around
the text that it all lined
up with your subviews.
So sometimes you wanna
draw in drawRect, right?
You want to actually
draw in there.
And the way you do that
is with a class called
NSAttributedString, okay?
So NSAttributedString
is not a string.
It's not related in any way
actually to string, and
it's not even an NSString
which is the old Objective-C
style string that was
indexed by ints where
the Swift's one is indexed by
string.index, unfortunately.
It's neither of those,
it's its own thing.
Okay?
It's very closely
aligned to old NSString,
not as closely aligned
to the modern string.
But anyway, what an attributed
string is it's a string,
you can make it out of
a string or an NSString.
And those characters have
attributes, colors and
fonts and
things like that, okay?
And it's very simple,
you create one of
these strings and
you just send it to message
draw at and it will draw
that string at that point
at its upper left corner.
Then you can even find out
the size it's going to need to
Okay?
draw it by sending the message
size to an attributed string.
Okay?
Now one thing that's
kind of bummer about
attributed string,
it's really an old style API,
var and let don't even work
to make it mutable or not.
So if you want a mutable
attributed string, attributed
string where you're gonna
change its attributes and
change its text, you need to
have a different class called
NSMutableAttributedString.
So things like set attributes,
and things of that,
don't work on
an attributed string.
You have a mutable
attributed string.
Now, you can, if you have an
attributed string, mutable or
not, you can get back
the string that's in it
as a string object using
the var string, or
mutable string in
a mutable case.
That's kinda
confusing because,
of course, you're used to var
and let being how a string is
mutable or not, but that's how
you can get the string back.
But let's talk about how
you set the attributes.
So you set the attributes just
by passing in this dictionary,
called attributes there.
You can either set attributes
or add attributes to what's
already there, and
this dictionary, String:Any,
the string is just a key like
this is telling you what
the attribute is, like it's a
font, or a color, or whatever.
And then the Any is,
it might be a font,
it might be a color,
depends on what the key is,
that's why it's an Any there,
because it can be
all kinds of things.
And really important to
notice here is the range.
You see that range?
It's not range that I
talked to you on Wednesday,
it's NSRange.
NSRange is an integer indexed
range into that string,
that attributed string.
Old style integer,
not string.index.
So this makes for a lot of
trouble when you're using
attributed string
in the Swift world.
And my recommendation to you
is that you use this method or
this var rather on
String called utf16.
utf16 will give you
back what's called
a String.UTF16View.
That is a collection of the
characters, it's not really
a collection like characters
is, but it is a representation
of the string as distinct
16-bit Unicode characters.
Which is much more aligned,
in fact I think it's exactly
aligned, to what
NSString does.
The only problem is,
that thing that it gets,
that comes back, is still
indexed by String.Index.
So you have to say what's the
startIndex, offset by five,
that kind of business to
move around in there.
And plus, you can't pass
a range of String.Index into
this setAttribute.
So you have to kinda
convert from String.Index,
how much you've advanced over,
to an integer when you
make these NSRanges.
So, I'm sorry to
say it's difficult.
I'm not gonna actually
ask you to do that,
this in the homework.
Partially because it, it's
kind of a pain in the neck.
And I don't want you to
spend your valuable homework
time working on it.
But just know,
if you start using this,
that you're gonna have this
unfortunate disconnect.
And I keep hoping every
time iOS comes out,
they'll come out with an
attributed string, not NS, but
attributed string,
that's matched up with string.
But they haven't done it yet.
It's pretty complicated to do,
I can imagine, so.
So what are some of these
attributes that you can set?
So there's things like
NSForegroundColorAttributeN-
ame, that's how you set
the color of the text.
There's also
NSBackgroundColorAttributeName
which, fonts have foregrounds
and backgrounds, but
don't worry about
that too much.
NSStrokeWidth so
you can draw your characters
really thick or thin.
NSFontAttributeName, where
you can provide a font.
And there's about 15 others,
and you can go look in the
documentation for all of them.
But speaking of fonts,
if you wanna set the font
you're gonna draw with,
how do you do that?
Well, fonts are super
important in iOS.
Never underestimate the power
of a font in building
a cool UI.
Look at all these UIs.
Look at how important
the choice of font, size,
position, all that stuff is.
So, how do we get a good font
so that our UI will look good?
Well, we're gonna use this
very important static
method in UIFont.
So you send this to UIFont,
the class,
called preferredFont
forTextStyle, okay?
And so you can specify the
text style, which is kind of
like, what's the environment
you're gonna use this text,
what kinda text is it?
And so there's about eight or
so of them.
But three of them
are like a headline.
This is gonna be a headline.
So that's gonna be a bolder
font, a little larger maybe.
Then body font, that's like,
this is the user's data.
So in a Mail message,
this would be the message
they're actually typing
maybe--although it's
probably a multi-font.
But, and then footnote would
just be a small little text,
you see, from the bottom?
So I really encourage you
when you're using a font,
try to find a text style
that will work, okay?
Because it's gonna
be in sync and
compatible with all
the other apps,
because they're using
these preferred fonts.
And also, by the way,
if a user goes in Settings and
sets their font size
to be really large,
these will automatically
get larger, okay?
And, hopefully, if you have
your Auto-Layout working,
everything will expand or
contract properly, okay?
There's also system fonts.
Don't get confused between
the preferred fonts and
system fonts.
Preferred fonts are for
the user's content.
So, that's
the difference there.
Now, most of this stuff,
again,
you're not even
gonna set in code.
You're gonna set it in
Interface Builder in
the little Inspector window,
right?
You're gonna be setting,
both preferred fonts and
system fonts can be set there.
If you wanna use a specific
font like Helvetica Bold 13
point, you can do that.
I don't recommend it,
but UIFontDescriptor is
an important class to know
It's how you describe
that font that you want,
for that.
that special font.
So, you know, some apps,
typography is what they do.
And so they need to be
able to do specific fonts.
Alright, so that's text.
How about drawing images?
So images, again, you,
we have a thing like UILabel.
It's called UIImageView.
And you could just make
an image be a subview of
your view if you wanted to
have an image in there.
But, again, sometimes you
wanna be able to control that
in your draw, your drawRect.
And we do that with
the UIImage object, okay?
I already showed you actually
when I was talking about
failable initializers
how to create a UIImage.
You just put it in
your xcassets file
in Interface Builder.
And then you say UIImage
named, and it gets it by name.
And if it can't find it,
it returns nil.
So that's the number one way
you're gonna get an image into
your app is put
it in xcassets.
But there are other
ways to do it.
You can get it from a file,
like if you had a .jpg file.
Of course, I haven't shown
you how to get files.
So you don't know
how to do that yet.
But, you can do it that way.
And you can also get it just
from raw data, raw jpg data or
something that you got over
the Internet or from a URL or
something, you can do that.
You can even do it by drawing
with all those path things.
You can use this
UIGraphicsBeginImageContext
for a certain size region.
And then you can just
use UIBezierpath draw or
get graphics context,
whatever, draw in there.
And then there's
an EndImageContext.
And it'll capture it and
create a little image for you.
So that's another
way to do it.
So once you have an image,
okay, that you got from any of
these sources, you can just
draw it inside your drawRect
by saying draw atPoint or
draw inRect.
Or actually, I think that's
probably drawAt space point,
not atPoint:.
And drawIn space rect and
drawAsPatternIn space rect.
Those do kind of what
you would think, right?
draw atPoint draws it where
that's the upper left hand
corner, it draws it
in its natural size.
draw inRect is going to
scale it to fit inside
the rectangle
that you provide.
And drawAsPattern
is gonna tile it.
So presumably that's
a small image and
you're drawing a texture or
something.
And it's gonna
repeat it over and
over to fill the rectangle,
okay?
I'll fix this slide and
repost it.
Alright, one thing to be
careful of with UIView.
When UIView changes size,
you do not get asked
to redraw by default.
What it does is, believe it or
not, takes what you've drawn,
grabs the pixels, and
stretches them to
fit the new bounds.
Okay, now, this is often
not what you want.
Often, what you want is,
okay, if my bounds change,
ask me to redraw again
in my new bounds, okay?
So how is this controlled?
It's controlled via this var
in UIView called contentMode.
And the contentMode can be
things like left, right, top,
bottom, topRight, topLeft.
That's basically saying,
take my bits and
shove them up into
the left corner you know,
one of these spots,
center or right.
Don't touch,
don't do anything with them,
just move them in
the new bounds.
Well, that's likely to cut off
what you've drawn or something
like that depending on how
much the bounds have changed.
Like when you rotate,
you know,
the bounds changes
quite a bit.
There's also the scaling ones.
And this is the default,
scaleToFill.
And that says, take my bits
and take my new bounds and
scale it to fill.
I can preserve the aspect
ratio if I want.
Although, again,
that's probably gonna
cut something off.
But the real one that
you want is redraw.
If you set your
contentMode to be .redraw,
then when your bounds change,
your draw is gonna be
called--your drawRect,
draw with the rect argument.
So in your assignment three,
you're gonna wanna do this.
You can actually do this,
you can do it in code
by setting that var.
But you can also do it in
Interface Builder, okay?
In the Utilities window,
in the Inspector preview.
Just, I think it's the very
top one, contentMode.
All right, so I'm, I'm gonna
be leaving the slides here so
I will tell you
what's coming up.
I'm gonna do this demo right
now where I'm gonna do
a custom view, a FaceView,
a UIView that draws a face.
And then Wednesday,
I'm gonna talk about gestures.
We'll add some gestures
to control our face.
And I'm gonna start talking
about multiple MVCs,
I'll finish up with
multiple MVCs next week.
Your assignment three requires
you to do multiple MVCs, so
I'm not going to make it due
until a week from next Monday,
because you'll need
next Monday's lecture.
However, I'll probably ship
the assignment, the write-up,
on Wednesday, because a big
part of that assignment
is drawing your own custom
view and you'll certainly know
everything you need to know
to do that right off the bat.
So you can kind of get
started on the view, and
then next Monday, you can
start doing the multiple MVCs.
And you'll still have a full
week until the next Monday,
to get that done, alright.
No Friday section this week.
Okay, so as with most
demos in this course,
I'm going to start
from scratch, okay.
We're going to do
a completely new app.
No more calculator in here.
So I could click on here
to open my calculator.
But instead, I'm gonna go back
here to Create a new project.
Okay, it's gonna be
Single View Application,
as I told you they
all would be.
I'm gonna call this
one FaceIt, okay.
And it's gonna start out
just drawing a face, but
it's gonna do much
more eventually.
And, still no core data or
testing stuff yet, so
I'm just gonna do FaceIt here.
It's gonna say where
do you want it?
I'm gonna put it in the same
place the calculator is,
in my Developer.
I'm not gonna be using SCM.
But of course,
those of you come who
came to Friday section,
you'll know how to use that.
And here is my new app here.
And I'm also going to
do my standard thing,
where I'm gonna take these
supporting files and
move them out of our way.
So they don't distract
us every time we look at
the Navigator here.
Because we don't need
those for this demo.
So just like every other thing
we've done, we have a view.
Here's our story
board with our view.
Oops, not that small.
And of course,
we have our controller.
And I'm gonna delete this
out of the controller,
as usual here.
And this time, we're going
to start right off here
by building a custom UIView,
custom UIView subclass.
Now, the way we do that
is the saw way we built
the CalculatorBrain.
We go here, new file, right.
That's how we add new
files to our project.
But this time, for
CalculatorBrain we chose Swift
File because it, you know,
it wasn't a UI thing.
It didn't inherit
from any iOS class.
But now we're gonna choose
Cocoa Touch Class, because
it's gonna be a subclass of
a Cocoa Touch UIKit class.
So we click that.
It says, what do you want
it to be a subclass of?
And we want UIView, but you
can see there's other things.
UIViewController, and
other things that we'll
learn later in the quarter.
But this is
a subclass of UIView.
I'm gonna call it FaceView,
because it's a view
that draws a face.
Okay, it's a good name.
Alright, so we click here.
It says,
where do you wanna put it?
We usually wanna be very
careful to put it in the same
place as everything else is.
You don't want it in
Supporting Files, and
you don't want it at this top
level, the project level.
You want it inside
this folder right here,
that has all your stuff in it.
So we'll do that.
Alright, so
here's our FaceView.
And you can see right off the
bat in FaceView, we get this.
Which is our draw, okay,
the draw with the rect.
Notice that it is
commented out.
And that's because for
performance reasons, iOS
doesn't want to ask views that
don't actually do any drawing,
to draw.
Because it has to keep
a backing store for
them, and there's memory
stores and all this stuff.
So by default this
comes commented out.
But of course,
our FaceView is going to draw.
It's going to draw a face.
So we're going to
un-comment it out.
Okay, now we have
a FaceView here,
it doesn't draw anything.
But I actually wanna briefly
go back to our storyboard, and
put a FaceView in
the storyboard.
And it's really simple but
I want to show it to you.
if we go down to the Object
Palette at the bottom here,
And again,
where we got our buttons and
labels, you know I could
search here forever.
There's no FaceView in here.
But I can go down towards
the bottom here, and
you will see this one.
It's actually almost at
the very bottom, it's View.
See, it represents a
rectangular region which draws
and receives events,
as promised.
And so I can pick this
guy up and drag him out.
Okay, and drop him here
inside this view controller.
And remember that the top
level view in this view
controller is
a var called view.
Okay, a very important var.
Now, I want this view to
fill the whole space.
So I'm actually gonna use
the blue dash lines to
make this thing fit the entire
space, you see that?
Now, well, I also want to
do the Ctrl-dragging to
the edges that we did in
calculator, remember that?
But it's actually kind of hard
to do this because I want it
all the way to the edges.
But since I used the blue
lines, I can use a really cool
feature which is down here,
this button.
You see this button in
the lower right here?
It says
Resolve Auto Layout Issues.
If you click that,
one of the choices is to Reset
to Suggested Constraints.
So that is the system saying,
I'll make your constraints for
you based on what you
did with the blue lines.
So I'm gonna look
at your blue lines.
Since I used blue lines
all at the edges,
if I say Reset to
Suggested Constraints,
it's gonna hook those
things to the edges.
Because that's what
it looked I wanted.
Now I can double-check what it
gave me by clicking here on
the Size Inspector.
And if you look down
towards the bottom of
the Size Inspector, you can
see all your constraints.
And look at that, perfect
Trailing Space to Superview,
leading space here.
Excellent, all
exactly what I want.
So here, I've gotten all my
Auto-Layout with one click.
And that's going to be
possible to do quite a bit.
If you use those
blue lines and
you say Reset to
Suggested Constraints,
often it'll at
least get close.
And then you can kinda tweak
the ones it didn't get right.
Now, the other crucial
thing I have to do here
is that this is
currently a UIView.
If I go over here to
this inspector here,
which is the Identity
Inspector, you can see that
the class of the selected
thing is UIView.
So no matter what
I put in my draw,
it would never be called.
Because this is not
a FaceView, it's a UIView.
But I can just click here, and
go down and choose FaceView.
And now I've made
this a FaceView.
all the code I put in my draw
is going to draw in here.
So now,
And that's it,
that's all I need to do to
put a custom view into my UI.
It's very common to want
to put a custom view
in, in the UI.
So that's why it's so
simple to do.
Now all we need to do
here is in our FaceView,
write the code that
draws--draws our face.
So what are we gonna
do to draw a face?
Well, I'm just gonna draw the
kind of emoji face, this round
circle for a head, two
round eyes, a little smile.
Okay, a very simple face.
And, let's start by drawing
the skull of our face, the,
kind of the head of this face.
And I just start doing
that in draw here.
I'm going to use
UIBezierPath to do all this.
So I don't actually even
need to get the context.
That UI get graphics, get
context, don't even do that.
Just use UIBezierPath
automatically
knows what context you're in.
So you don't have
to do any of that.
So what do I need
to do though?
I need to kind of think
of how big my face is.
I want my face, if I'm in
portrait or landscape, I also
want my face to kind of be
the smaller of the two sides,
the height or the width.
You know what I mean?
Because I always want the face
to fully fit in there.
So I'm going to let my
skullRadius, so that's gonna
be the radius of my skull,
okay, equal the minimum.
And there's this nice min,
you see that min
function right there?
It's generic-typed
like an array.
Array of T, so that's the T.
It will take any type.
And it will compare
two things, and
return the one
that's the lowest.
So I'm going to get
the minimum of my bound,
bounds.size.width and
my bounds.size.height.
And then I'm going to divide
it by 2, because it's radius,
not diameter.
So now,
see what I'm doing here?
I'm just making it so that my
radius of my skull will be
smaller of the width or
height.
And then, what about where
I want the skull to be?
Well, I want it to be
right in the center.
So can I say, let
skullCenter equal my center?
Okay, that's a method,
can I say that?
That's a var,
anything wrong with that?
No, I see shaking heads--why
not, what's wrong with that?
Yeah?
He says because it'll
start from the top left.
Not quite.
Anyone else wanna take
a stab at this one?
It's because center, while it
is the center of this view,
it's in the wrong
coordinate system.
This center is in my
superview's coordinate system
and I'm in draw.
I need to be in my
coordinate system.
So there's actually two
things I can do here.
One I could use this cool
function in view called
convert which will
convert a point
from one coordinate
system to another.
So I can go down
to this one okay,
convert CGPoint from view, and
I could convert this point
center from my superview.
Okay, so just using
center I can convert it.
That would be fine, because
I've converted it from one
coordinate system,
my superviews, to mine.
That's probably a little,
someone reading
this code is like,
hm, why are they doing that?
A simpler way to do it is
probably just to create
a point, a CGPoint, that is
my bounds midX, that's my
middle X, see, that's a rect
thing, and my bounds midY.
Okay.
So I'm just creating
the point that is the center,
That makes sense?
much more
straightforwardly there.
All right, so now I have
my radius and the center.
Now I need to draw a circle.
So how do I draw a circle?
I'm gonna do that
with UIBezierPath.
So I'm gonna say let path
equal a UIBezierPath.
Now, when we look at
the constructors for
UIBezierPath here you can
see that we can draw an arc.
Which is actually what
I'm going to use.
We could draw an oval,
which would be cool,
except the argument is a rect,
and
I have the center and
the radius.
So I can't, I don't
really want to use oval.
We could draw a rectangle.
I want a circle,
so that's no good.
Or a rounded rect.
I actually want the circle,
not a rectangle of any kind,
okay?
So I'm gonna use this one
right here which draws an arc.
It just takes a center point
and it draws a sweeping arc.
And I'm gonna draw this
arc all the way around
to make a circle, okay?
So how does that work?
Here, I'm gonna make
some more space.
All right, so it wants to
know the center of the arc.
Well, that's my skull center,
right?
It wants to know the radius
of the arc, well,
that's my skullRadius,
this easy.
It wants to know
the start angle.
So that's the angle that
it's gonna start sweeping.
I'm gonna choose 0,
the angle 0 is straight
out to your right.
Okay, so if you're
looking at the screen,
to the right straight across,
that's 0.
And it's in radians,
how many people know what
radians are to measure angle?
Okay most of you.
So radians instead of degrees,
we measure how much we're
going up by radians.
Radians go from zero all
the way around to two pi.
Around the circle.
Start at zero and then it
will go around, pi over two,
pi, you know,
then pi is 180 degrees and
then around to two
pi is 360 degrees.
So it's in radians, so this
end angle has to be in radians
and I wanna go all
the way around.
So it's 2 times pi.
We know that Double.pi is pi.
And then clockwise is whether
I'm gonna draw the arc around
clockwise or the other way.
It doesn't matter because I'm
going all the way around to
get back to the start anyway.
So I'll just say false.
There you go,
counter-clockwise.
Now, I got a warning here,
an error.
Let's look at that error.
What does it say, it says
the binary operator* (and is
pointing to this little
multiplier right here) cannot
be applied to 'Int' and
'Double'.
Why is it saying that?
These arguments
to UIBezierPath,
the floating point arguments
like a startAngle and
endAngle, what type do you
think it's supposed to be?
No one?
I hear it being whispered,
yes, CGFloat.
All drawing has to be CGFloat.
So is Double.pi,
is that a CG float?
No, it's a double.
Is two a CGFloat?
Well it might be.
But Swift would have to
infer that it's a CGFloat.
And right now Swift is
confused about what that's
supposed to be because it
knows this argument is
supposed to be a CGFloat, but
the thing you're multiplying
it by is a Double.
So Swift doesn't know
what to infer here.
Doesn't know whether to
refer that to as a Double or
a CGFloat.
So the fix here, luckily,
CGFloat has a pi.
Just like double does.
Now, everybody's happy,
because Swift knows how to
interpret this
literal as a CGFloat.
And this argument to
the endAngle is now a CGFloat.
So now everybody's happy.
It's only complained that
we don't use path yet.
Okay?
Excellent, so now we got
this arc going all around.
Let's set something about the
path like it's line width for
example, we'll set a nice,
fairly thick line,
five points wide,
that's what that means,
five point zero,
five points wide.
And then let's set the color.
So I'm gonna get UIColor,
let's say, blue color and
we'll say set, and by the way
there's setFill and setStroke.
There's also just set.
Set sets both the fill and
the stroke.
Here we only need to set
the stroke color, but
I'll just say set so
that you learn about that one.
And now I can just say
path stroke okay and
it's going to
stroke that path.
So let's see what
this looks like.
Let's go do iPhone 7 here.
So hopefully this is
gonna draw our skull.
There we go, a skull.
Whoo, first time, excellent.
Okay, now I don't like
the look of that very
much because it goes all
the way to the edges and
with a thick line that's
actually cut off a little bit.
So I want to move that in
a little bit so we'll do that.
Let's rotate and
go from portrait to landscape.
Not good, not good.
Okay, why is that happening?
That it's doing that.
Well, that's that content
mode thing I was
talking about, right?
It's not calling my draw
when it goes to this other
bound size right there, so
it's just scaling the bits.
So let's fix both
of those things,
let's make it go in a little
bit, and let's fix those bits.
To fix the bits, we're
just gonna go back to our
storyboard, and
click on our view right here.
Lets get rid of this.
Okay, click on our View,
and go over to Utilities.
Inspect this with the
Attributes Inspector and look,
the very first one,
Content Mode, Scales to Fill.
Every time the bounds change
it's scales to bits to fill
and we want Redraw.
We could also probably
use Center, but
I actually want Redraw because
if my bounds got smaller for
example, I'd wanna
draw my face smaller.
I wouldn't want
to get cut off.
Okay, so there's Redraw.
That fixed that one,
that was easy to fix.
What about making this
thing kinda smaller?
To do that, I'm actually gonna
create a var called scale.
And it's a drawing thing so
it's a CGFloat.
And I'm going to set it
to let's say 0.9 and
that's going to mean 90%.
All I'm going to do
is take my radius and
multiply it by that scale.
So by multiplying
my radius by 0.9 or
90% it should zoom move
it in a little bit right.
Kind of in from
the edges by 90%.
So let's see if both
those things got fixed.
So the 90% worked.
Clearly, it's in 90% and
the rotation works also.
So we're off to
a good start here,
things seem to be
working just fine.
Alright, so, what's
the next thing we wanna do?
Well, we wanna draw eyes and
a mouth and things like that,
I wanna start thinking
a little bit about my
internal architecture.
And I'm kinda liking the idea
of having some private funcs,
like give me the path for
the skull.
And have that return
a UIBezierPath that
I can then stroke.
And then I'll have the same
thing, give me the path for
the eye, give me a path for
the mouth,
you see what I mean?
I'll get all these.
And so I can just take
this code down here
that creates this path for
the skull and
I'll just put it up here and
I'll just return this path.
And then, down here, instead
of saying paths.stroke,
I'll say
pathForSkull().stroke().
Do you see that?
Now, another thing is
the skullRadius and
the skullCenter, I want all
the other things like the eyes
and the mouth to all
be relative to that.
So if I make my skull small I
need the eyes to get smaller,
the mouth to get smaller,
everything to move in.
So I'm gonna use
these two guys,
I'm gonna make them instead of
being local variables in draw,
I'm gonna move them out and
make them be private vars.
And in specific they're gonna
be private computed vars.
So I'm just gonna take
what they were before and
I'm just gonna return them so
that no matter what my
bounds is, at any given time,
skullRadius,
that var--which of course we
have to type, so CGFloat--that
skullRadius is always going
to match by bounds, okay?
Because every time I ask for
it,
I'm gonna recompute it
using this little function.
And same thing
with skullCenter,
I'm gonna say private
var skullCenter,
which is also a CGFloat,
no this one is a CG point, and
it's going to be computed.
Now, one thing
you noticed here,
I don't remember if I covered
this in the other lecture but
you notice,
I'm not saying get here.
See, I'm not putting get and
set.
Well, I'm not putting set
because you can't set
the skull center.
Skull center is always
the center of my bounds so
I can't set it.
And then if you
have only a get,
turns out you don't
need the get.
Because it's kinda redundant.
So you get this kinda
nicer looking code here.
So now we have skullRadius and
skullCenter available
to all of our methods.
And so all our other paths,
like path for eye and
all that stuff can use them.
So let's get started on those.
Let's do path for
eye, how about that.
So in a private func,
pathForEye.
Now actually,
probably the path for the eye
is almost the same for the
left eye and the right eye.
So I'm gonna create a little
type here called Eye which
is just gonna be
a little enum.
And it's gonna just be
the left and right eye, so
private enum Eye.
Let's see Eye is case
left case right, okay.
So I mean it's perfectly
fine to use an enum
just to represent
something simple like this.
You don't have to always
be doing methods and
associated values.
We don't have any
associated values here.
We're just representing it as
a way to specify in this API,
which eye we want the path,
the UIBezierPath, for.
So, by the way, also I
wanna have some constants
that tell me where the eye is
relative to the center and
where the mouth is and
how big the eyes are.
So to save a little bit of
time here, I'm going to just
type those in at the bottom
here real quick.
Look how fast I typed them in.
This is, by the way, how we do
constants in swift we just
create a struct and we make
static lets on it which
are all of our constants and
what's really cool about this,
one it groups them together.
Like here I have Ratios,
it's all the ratios between
the skull radius and all these
things I want to do like
the eye offset and the mouth.
Also it types them.
You see these
are typed constants.
I can put the type in there,
because they're just vars,
they're static vars
on this struct.
Okay.
We don't have any storage
in this struct.
Doesn't have any methods.
It just is only used for
constants here.
Now, I'm gonna use these
constants down here, and
I'm gonna use
the skull radius and
center up here to calculate
the path for the eye.
So how am I gonna do that?
First I need
the center of the eye.
Now, I'm gonna create
a function to calculate
the center of the eye.
But I only need it for
pathForEye.
So I'm actually gonna put
it inside pathForEye.
So I'm gonna create
a function here, centerOfEye.
Just gonna type it in quick
here to save some time.
I'll go through it though.
And centerOfEye, look how
it's inside pathForEye.
And that's perfectly legal,
some of you are probably using
that strategy in
your assignment two.
I think I mentioned it in
a hint, that you can do it.
And all it does is, it keeps
centerOfEye inside here,
because it's not
needed anywhere else.
So now, readers of my code
don't have to worry about this
thing being called
somewhere else, and
what it's semantics
might be out there.
They already know that it's
only used in this nice,
little space right here, so
it's kind of a nice way to
arrange your code to make
it a little more readable.
So how does centerOfEye work?
Well it takes the eye, and
it just gets the eye offset by
taking the skull radius and
dividing it by one
of those constants,
the ratio between the skull
radius to the eye offset,
that's how much it's
gonna offset the eye.
Now I'm gonna offset the eye
the same amount up as I do
to the sides.
So the line between
the nose of our face, and
the two eyes is gonna be
equilateral triangles, or no,
not quite equilaterals.
It can be a little wider, but
the same distance going up as
it is going out to the sides.
I'm gonna start with the
eyeCenter being in the center.
And then,
I'm starting with the eye in
the center of the face, and
then I'm gonna move it up and
over.
Okay.
So here I'm moving it up.
Notice that up is
minus the eye offset,
because decreasing y is up,
increasing y is down.
And for x, I'm going to
add the eye offset or
subtract the eye offset,
depending on whether it's
the left eye or the right eye.
So for the left eye, I'm going
to subtract the eye offset.
And for the right eye, I'm
going to add the eye offset.
Okay?
Everyone understand
that little
construct right there, I hope.
Okay and then it's
returning the center.
So now I have
the center of the eye.
So using the center
of the eye,
I can say let the eye radius
equal the skull radius
divided by the ratio for
that one,
which is
skullRadiusToEyeRadius.
Okay, so
that's what I'm gonna do.
And I'm gonna let
the eyeCenter just
equal centerOfEye,
whichever eye.
The eye that's up here.
So I'm just calling this
little function right here.
And so
I have those two things.
So I can just create
another circle.
So I'm going to let path
equal UIBezierPath and
do that arc again.
Here the center is
the eye center.
And the radius is
the eye radius.
And the start angle
is still zero.
Then end angle is still
CGFloat.pi* 2, and clockwise,
it doesn't matter.
I'll go the other
way this time.
Okay, so there's my path.
Let's set path.lineWidth
equal 5.0 again.
Starting to get tired
of typing that.
It's probably not
a good thing.
And then let's
return the path.
Okay.
So that's it.
So that gets the path for
either the left eye or
the right eye.
we'll say pathForEye,
the left eye, stroke.
Okay, pathForEye,
the right eye, stroke.
Okay, I hope everyone's
comfortable with the fact that
I'm calling a method,
taking this return value, and
immediately sending
it a message.
So, let's see how this went.
Let's see if we
got this right.
Look at that.
FIrst time.
It's really going well today.
Okay, so there's our two
lines, they look good.
You know what would be
kind of cool though?
If we could have open eyes and
closed eyes.
So how could we, how could
we have open eyes and
How about this: let's go up
here and just like we had this
closed eyes?
var scale which by the way
notice I left the var public.
Scale, so that people who
are using my face view,
they can control
the size of the face.
I don't mind.
And, I'm also gonna have eyes
open, which is going to be
a bool, which will
start out being false.
And we're just gonna
make our pathForEye,
look at this var,
look at the value of this var.
And either have the eyes
open or closed.
So, I'm back here in path for
eye.
So, if the eyes are open then
we're just gonna do what we
were already doing here,
this business.
Okay, because that's
what we did so far.
But if the eyes are closed,
then I want the path
to be different.
So, watch what I'm
gonna do here.
Let path be a UIBezierPath
without a value to start.
Okay, and then I set it here,
and I'm gonna set it here, and
that's allowed.
In other words Swift is
smart enough to know,
you created a let, which can
only be initialized once.
But you conditionally
initialized it here,
because now I'm gonna
say path equals.
And for the closed case
I'm just gonna make
a bezier path that
starts out blank.
And then I'm gonna
just move to, line to,
to make a little horizontal
line for a closed eye.
So, I'm gonna say
path.move(to: ) to move to
a point, CGPoint, we use
this constructor right here.
Not that one, let's use,
this one, CGFloat.
And the point we're gonna
move to we're gonna move to
the eyeCenter x
minus the eyeRadius.
So, we're gonna move to
the center of the eye and
back up with the eye there.
And we're gonna be
at the eyeCenter.y.
So, we're gonna right
in the eyeCenter and
we're gonna draw
a horizontal line so
we're gonna move to
the left side of it.
And then we're going to add
a line to the right side.
So, another CGPoint
which is this one again.
And this one is going
to be the eyeCenter.x
plus the eyeRadius.
And it's still at
the eyeCenter, okay?
Make sense?
Two more parentheses in there.
Everyone see what I did there?
But I just wanna make
sure you understood this
thing of let path.
You don't have to say equals
here as long as this if then
still only initializes it
once and doesn't change it.
Because it's still
a valid let.
So, let's go take
a look at that.
Okay, eyes closed.
Excellent, okay?
They're closed eyes.
We can go back here,
set this to true.
And again,
we should get open eyes.
Questions?
So, the question is when
do people do a custom
view like this when they
draw off their own thing?
In other words, when they
don't use this built in things
like button and things like
that well it depends on
the content that
they are providing.
But a lot of times, maybe they
are not drawing with arcs and
circles, maybe they're drawing
with images and text okay?
They're laying how they
want down to a level or
in an orientation that those
can do or maybe they're doing
text along a curve, which you
can do with this for example.
So, it's that kind of thing.
You might not see raw
drawing like this.
We're doing raw drawing
because it's simple and
I'm trying to show
you how you do it.
But there are apps
that are drawing
apps where you can take
your finger and draw.
They would clearly do
this as well right,
some of you might do that
as your final project.
Okay, so
anyway there's our eye.
So, we've got our eyes going,
we've got our skull.
How about our mouth?
We've gotta get the mouth
going so let's go do that.
And we're gonna do
the same thing there.
I'm gonna have a private
func pathForMouth and
it's gonna be a UIBezierPath.
So, how I'm going
to do the mouth.
Actually, I'm going to start
by drawing the mouth as
a rectangle,
just to show you where I'm
gonna put it on screen.
And then we'll turn it,
we'll use a bezier curve,
actually, to make the mouth.
So, how am I going to do that?
First, I'm going to calculate
some things like the width
of the mouth, the height of
the mouth, and the offset of
the mouth--the offset down
from the middle of
the face--using more of these
ratios.
So, I'm just calculating
the mouth, width,
height, and offset.
Now, I'm gonna use that to
create the rectangle in which
I'm going to put the mouth.
Let's do that, let mouthRect
equal and so the mouthRect
is gotta be offset down
by the mouth offset.
And it's gonna be the width
and height, so let's do that.
So, CGRect we'll use this
constructor right here,
CGFloat, we'll do
the skull's center dot x
minus the mouth's width,
divided by two.
So that's, because we
obviously want the mouth
centered in there,
and then for y,
we'll use the skullCenter.y
plus the mouthOffset.
And again it's plus,
because plus is down
in our drawing system.
And the width is just
the mouthWidth and
the height is the mouthHeight.
Let me make this a little
easier to read like this.
Everyone understand what I'm
doing there with
the mouse rect?
Let's just draw this rect.
So, I can say let path
equal UIBezierPath.
BezierPath knows
how do a rect.
It's this one down here.
The rect is our mouthRect and
let's just return that path.
So, now we've got a path for
the mouth.
Let's go down here and
stroke it by saying
pathForMouth().stroke().
Let's see what
this looks like.
Okay, excellent.
So, we have a mouth.
Kinda looks like a robot face.
We want it to have a nice
curve, a smile or a frown.
So, we gotta start thinking
a little bit how we're gonna
represent whether this
is smiling or frowning.
And so I'm gonna introduce
another var, up at the top,
here, just like I have it
with the eyes are open.
I'm gonna have a var which I'm
gonna call mouthCurvature and
make it be a Double.
I'll set it to,
let's say 1.0 and
the semantics of this I'm
going to have it be that
1.0 is full smile and
minus 1.0 is full frown.
And this is going to be public
and this is going to be
the public API that someone
uses when they want to use my
FaceView to tell me how much
this mouth should be smiling.
Okay, the mouth
curvature right here.
And I've just
defined it this way.
It's public,
I've documented it.
And so people can set it
to whatever they want.
So I'm going to use
this now to do it.
Now one thing is I've defined
it as a double because,
you know I'm not actually
doing the drawing right now
I'm just talking conceptually
what curvature is.
So, I need to convert this in
the some meaningful CGFloat,
and then use that
to draw this mouth.
So, how am I gonna do that?
The way I'm gonna do that do
that is let's get this back up
here and I'll show you, on the
rectangle that we have here.
I'm gonna use what's
called a Bezier curve,
how many people know
what is Bezier curve is?
Only one person!
My Gosh, okay so
a Bezier curve is just
two end points a line
between two end points but
there are two other points
called control points.
And you can kinda think it as,
think of it as the line
starts out at the start,
starts heading for
one of the control points.
As it gets close, it starts
heading for the other one.
And as it gets close to that
one, it starts heading for
the end, okay.
So, the control points kind
of pull on the line and
give it some curve.
And you can put those control
points anywhere you want.
Obviously, we're gonna
put ours like this.
So, my start is gonna be right
here in the middle of this
line and
my end is gonna be right here.
So we're gonna draw
a line across here.
And my two control
points are going to
be down here somewhere,
on both sides of his chin.
the line is gonna start here,
start down towards this one.
And so
Whoop.
Starting going to
the other one.
Whoop. Come back up here.
And make a little smile.
And if I move my
control points up to
the top, then whoop.
It'll be a frown.
Everyone understand that.
So I need four points.
The start, the end, and
the two control points.
Let's do those.
The start is easy,
that's just the middle
of the left edge, okay.
So I can say
the start is CGPoint.
And again we'll do
this kind of CGPoint.
And it's going to be the mouth
rect, our little mouth rect,
MinX, that's the left edge,
the minimum X, and
mouthRect.midY, that's
halfway up the mouth rect.
And the end is going
to be CGPoint.
This float.
And this one's gonna be
the mouthrect.maxX and
mouthrect.midY on
the other side.
So the two ends,
start and end,
are right in the middle of my
mouth rect on either side.
So now I need those
two control points.
For the control points I need
to think of how far down
they're going to be.
And it depends on
the mouth curvature.
The more smile I want, the
farther down they need to be.
The more frown I want, the
farther up they need to be.
So I'm gonna create another
thing called smileOffset.
And this is gonna be a
CGFloat, because it's gonna be
something that I'm using
to do drawing here.
And I'm gonna make it equal
to the mouthCurvature,
which is a double,
times the mouth rect.height.
So I will move down those
control points all the way
the entire height of a mouth
rect if I'm fully smiling.
Now, there's some problems
with this line of code.
One is, if you look at
these things right here,
it's saying you can't multiply
a Double times a Float.
This is a float,
this is a double.
So I'm gonna have to
convert this to a float
by using a constructor for
CGFloat.
Luckily, it has one that
takes a double okay.
Another thing here is smile
offset has to be between,
you know, one, or sorry,
mouth curvature here has to
be between one and minus one.
So I'm gonna enforce that.
Because I wouldn't want this
path curvature to be five, and
now he's smiling so
big that it's, you know,
on the floor literally.
Jaws on the floor.
We don't want that.
So I'm going to use min and
max to do that.
I'm gonna say max
minus one of min
of the mouth curvature and
one.
And that's going to restrict
it to be between minus one
and one.
Everybody got that.
I'm just using min and
max to do that there.
And notice that
it's automatically
made these be doubles,
which is fine.
So the result of min and
max is double, and
that's being converted
to a CGFloat.
That works fine.
Okay, so now that I
have that smile offset,
I can say how far down
my control points are.
So I'm gonna let cp1, which is
control point one, it's gonna
be smile offset times
the mouth rect height down.
And I'm gonna make
the two control points be
one third of the way in from
the edges of the mouth rect.
Does that make sense?
We wanted to kinda head down,
we wanted to kinda
be one-third of the way
along from each side.
So cp1 is gonna
be on the left.
That's gonna be a CGPoint.
And this again.
And so
this one will be the start.x.
Start is where we're
starting right here.
Plus the mouthRect.width
divided by three.
So I'm going a third
of the way across.
And then the y is a start.y
plus the smile offset
which could be negative if
mouth curvature is negative.
Smile offset might be
negative, meaning going up.
And so, this will be a frown.
Or it could be positive and
then it will go down.
Then cp2 is almost exactly
the same so I'll copy and
paste it, cp2.
It's just that here we're
gonna go to the end and
move back by mouthRect.width.
But it's still it's at
the same level okay because we
want it to come down, go
across, and then come back up.
So now that we have
these control points and
the start and the end, now we
can draw that in the path.
So we'll just do go our
Bzier path right here.
We'll leave the rect in there
at first so we can see it.
And I'm just gonna tell
the path to move to a CGPoint,
which is the start and,
actually,
you don't even
need to do that.
You just say,
move to the start.
And then, we're gonna
draw a curve, addCurve,
which adds one of
the Bezier curves.
And we're going to the end.
And the control point is cp1,
and the other is cp2.
So let's take a look.
Alright, excellent, so we
have mouth curvature is 1.0,
we've got a nice
big old smile.
Okay, we don't really want
this square there anymore,
rectangle, so
we'll get rid of that.
We can just do that by
creating an empty Bezier
curve to start.
Also, we want the path's
lineWidth to be 5.0.
One nice, even amount.
And let's go ahead and
check some other things.
Let's see if the mouth
of minus 0.5.
Let's see if that gives
us a slight frown.
Should give us a slight frown,
right.
Neat, okay.
Alright, what's the last
thing I'm gonna show.
One thing that's a little
bit of a pain is
every time I wanna check
the mouthCurvature,
I gotta go run the app.
Back, change it, run.
Or every time eyes open,
eyes closed.
Back and forth.
in Interface Builder, okay?
I can see a button
when I change it's things
in Interface Builder.
And wouldn't it even be cooler
if I could have an inspector
in Interface Builder,
that would let me
inspect these things.
Well, of course
we can do that.
How do we do that.
We go up here, and we just
make this IBDesignable, okay.
If you put IBDesignable in
front of a UIView at the top,
then when you go over to your
storyboard, at the top, you're
gonna see it here, compiling
that code, integrating it into
Interface Builder, and
showing it to you.
Okay now unfortunately we
don't have an inspector here
that allows us to
inspect those things.
But we can do that as well.
Go back to FaceView here.
And I'm going to say for
example make the scale
IBInspectable.
Let's make eyesOpen
Let's make the mouthCurvature
IBInspectable.
Let's add a few
other things here.
Let's make the lineWidth
IB inspectable.
So to do that, we can't have
this 5.0 going on over here,
we're gonna have to add a var.
So we're just gonna add
an IBInspectable var.
Which is gonna be the line
width, which is a CGFloat.
We'll start it out at 5.0 but
we'll be able to change it.
So now we can go everywhere
where we have that 5.0.
We'll just change
it to use this var.
We can also do the color.
IBInspectable var the color,
it's a UI color.
Okay, we'll start it out
as blue like it is now.
So where we have
view UIColor.blue,
we'll use this var instead.
Alright, we'll give
you a color blue.
I'm just gonna say color,
to set the color.
Okay, so basically it's taking
all the things in my app and
just making them not
only configurable,
as public variables,
but also inspectable.
So let's go back to our story
board and see if this works.
Sure enough, right away,
you see up at the top there,
Face View, the scale, whether
the eyes are open, line width,
the color, mouth curvature,
are now inspectable.
So let's close the eyes.
Let's have the mouth
curvature be 0.5.
Let's make the color
be orange.
Let's make the line
width be two.
Let's make the scale be 0.5.
Make the scale be 0.9 again,
whatever.
Now another interesting thing
about this is just like if you
were inspecting
a UIButton here.
When you run it's going to use
these settings as
the initial settings.
You truly are editing this,
just like you would
edit anything else,
any other custom view,
see it comes up like this.
Got it?
Now one thing that you
have to do when you have
an IBInspectable is you have
to explicitly type you cannot
let Swift infer it.
Because while Swift can infer,
Interface builder cannot.
It doesn't have
an inference engine there.
So always make sure you
put the actual type
in all the IBInspectables.
Alright, that's it!
what we're gonna do is we're
gonna add a model to our MVC.
Next time,
And we're gonna start putting
some gestures in here.
And then we'll start talking
about multiple MVCs.
>> For more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.