[MUSIC]
Stanford University.
>> Welcome to Stanford CS193p,
Developing Applications for
IOS, this is Winter
quarter 2017.
Today we are going to
talk about a few things.
We're gonna start though
giving a demo about what I
talked about last time
which is multiple MVCs.
After that I'm gonna do some
slides on the view controller
lifecycle, really important
mechanism for finding out
what's going on with your
MVC as time goes flows by.
And if I have time left at
the end, I'm gonna start
talking a little bit
about memory management,
which is basically managing
the memory of reference types,
things that are in the heap.
How do they get managed?
How do they know when
the stay in the heap, or
leave the heap?
But first, we're gonna
start with this demo.
I'm calling this demo
emotions in FaceIt.
If you remember last time,
we built a nice MVC that
knows how to draw a face.
It was a pretty
generic MVC and
how to model,
which is a facial expression.
So now we're gonna build a
more complicated app that has
two MVCs.
One MVCs is going to let
you choose an emotion.
Like happy or sad.
And then the other MVC is just
gonna be our generic face
view, and
it's gonna show that emotion.
we're gonna learn how to use
the split view controller and
By doing that,
navigation controller, combine
MVCs, to make a big graph.
It's a simple example because
of time constraints but
you should get the idea.
So here I'm back in FaceIt,
this demo we had last time.
One thing before I start,
I wanted to show you something
you're going to need for
your homework, which is how
to rename a ViewController.
I have this
ViewController here.
This is the ViewController
that shows the face.
Remember, here's the faceView
var and here's it's model.
So I don't like this
name ViewController.
It's really quite too generic.
It's almost like
it's super class,
which is UIViewController.
Really this wants to be
some specifically named
view controller, and in this
case it shows a face so
this probably best called
it faceviewcontroller.
So I wanna just type
face right here, and
hope that's enough.
But of course as I mentioned
in like lecture number one
that's not enough.
You can't just
rename right there.
You actually have to rename
a couple of other things.
One, the file that it's in,
you see the file,
is still called
viewcontroller.swift.
We almost always want
to have our name of
our file be the same as the
primary class that's in there.
Now, it's not required in
swift, the name of the file
could be completely different
than any class in there.
to kinda help people find the
code that they're looking for,
But generally,
we wanna have the name of
the file pretty much match
the name of the main class.
It could be multiple
classes in a short file,
that's perfectly
allowed as well, but
especially if it
is the main one.
You might think,
well that's enough, but
there's one more very,
very important piece of this
which is in the story board.
We haven't really talked
too much about this- well
actually, we did see it,
with the Face View.
We did this with Face View,
but
we need to inspect this
controller, and I'm
gonna click on the controller
by clicking this orange thing
up here, that represents the
controller for this whole MVC.
'm gonna go over to this same
inspector we went on when we
changed the face view from
being a generic UI view to
being a specific face view.
'm gonna do the exact
same thing here.
So 'm picking this whole
view controller and
'm going to the identity
inspector up here and
'm gonna change the class
from ViewController,
that's what it was the generic
name to Face view controller.
So if you forget
to do this piece,
than none of your outlets
are gonna be hooked up.
And iOS is gonna be very
confused because you're
gonna be asking it to couple
outlets to a different class.
SomeClasses doesn't exist
anymore cuz I renamed it away.
You'll need to do that for
your homework.
You'll have to change
your current calculator
MVC from being called
View Controller
to being called something like
Calculator View Controller and
that's because you're gonna
have this new MVC- the graph
view controller- and you wanna
make clear which one is which.
Now I'm not gonna touch my
Face View Controller or
MVC at all in this
demo from here on.
I'm gonna build this
multi-MVC app, and
I'm gonna use the face view
controller that I just
finished building last time
as a reusable component.
Just like your graph view
controller is gonna be a
reusable MVC in your homework.
I said that I wanted
to have two MVCs.
One is just a list
of some emotions.
And then I'm going to use this
MVC to show that emotion.
So let's just dive
right into this and
put another MVC into
our storyboard.
We have this one MVC,
we get another one, in exactly
the same way that we get a new
button or something like that,
which is to go down here
to the utilities window
at the bottom here and just
drag out a view controller.
You just pull it out and
drag it right into your
storyboard like that.
Now this MVC right here,
what's gonna be its class
of it's controller?
It's just going to be (if
we select it by clicking on
the orange thing),
UI view controller.
In other words
not a sub class.
So we're gonna need to create
a custom sub class for
this view controller
just like we have for
our face view controller.
We'll do that in a second.
Before we do that though,
I wanna talk about
this little arrow.
You see this arrow right here?
This is the arrow that tells
iOS when this app launches,
use this MVC as the first
thing that appears.
It's like the "entry"
into the storyboard.
And so if I want it
to be the other one,
I can just pick it
up with the mouse.
And drop it on that one.
And now this one
is my entry MVC.
I also want you to notice
that we have a warning here.
You see this yellow warning?
I'm gonna click on that,
and we'll see here it says
face view controller is
unreachable, because it
has no entry points.
It's saying this view
controller right here with
the face, you're never
gonna see that in your app.
Which is true, because my app
is gonna come in here to this
blank one and I can't get
to the FaceView from there.
Now of course we're going to
add SplitView controller,
and navigation controllers,
and we're eventually gonna be
able to get there, but I just
want you to understand what
this unsupported
configuration means.
It just means that
you can't get there.
If I move this back,
this arrow off of this and
back over to here,
now this one, you see,
view controller
is unreachable.
Which makes perfect sense.
If I run this app by the way,
let's go ahead and run, you're
gonna see that my app's gonna
come up completely blank.
That face will not be
there because that MVC is
really not even being used.
It's in the storyboard
right now, but
since it's not accessible
we can't navigate to it.
We can't segue to it to
use the terminology you
learned last time.
We get this
completely blank UI.
If we want to have things
like outlets and actions,
or anything like that, with
this View Controller, it needs
to have a custom subclass
of UI view controller,
it can't just be generic.
So we're gonna create that.
We're gonna go to File, New
File, remember that's always
where we go when we create
a new UI View Subclass,
a new UI View Controller,
any Calculator brain.
We did all those
from new file.
So I'm gonna click new file.
This is gonna be a sub class
of a UI view controller.
I'm gonna pick this one here,
cocoa touch class.
We use swift file over
here when it was just
calculator brain,
not a sub class of anything.
But here, we're gonna
do cocoa touch class.
And it says subclass of what?
Okay, it's even defaulted
here to UIVewController.
Remember earlier
we picked UIView.
We're gonna leave this
UIViewController and I'm gonna
call this view controller
my EmotionsViewController.
So this gonna show
the emotions like happy,
sad, whatever, and
then I'm gonna click on
it to go show the face.
So I just do that.
Go over here, it says
where do you wanna put it.
Again, I do not
wanna put it here.
You see where it says
Group FaceIt, and
it has that blue icon.
We wanna put it down in here.
So if you put it here,
it's gonna be at
the very top level.
Down here, it's with all
your other classes space
faceview.swift, etc.
So make sure you
remember to do that.
So here I popped it in there.
There's my view controller
selected in the navigator.
Let's make the navigator
a little bit wider, so
you can read it, there we go.
EmotionsViewController and
you can see it's giving
me a little bit of code.
These right here are part of
the ViewController life cycle,
which I promise I'm gonna
talk about right after this
but not now.
There's this other thing
that's commented out down
here, which is actually really
important to today's lecture.
This is Navigation method,
which you know all too
well from last lecture.
It's called prepare for segue.
This is the method that's
gonna be used when we segue or
transition from this
MVC to another one.
And we have to prepare that
other one to do its job and
here's why we do it,
prepare for segue.
We'll be coming back and
implementing prepare for
segue, in just a minute.
Now that we have this new
class, EmotionsViewController,
we have to do the exact
same thing we just did.
Which is to go back
to our storyboard,
click on this View controller,
go to the Utilities window,
get that identity
inspector up.
And then pick the class in
EmotionsViewController, so
that this is now
an EmotionsViewController,
not a generic
UIView controller.
So now that we've
hooked that up,
we can start building
our UI here.
What is our UI here?
It's gonna be super simple,
I'm just gonna grab
some buttons, so
let's get one here,
let's change some
attributes of that button.
How about let's make
the font really big,
something like 40 point
is probably good.
Let's go ahead and
make some more of them,
I'm gonna copy and paste.
I think three of them is
enough for this demo.
We'll have one of our emotions
be sad, another emotion be
happy and I don't know if
this is an emotion but
we'll have this
one be worried.
Those are gonna be our three
things we're gonna show
with our face.
view, let's put a little
space in between them there.
We'll fill equally even though
they're all buttons, so
they're all gonna be
filled equally anyway.
So we've got this nice
stack view right here.
Now, one thing about this
stack view is, if I put it
here and I go down to look at
my various orientations and
devices, if I go
landscape here, "Ugh!".
It gets cut off, right?
So I really want these, this
stack to stay in the middle.
I don't wanna do the same
thing I did with
the calculator where I'm
sticking it to the edges.
I just want it to stay in
the middle cuz I don't want
the buttons to be kinda
really spread out.
I want them to stay
kind of collected but
I want them in the middle.
I can still do that
with the autolayout,
the same way we did
in the last demo.
I'm just gonna pick
up the thing and
use the blue lines to
indicate what I want.
Which is I want
this in the center.
I'm holding this, so
that the blue lines
come on in the center.
And when I let go, iOS
interface builder here knows "
he wants that in the center".
So that when I go down here
to this little guy again and
I say reset to
suggested constraints,
just like I did in
the last lecture,
it creates constraints
that put it in the middle.
And we can verify that by
going up to this inspector,
this is the size inspector.
It shows the size
of the thing but
it also shows the constraints,
the autolayout constraints.
And this is constrained to
align its center horizontally
to the superview center and
it's centered vertically
to the superview center.
Now if we do the rotation,
we see that it stays
in the center.
I'm giving you a little
taste of autolayout,
I'm gonna give a whole
lecture on autolayout
in a couple weeks.
But I'm just trying to
give you a little hint
about how it works for now.
Alright, so we have this,
this is our UI,
that's the entire UI
that we're gonna do.
Now let's go ahead and
run this,
run it on iPhone briefly here
Just to make sure that we've
actually put this in our UI.
There it is.
Sure enough if I click on it,
rotation, seems to work fine.
We can even check to see,
does this work on iPad?
Let's try this one
now right there.
Here it is, here's our UI.
It's working fine here and
we can rotate here as well and
get this gigantic
landscape iPad.
Is there any way
to go smaller?
What's the smallest
we can go scale?
25%?
There we go,
that's small enough.
So we've got all this screen
real estate here on an iPad.
It's be really great to use
the split view to have these
words on the left and the face
that matches it on the right.
So that's exactly
what we're gonna do,
we're gonna go back to our
storyboard right here and
make that happen.
And to do that, again, is just
a matter of dragging something
out, I'm gonna make my
scale really small here, so
you can see this
as we drag it out.
But here we're gonna drag out
the split view controller
cuz we wanna put these
two MVCs in an MVC
that has them as
part of its view.
So when I drag this out,
you're actually
gonna see I get more
than just a split view,
I get some other little MVCs
that come along with it here.
And I don't really
need any of these other
MVCs that come along with it.
Trying to make your
life easier, but
I find that 99% of the time,
you don't need these other
things that come with it.
So I'm just going here and
select those and delete them.
So let's get rid of this one.
Whoops!
Not the whole thing.
Let's just get
rid of this one,
sorry, there and we're gonna
get rid of this one and
we get rid of that one.
I'm just left with my
split view controller and,
of course,
my two MVCs are here.
Let's move this little more
over to the side here,
scroll down a bit.
And now I just wanna make this
be the master of my split view
controller and
I want this to be my detail.
Whoops, other way around,
this is the master,
this is the detail.
When the app starts,
I don't want it to start here,
I want it to start here,
don't forget this step.
If you want the app
to come here and
then show the split view
controller with both things.
So how do I make this the
master and this the detail?
I'm just gonna hold
down control and
drag from the split view
controller to the master.
And then in here,
Only these two,
master and detail.
So I'm gonna make
that one the master,
it makes this little
master connection there,
that's not a segue by the way,
that's a kind of like,
somewhat like an outlet
connection but
it's a specific connection
to that master var there.
This one is the detail.
So I've made my master and
my detail here.
Zoom in a little bit.
That's really all I need to do
to get these both on screen.
So let's go ahead and run and
see what happens here.
Alright, so here we go.
Sure enough,
there's the face on the right.
Here's this stuff on the left.
And if I click this,
nothing happens.
The face doesn't show.
Now why does nothing
happen there?
Because we have to do
the step of having a segue.
If we want to move
to a different MVC,
we have to segue to it.
Each of these is gonna have to
have the segue to this MVC.
And when it segues, it's gonna
replace that MVC with a new
one that's properly prepared
to show that motion.
Let's go do our segues.
Segues also of course,
we use our favorite gesture
which is Ctrl + drag.
So if I wanna make a sad
segue, I'm just gonna hold
down Ctrl and drag it to the
MVC that I want to segue to,
the MVC I want to show
when I press Sad.
So I do that.
Now, you notice that I
have some choices of what
kind of presentation,
what kind of segue I want.
For example, Present As
Popover would present
the thing I'm segueing to in
a little popover window on
top of everything else.
Present Modally would take
over the whole screen and
show the new MVC.
Then there's show and
show detail.
Show is only used when you're
in a navigation controller,
the thing where they've got
the cards sliding on top,
like the settings
example I showed you.
Show detail is used in a split
view setting or in a hybrid
setting, where sometimes
you're in a split view, and
sometimes you're in
navigation view,
which is gonna be the case
that we're gonna be in here.
Show detail means show
this in the detail side of
the split view.
I'm gonna show detail there.
I've made this segue, you
see it appeared right here.
This is a segue,
looks a little different
from this thing,
a little different
icon right there.
This is a segue and
you can click on it, and
in fact you can
even inspect it.
And you must inspect it,
in fact,
go to the attributes inspector
and inspect it, because you're
always gonna wanna give
every segue an identifier.
This is just a unique string,
that in your code you'll
be able to reference
in order to say,
"I'm talking about
this segue right here".
So, I'm gonna call
this my sad segue.
Then I'm gonna do the exact
same thing here for happy.
I'm gonna just show
detail on that one.
I'm gonna inspect that segue.
See, there's our sad one.
Notice that when
you pick a segue,
it shows you what
it's segueing from.
If I pick this one, it shows
it seguing from the other one,
so we know which one it is.
So this is the happy one, and
then we'll have our
little worried segue.
Where's that one?
It's right there, worried.
Okay, so that's it.
So we've created these segues,
put them in the, we'll put it
into split view first,
then we created the segues.
And now when you click
on those buttons,
it's going to segue to this
detail and in fact in a split
view it replaces the one
that's there with a new one.
Remember that segues
always create a new one,
Don't forget that, that segues
always create a new one.
Something easy to forget.
Especially in the split view,
it looks like,
" it just changed the one
that was already there".
But no, it actually just
completely replaced that
detail segue by doing that.
If we run this it
it's gonna look like
it doesn't didn't even work.
Even though we hooked
these segues up,
it looks like it's just
not doing anything, watch.
Okay, so is he sad, happy,
worried, nothing is happening.
Absolutely nothing is
changing over here.
Now, what's interesting is
it is in fact seguing, and
it is replacing that.
The only problem is,
we didn't prepare that thing
to show the right emotion
before it showed, so
it is just showing
the neutral emotion.
It's creating a new MVC, but
it's just showing neutral,
because it has not been
prepared to be onscreen.
We have to go back to the
emotions view controller here,
and do this prepare for segue,
and prepare that destination
detail view controller to
do what we want it to do.
Let's get rid of some
of the comments here,
just to make our code
a little cleaner.
And get rid of that, as well.
Actually, we can even
get rid of that.
Okay, so
here's our prepare for
segue with this extra
argument sender,
which I'll also talk
about in a little bit.
So what do we do when
we prepare for segue?
There's usually two really
important piece of information
we need when we're preparing
to segue to an MVC.
One is we need to know which
segue, tha's the identifier.
The other one we need to
know is what is the new MVC
that this system
just created for
us that we're
supposed to prepare.
Both of these things
are found inside this
argument right here, this
segue, this UIStoryboardSegue,
if we ALT click on it.
Can't get it.
Sorry about that,
here we go, on this guy.
We have the storyboard segue,
and
if you'll look in
the documentation for it,
you'll see that it doesn't
have a lot in there.
But one important thing is the
destination view controller,
and one is the identifier
of the segue.
This is also the source,
which would be the emotions
view controller.
That's really just
got the information
that we need to
prepare this thing.
Let's go and first get the
destination view controller.
I'm gonna say let
destinationViewController
equal the segue's destination.
So I've got that
view controller.
Now that is a type UI view
controller, if I alt-click on
that, you'll see it's
type UI view controller.
That's because segue is this
generic UI stroyboard thing,
it doesn't know anything
about face view controllers,
EmotionViewController,
anything like that.
So, we're gonna have to
actually use that casting
mechanism with as.
Remember that as casting that
we did with Any, in AnyObject?
We're gonna have
to do it here,
because this
destinationViewController
better darn well be a face
view controller, or
I don't know how
to prepare it.
That's the only thing
I know how to prepare,
this emotion for us,
so it'd better be that.
So I'm gonna say, if I can let
a FaceViewController equal
the destinationViewController
as, and
I'm gonna do it conditionally
here, a FaceViewController.
Then, I'm good to go.
So now remember, this as kinda
conditionally checks to see if
it's possible for this to
be a FaceViewController.
And if it's not, my
preparer's gonna do nothing.
And it's gonna let that
destination view controller
appear unprepared,
because it doesn't
know how to prepare it.
Cuz we only know how to
prepare, (at least so far in
our app), we only know how to
prepare a FaceViewController.
Okay, in fact some would
say don't use, as, with,
if let, here.
Just use as exclamation point,
and make your program crash if
you try to segue to something
you're not expecting.
Cuz again, you'll find
it when you're debugging
before you ship your product.
So I can see the argument for
that.
But we'll make it so we'll
just ignore it, if we can't
convert that destination
to a face view controller.
Alright, so now let's
check the identifier.
One thing about the identifier
is someone might have
forgotten to set it
in the storyboard.
So I'm gonna do
an if let on it.
if let identifier =
segue.identifier.
Cuz this segue.identifier
right here,
you can see is
an optional string.
So it might be not set,
in the storyboard.
So I'm checking to make sure
that it is in fact set.
And now I need the expression,
the facial expression,
that I'm gonna set
in this space for,
this is where I'm gonna
do the actual preparing.
And I could do a little
switch, or an if then, else,
if then, else here on all
the different segues: sad,
happy, worried.
But I'm imagining that "
my app might have 20 or
30 emotions someday".
As such, I wanted to do
something a little more
extensible, similar to what we
did with the calculator brains
operation, which is I'm
going to create a private
little dictionary here
called Emotional Faces.
And it's going to a dictionary
that has Strings as the keys,
and Facial Expressions Facial
expressions, FacialExpression.
Oops, sorry this was
supposed to be colon
FacialExpression as
the values.
I'm even gonna just put
the values in right here.
So this is just
a little dictionary.
This string is gonna
be the identifier here
that comes back,
the name of our segue.
And the FacialExpression is
gonna be the facial expression
that I want to use there.
What's it complaining
about here?
Cuz I didn't have
any in there.
Yeah, cuz we have
nothing in here.
So let's put some
things in here.
Let's do sad.
What's a good facial
expression for sad?
Well let's create one,
a facial expression where
the eyes are probably
closed eyes, and
the mouth is in a frown.
That sounds pretty
sad all around.
And then for happy,
it'd probably be the facial
expression with the eyes open
and we'll let the mouth in
a big smile, of course.
And I think that worried,
I looked at a few
facial expressions.
I thought, worried, the best
thing that looks like that was
eyes open, and the mouth kind
of in a, a little smirk.
That face, for some reason to
me, looks a little worried.
Now I've got this table,
which I can add more
things to over time.
And all I have to do is make
a new segue for it, and
have the identifier
match the string here.
Now, I might have an
identifier that's not in here,
so I'm gonna say if I can let
the expression I want equal
My emotionalFace is here,
sub the identifier.
So I'm looking it up there.
But it might come back nil
cuz we know that if we
look something up in
dictionary it's not there,
it will come back nil.
So that time we're
doing if let.
By the way, look at this
I have, if let this,
if let that, if let this.
And you can imagine to having
four or five of these, and
you start getting really deep,
and
the code is really
kinda messy.
You can actually just
do these with commas.
You can just put right here,
this one, and then a comma,
and then this one,
and then a comma.
So you can put as many of
these things as you want.
And not just lets, you know,
if let comma, let comma, but
also other expressions too,
other things.
Like, it's almost like an
ampersand kind of expression.
And then makes it so
that I don't need all
these curly braces.
I can just use this one
top level curly brace.
Now I have the expression.
Here is where I'm
gonna do the prepare.
I'm gonna say
FaceViewController,
prepare yourself by
making your model,
the expression equal
this expression
that I just looked
up in that table.
So that's the actual prepare.
That is where I am preparing
this new MVC that it
created, this brand new
FaceViewController I just
created with the segue.
I'm preparing it to
do what it does.
So let's see if that works.
The face should
be prepared now.
When it gets created,
we should see a face.
The right face.
Okay, so here it is.
Let's try.
Woo-hoo, happy.
Well, it looks a little
worried, and sad.
Now, let's see how happy we
are, though, on an iPhone.
Because we know that on
an iPhone, it's kinda small.
Split View, not really enough
room for a Split View.
So what's gonna happen with
this storyboard on an iPhone?
Let's find out.
Okay, well, here we go,
Sad, Happy, Worried.
Excellent, let's see Happy.
All right, we're happy.
Well, now we're not so
happy because we can't
get out of here.
We got this happy face but
I can't get it back.
Let's try going, well, even in
landscape, no Split View, so
now there's no way to get back
to pick any other expression.
So in the iPhone, you get
to pick one expression and
you're done, and
that's the end of the app.
You have to quit
the app now because, or
turn your phone off, I guess.
There's absolutely
nothing you can do.
You're stuck.
I guess you can make
the eyes blink.
So this is not a very good
app on the iPhone, obviously.
That's about it.
So what are we gonna do?
Since we have no
Split View on the iPhone,
(you actually can have a Split
View on the iPhone by the way,
but you have to do a special
stuff to kinda enable it.
But by default
the Split View doesn't work.
Well, of course,
Apple understands that.
That Split View is not
very good for iPhones.
iPhone Plus is by the way,
it does work, and
I'm gonna show you
that in a moment.
They know it's not that good.
So if you go back to
your storyboard here.
We're gonna go back
to our storyboard,
and we're gonna look at this.
And we're gonna say,
hmm, well, on iPhone,
I'd really like this UI to be
navigation controller instead,
not a Split View.
Navigation Controller where
when I click on this emotion
it chose the face by
sliding it on top, but
I'll have a back button so
I can go back,
pick a different one.
It'll slide it on top and
I can hit back,
you see what I mean, so
I can go back and forth.
And you can do that
incredibly simply.
You just pick this view
control right here, and
go to editor.
Embed in
Navigation Controller.
And it's gonna insert
a Navigation Controller
in the middle there, see that,
how I put that Navigation
Controller in there.
And what's really cool is with
the Navigation Controller you
actually get a little title
bar, and you can go straight
here in interface
builder if you want and
put a title in there
like maybe emotions.
We could call it,
it's the name of our app or
that's what these are in
this NVC rather, so
I'll put a little title in
there, and that's really cool.
And so now when we run, I get
my face coming up in neutral
mode, and if I go back, now I
can pick something like happy.
Now one thing you might be
interested in there is like,
whoa, it came up
in neutral mode.
Instead of coming up on this
page, you kinda would expected
it to come up on this page.,
wouldn't you?
And we actually made
it extra credit for
you to go to figure
out how to do it.
And what you need to
do is something with
Split View Controller.
It's delegate, which I'm not
gonna talk about the delegates
until Wednesday, that's why
we made it extra credit.
But you're gonna use
Split View's delegate and
read the documentation,
and you can make it so
that it'll come up
on either page.
Either on this detailed page
or on this master page.
But you can see that this is
working great, in fact we've
even got this nice little
title bar up here, and we can
switch back and forth between
any emotions that we want.
And let's go see what happened
when we did that to iPad.
Did we break the iPad?
Let's hope we didn't break
the iPad by doing that.
Here we go.
It comes up.
There's the face.
By the way, you can do
Split Views in Portrait.
You just slide out.
You see, it slides out like
a little shelf like that.
Or you can rotate and
see them side by side.
And it's still working.
So the iPad is
working just fine.
Well, unfortunately,
there's no zoom level
that's a better zoom level.
But the iPad has a title here.
But it'd be really
cool if there was
a title over here, too.
Like maybe this would say,
sad and
if I hit happy it would say,
happy over here.
Wouldn't that be cool?
To have a title on both
sides of that, that's
often in a Split View that we
want, because you want kind of
the balance between the two
to have tittle on both sides.
So no problem, let's just go
back to our storyboard here,
and select this
View Controller and
embed it in
a Navigation Controller.
And in fact, if we go here and
look at an iPad.
What it's gonna look like on
iPad, especially in landscape?
We'll see that,
ooh, this is looking what
like exactly what we want.
when it's in detail, its got
a title bar, a title bar here,
Look.
See,
title bars everywhere.
It's fantastic,
this is gonna be great.
Let's do it.
All right, look at that,
title bar on the top.
And, uh-oh, we broke it.
What happened there?
Why did we break that?
Well, this has to do with
the preparation piece.
And I talked about this
in the lecture last time.
Because what prepare
is doing is,
it's creating a new MVC here,
and then we're preparing it.
The problem is that now when
it creates a new MVC here,
what is the MVC?
What kind of MVC is it?
Anyone want to hazard a guess?
Cuz it's not a face
view controller
anymore, what is it?
Yeah, it's a UI
navigation controller.
That's the new MVC
we're creating,
it has a faceView in it, but
it's still a UI
navigation controller.
So our code that
we have back here.
That's doing this prepare.
It says,
if I can let the faceView
equal the destination as
a FaceViewController.
Well, I can't do that
because it's not.
It's a UI navigation
controller instead.
And I'll show you that
in debugging here.
Let's go ahead and set
a break point right here, and
go back over here and
pick one, like happy.
Here it breaks.
And if we look at this
DestinationViewController,
those of you who came to
the debugging Friday section.
We didn't really go over
this cool feature, but
if you just mouse
over a variable.
You see how I just,
I'm holding my mouse over
DestinationViewController?
You see it's
showing that there?
There's two really
cool buttons in there.
You see this one
looks like an i?
And this one looks like
the letter i for info.
If you click the one that
looks like a i, it'll actually
show you that View Controller
right there in the debugger.
Which is kinda cool.
And if you go over here and
click the other little i,
it'll show you
the class that it is.
In this case, it's a UI
navigation controller.
And this works for
all kinds of types,
colors, even a map location.
It'll show you a map with
the location on there.
So this little mouseover
debugging thing is
But anyway, we see that
DestinationViewController
really cool.
right there is a UI
navigation controller.
We know that's no good.
So what are we gonna
do about this?
Well, I'm gonna check for
this case, okay?
I'm gonna say, if I can let
navigationController equal
the destinationViewController
as a UINavigationController,
in other words,
if that destination is a UI
Navigation Controller, then
I'm gonna grab the visible
ViewController out of it and
use that as the
FaceViewController hopefully.
So, I'm gonna say
in this case I want
the destinationViewController,
which is this thing up here,
which now it needs
to be a var and so
I'm gonna change
its value here.
I'm gonna let that equal,
the navigationController's
visibleViewController.
Okay, now this is great,
visibleViewController is
a really nice method and
navigation control,
it shows you whichever
card stack is currently
visible, exactly what I want.
The only problem with it,
however, is it returns
an optional, because
nothing might be visible in
the navigationController
right now.
Okay, you might have
never put anything
in the navigationController.
So since that is an optional,
I'm gonna have to give it
some default value,
and the default value,
I'm just gonna say, just use
the destinationViewController
as is if I can't get
the visible ViewController or
the navigationController.
So it's kinda a default to
use what it already was.
Basically, don't change it.
So this little if is nice,
because now my code works if
it's in a navigationController
or even if it's not.
Because if it's not in
a navigationController,
this is gonna do nothing.
That's going to fail.
Alright, this as is
not going to work.
And we'll go straight
down to checking
if it's a FaceViewControllor.
So if I later came along back
to my storyboard here and
eh, you know what, I don't
really want the title on here.
I decided,
And I took this
navigationController out
of the picture, my code would
still work, cuz my code works
whether I'm going straight
to a FaceController or
through a
navigationController.
Let's see if that indeed
fixed our problem.
Here we go, let's try it.
Happy, yeah, worried, sad.
Happy, we're happy
that it's working.
Okay, now we have this nice
title bar at the top and
we said, wouldn't it be cool
if we could put a title, so
let's do that.
Let's put a little title here,
in fact the title I'm gonna
put here is whichever button
brought this MVC up.
So if the sad button
brought it up,
I'm gonna get its current
title and put it up here,
kinda like we did
in the calculator.
Look back to the sender and
luckily prepare for segue,
has the sender.
This is the thing that
cause the segue to happen.
Which is going to be
one of those buttons.
So right down here, I can just
get the current title of this
sender right here and
set that to be the title.
Now if you remember
from the lecture about
navigationController, the way
that you
set things that appear when
it's in a navigationController
like the title,
you can also set the buttons,
the back button
title you can set,
or you can even put write
buttons in the top.
You do that with this thing
called NavigationItem on
UIViewController.
So I'm gonna take
the faceViewController's
navigationItem, which,
by the way the navigationItem,
you can just kind
of think of it as
a bag of goodies that only
UINavigationController uses.
And it only looks in
that bag of goodies
when this ViewController,
the faceViewController,
is the visible ViewController
in the NavigationController.
Then it looks in this bag of
goodies and you can see that
there's a lot of things
in the bag of goodies,
like leftBarButtonItem,
rightBarButtonItems, and
of course the title.
Which is what I
want to set here.
I want to set the title of
the navigationController
when this thing is visible.
And I'm gonna send it,
I want to send it to the
sender's current title, but
I can't quite do that.
Why can't I do that?
Why is that not gonna work?
This.
See any problem?
Yeah, this is Any.
And Any does not
understand any messages.
Because it doesn't
know what it is.
So we have to take this any
and turn it into a UI button.
And we do that by saying this,
sender as the UIButton.
Now we could almost
send current title.
The only problem is this.
What is this type of,
what is the type of, if I can
select it, this expression?
What's its type?
No one wanna guess
on this one?
No one?
It's an optional, right?
Because "as?" returns
an optional, so this is
an optional, so we can't send
an optional current title.
We need to either
exclamation point it, or
a little safer,
we could optional chain it.
Because we know that optional
chaining is just going to
ignore the rest of this
expression if that happened to
not be a button.
And this as returned nil,
because this couldn't be
turned into a button.
So we'll just optional chain
in which case the title here
will be set to nil, because
this whole thing will be nil
if this optional
chaining doesn't happen.
And that's okay,
because we look at the title
of a navigation item.
It's an optional.
So we can send it to a nil.
And then this will, it will
have no title up there.
I intentionally put
this thing in here for
lot of things going on here.
We have the any cast going on.
We have optional
chaining going on here.
We use the navigation item.
So there is a lot in
this line of code.
So make sure you kind
of understand what's
all the pieces going on there.
Now we should be getting
hopefully the title of
the button appearing as the
title on the right-hand side.
So happy, sure enough,
there's happy.
Worried, there's worried.
Sad, happy.
And of course if we rotate,
we're still getting
the title up there.
We can slide this thing
out and pick sad,
and it happens back there.
Slide that thing out
of the way if we want.
Rotate back.
How about iPhone 7?
Let's see if we've
broken that.
It appears with this split
views detail coming up first
in this neutral mode.
We'll go back to emotions.
Pick Happy.
Sure enough, it's setting that
title fine there as well.
If we go here.
Since it's an iPhone,
can't do split view,
it's still working fine in
navigationController mode.
Let's go look at a 7 Plus.
There is a 7 plus which
is kind of a high breed
between iPhone 7 and an iPad.
And in portrait mode,
an iPhone 7 plus works
just like an iPhone.
So it's gonna be the
navigationController back and
forth.
But in landscape,
it'll work like an iPad.
Okay, so obviously an iPhone
7 plus in portrait mode,
it is not big enough to do the
slide-out thing like an iPad
does in portrait mode, but
in landscape mode it is, so
let's make it so
this thing fits.
That's close
enough to fitting.
I'll go small here.
All right, so this is a plus.
And you can see it comes
up in portrait mode.
It's acting like
it's an iPhone.
See that, okay?
It's just doing that.
But look what happens if
I go to landscape mode,
I get a split view.
Tha's working fine.
So see how we built in the
storyboard this hybrid UI and
it works on all the different
kinds of devices.
No matter whether they
control with you or
not it'll default
go back to using
navigationController,
whatever.
And the only thing we
had to do in our code
as a concession to the
cross-platform is checking for
that navigationController and
only for
the thing we were segueing to.
Back to the slides.
Our next topic here is
the View Controller Lifecycle.
Now, everything
has a life cycle,
even we have a life cycle:
we're born, we live our lives,
things happen, and we die.
Well, that happens to
a View Controller as well.
It's just born, things happen
to it, and then it dies,
it leaves the heap.
That's what happens
on its death.
Why do we care about the view
controller lifecycle?
Because we often wanna
do things at various key
inflection points
in its lifetime.
The start of a lifecycle
is really simple.
It gets initialized,
and 99.99% of
the time a view controller is
coming out of a storyboard.
Its initializer is this
special initializer coming out
of a storyboard.
In your reading assignments,
I actually explained
how this works.
But we don't usually override
the initializer of a view
We're going to use the other
ways we know to initialize
controller.
each variables.
I'm not even gonna talk about
how to make one in code.
Because we just,
just don't do that.
You can see why, right?
Because view controller
is complicated.
It's got all the UI, the
buttons, and all the stuff.
You're generally not gonna
be making that in code.
What happens then
after it's created?
The next thing that happens
is if it's being segued to,
it gets prepared.
Like when we prepared the
FaceView Controller there by
setting it to model.
That's the next thing
that happens after it's
initialized.
The next thing that happens
is its outlets get set.
So, for the FaceView,
its FaceView outlet got
set after it got prepared.
Then, it appears and
disappears on screen.
In our example right there,
the master
was constantly appearing and
disappearing on screen.
Every time, on the iPhone, for
example, that we hit happy or
sad, it would disappear.
And the face one
would come on.
And then, we'd hit back and
it would reappear.
By the way, when that happens,
the face one didn't disappear.
Well, it disappeared and
it also got thrown
out of the heap.
Because we reuse
the things we segue to.
But that master,
we don't segue to it.
It sits there as the master in
the split view all the time.
But it's appearing and
disappearing on screen.
So that's a big thing that
happens its lifecycle.
Another thing that happens
during the life time of it is
it's changing its orientation.
We're rotating the landscape.
We're on a iPad and
we're sliding it out as
a tray in portrait mode and
then we rotate to landscape
and it's sitting on the side.
So it's changing its shape.
Even the face view of the iPad
when we're in portrait,
it's big, tall and big.
But then we switch to
landscape it's kind of more
like a square, and
a little smaller.
So it's always
changing geometry.
And then it could be in a low
memory situation as well where
we need to recovery
some memory,
this almost never happens,
but I have to mention it.
It's really maybe not even
part of the view controller
lifecycle but it's a good
place to talk about it,
cuz it's not really
that important.
Let's talk about
the messages that
are sent to invoke methods
in your view controller
when these various
things happen.
So you already know about
your outlets being set.
And you can watch that
with your did sets,
the property observer,
did set.
And you already know
about preparing,
I just showed you about that.
So after those two
steps are done,
you're gonna get this message,
viewDidLoad.
Super important method.
You're only gonna ever receive
it once in the lifetime
of a viewController.
And it's really where
you're gonna put
almost all of your
initialization.
For example, a lot of times
here's where you'll call your
update UI method, the thing
that updates your UI from your
model, very often you're gonna
call that in viewDidLoad.
Cuz now your model is set
because it got prepared
probably, and your outlets
are set because this is how it
always happens after
outlet setting.
Now, one thing not to
do in here though.
Very careful,
listen carefully.
Do not do geometry-based
things in viewDidLoad.
Because when
viewDidLoad happens,
you have not yet had your
final geometry established.
You don't quite know if
you're portrait, landscape,
what device you're on,
you don't know yet.
So do not do things with
your bounds in viewDidLoad.
Many of you will make this
mistake so perk up those ears.
Do not do that.
I'm gonna show you other
methods in the new controller
lifecycle for doing that but
do not it in viewDidLoad.
The next thing I said to you,
appear and disappearing.
You're always appearing and
disappearing on screen.
When you appear,
you're gonna get two messages.
The first is viewWillAppear.
And that's sent to you before
you're actually on screen, but
just very very
soon going to be,
guaranteed you're going
to be on screen soon.
So, what is
viewWillAppear for?
What are you going to do
in a view will appear?
Well one thing is if there's
anything that changes in your
model when you're
not on screen,
maybe your model is
a network database or
something and
it's changing on the screen.
Then when view appear happens
you're going to usually update
your UI from your model.
So maybe you wouldn't do
update UI in viewDidLoad,
you might do it here.
That's if it could change
when it's not onscreen.
A lot of MVCs,
their model only changes
when they're onscreen, so
you wouldn't have to
do anything here.
But if your model can be
changed out from under you
while you're off screen,
then you, when you reappear,
obviously you wanna show the
current state of your model.
So that's a good one.
Another thing you might
do in viewWillAppear
is start something expensive.
Because in viewDidLoad you're
not guaranteed that you're
ever gonna come on screen.
There are MVCs that
occasionally get loaded up,
but then the user clicks
away somewhere else and
you never get shown on screen.
But if viewWillAppear happens,
you know you're
going on screen.
So here you could kick
off something expensive.
Especially kick off
a thread that goes and
does something expensive
in the background.
Cuz we're gonna talk about
multithreading next week and
you're gonna see that anything
that takes any amount of time
or energy on the part of
the processor or the network,
you're gonna wind up
doing a separate thread.
So you might kick off such a
thread here in viewWillAppear.
There's also
an another method,
viewDidAppear which gets into
after you're fully on screen.
The animation to get you
on screen is on screen so
you're there.
And what would you do here?
There's usually not
a lot to do here.
You might start
an animation though.
You've got some MVC that
has some animation going.
And it doesn't make any
sense to start it before it
So once it gets on screen
then you start it going.
gets on screen.
ViewWillAppear and
viewDidAppear happen so
close together, it's probably
not gonna save much to wait
until viewDidAppear to
start the animation,
but eh,
a lot of people will do that,
just to kind of for
clarity of programming.
And then, of course,
you can disappear, and
get the same thing there,
a viewWillDisappear and
a viewDidDisappear.
One thing you notice in all
of these view controller
lifecycle is that
I'm calling super.
You see that?
super.viewWillDisappear, and
I did it for
superViewDidLoad, and
superViewWillAppear.
All of them, all of the view
controller lifecycle methods,
always call super.
You always wanna give your
super class chance to do it.
You'll see actually in
the demo why you do that.
Always do that.
Always do super there.
So in viewWillDisappear,
a lot of times here you're
undoing the things you
did in viewDidAppear.
Like if you had
an animation going,
you're gonna stop it here,
because you're
about to disappear.
Here you might also
start some cleanup.
Your MVC disappeared, and
so, if you allocated some
resources or something that
you don't need, network
connection open or something.
That only makes sense to be
open while your MVC is on,
then here is a good place
where you can shut it down,
and there is a did
version of this as well.
A lot of times people
look at viewDidAppear and
viewWillDisappear as matched,
you know, one undoes
the other, and then the same
thing with viewWillAppear and
viewDidDisappear, those
are gonna undo each other.
I still haven't talked
about geometry until now.
You don't want to be doing
geometry in viewWillAppear.
Your geometry actually
probably is set
in viewWillAppear, but
you shouldn't count on that.
You shouldn't do geometry
in the view wills and
did appears and
disappears either.
Geometry changes: there's
methods especially for it.
One thing to consider is, you
almost never need to write any
code when your
geometry changes.
That's cuz you
have auto layout.
I mean,
look at the app I just wrote.
I've got that sad, happy,
worried block of text, and
when I rotate it it
stays in the middle.
I didn't have to write
any code for that.
And even more
complicated UI's.
You're usually using
auto layout and
it's doing it for you.
So most time you
don't need any code.
But if you did feel like
you needed to do some code
Let's talk a little bit
about how you do that.
There's two methods,
viewWillLayoutSubviews and
viewDidLayoutSubviews.
And these are sent to you.
In between these being sent
to you, Autolayout happens.
So if you wanna get involved
in the geometry change of your
view, before
Autolayout starts,
you can do it in view
will layout subviews.
If you wanna wait until
Autolayout does what it does
and then you wanna
get involved,
you can do it in
viewDidLayoutSubviews.
So when did these get called?
When a bounds of
a view changes,
all of its subviews might
have to be moved around.
Maybe the view
is know tall and
thin, instead of short and
wide.
It's views are gonna have to
be moved to be in the right
place, just like again we
rotated the emotions thing and
we need to move that
stack view up or
all over a little bit
sustained in the middle.
That's primarily
what's going on here,
that's why this method is
called viewWillLayoutSubviews.
Its bounds changed and
now all its subviews
need to be laid out.
What about the things the view
actually draws itself like
the face?
That has nothing
to do with this.
That's a view thing.
That face view, when the
bounds change, if it's content
mode is redraw like we set it
for the face view, it's draw
method's automatically gonna
get called at the new bounds.
So you don't have to
do anything there.
So viewWillLayoutSubviews,
is what happens,
when you have subviews.
This happens at the view
level, so views have a method
for laying out their subviews,
called layoutSubviews.
Subviews, and the
ViewController also gets to
find out when its view,
and by this I mean the var
view in ViewController,
you remember what that var is?
That's that top level view.
There's a var for
that in your ViewController,
it's saying that view is going
to layout its subviews, and
that happens when that top
level view changes, usually
due to rotation but other
things can change it as well.
One thing about these methods
is you should expect that they
may be called all the time.
Don't try to anticipate when
they're going to be called.
Just, whenever they're called,
you do what you're supposed,
you're supposed to do,
and they might be called
repeatedly with the same
bounds.
So the bounds might not
actually have changed,
because this is not called
view bounds changed this is
called viewWillLayoutSubviews
and viewDidLayoutSubviews.
And there are other things
besides bounds changes that
might cause that top-level
view to have to layout it's
sub views.
So expect this to be
called fairly often and
you should always
react to it correctly.
Even if it's called
repeatedly with the same
bounds or whatever.
Now, auto rotation,
the bounds changing by
rotating the device, actually
has a couple of little extra
pieces of interest to it.
The most notable is animation.
So normally when you rotate
it's just going to be
ViewWillLayoutSubviews and
everything's just going to,
auto layout's going to happen,
everything is happening fine.
However that changes, all
those changes are animated.
If you look closely when
you rotate your device, all
the views are kind of flying
across to their new location.
It's really kinda
cool actually.
They're being animated.
They don't just pop
appear in the new place,
they slide over.
Well, you can participate
in that animation,
now we haven't talked
about animation.
We will in about three weeks.
But you can participate
with this method,
ViewwillTransition to
size with coordinator.
And that coordinator has a
little closure you can set on
it that will cause some
animation you want to do
to happen alongside
the rotations animation.
So if you want to animate
moving some user doing
something else that doesn't
happen automatically for you,
which most stuff does
with autolayout,
you can do that here
with this method.
Low-memory:
didReceiveMemoryWarning
will be sent to your
view controller when
the system's low on memory,
it's trying to get some back.
This almost never happens.
I just can't remember the last
time this happened because
the devices have so
much memory these days.
Usually if this happens
though, you wanna pay
attention because you're
using a lot of memory.
If the system is sending this
to you, either you are or
some other app is
using a lot of memory.
By the way, if you are an app
that uses a lot of memory, and
you don't keep it
under control,
the system has the right
to just kill you.
Just kill your app.
And it will do it, absolutely.
Even if you're in
the background,
if you've allocated a ton of
memory and you're being a bad
citizen they just kill you off
to get your memory back what
kinda memory would you free
up if you got this method.
Let's say you had an image
that's not currently on
screen, and you can create
it from a file on disk.
We haven't really talked about
this, but your phone has
permanent storage,
flash memory, and you have,
let's say a JPEG image,
you can just recreate it.
Well, you would definitely
release that here.
Cuz it's not on-screen, and
you can create it real
fast from the disk,
so there's no reason
to keep it around.
So that's something
you could release.
Basically any memory that
you can quickly recreate.
Or that is not currently
on-screen, and
you can create it when
that comes back on-screen.
That's a good
thing to release.
But only big things.
Don't release little
tiny 100 byte things.
No, we're talking images,
sounds, videos,
big ol' things.
There's one other
little thing:
it's not part of the
UIcontroller life cycle, but
every single object that comes
out of a storyboard: views,
view controllers, everything
gets sent awakeFromNib and
they can send it pretty early.
Like right as
soon as they come
out they get sent
awake from nib.
Now you can't use it to like
satisfy the requirement that
all vars are initialized.
But you can use it do early,
really early initialization.
For example remember I
mentioned about you want your
split view controller to
come up showing the face or
come up showing the emotions
instead of showing the face?
In your calculator,
it would come up
showing the calculator,
instead of the calculator's
graph, and
I said you needed to do that
by setting the delegate.
This delegate of
the SplitViewController,
that's something you
might wanna do to make
get that delegate
involved early.
We'll talk about
delegates on Wednesday.
So awake from nib, rarely
used and sometimes overused.
I would say if you could put
it in another method like view
did load or
view will appear or view.
Did layout put it there first.
Don't put it in away fromNib,
that's kind of a last
resort place to put things.
It's probably better
than overriding in it.
But that's the only
thing it's better than.
So here's the summary of
the entire view controller
lifecycle.
You can instantiated,
created out of the storyboard.
You get awake from
nib sent to you.
Segue prep happens.
Somebody prepares you if
you're being segued to
which most MVC's are.
Outlets get set.
Your face view, and
your calculator.
It's your display and
things like that get set up.
ViewDidLoad gets called.
Again, with viewDidLoad,
look at all the things that
happened by the time
viewDidLoad gets called.
It's a great place to
put initialization.
You enter kind of
the normal life cycle
where you're getting
appearing and disappearing.
disappearing with the the will
and did appear and disappears.
Appearing and
Along the way, and
at any time actually,
even before viewDidLoad,
you can get these sent to.
Although that would be rare.
But anytime you can be,
actually I'm not sure you can
get it before viewDidLoad.
Take that back But any time
when view will appear and
disappear is happening,
whether you're on-screen or
not, you could get
viewWillLayout subviews and
viewDidLayout subviews sent to
you, auto-layout happening.
By the way, why would you
ever be sent these methods
when you're not on-screen?
Well, the system might be
preparing to animate you
coming on-screen.
When the system
animates things,
one of the ways it can do
it is having you draw one
orientation, have you
draw in the other, and
then it kind of moves the bits
from one to the other.
That's one kind of
animation can do.
So you might be off screen,
and it's asking you for
both of those.
So it sends you this twice,
once to get this
orientation and draw, and
then once to get this into
orientation and draw.
And then when you
come on screen,
it animate you from
one to the other.
So, that's why you can
get this at any time
on screen or off.
Also at any time you could
get a low memory warning.
And then you're done.
It leaves the heap when it
goes off screen if it was
segued to, as long as it's not
itself segued into something.
But when it's done
it gets thrown out.
Okay, so
I'm gonna show you a demo that
will make all of this
a lot more concrete.
Let me go through the rest
of this in case I don't get
back to the slides,
I think we will, because
I think we're gonna have time
to do this other, topic.
After the demo,
I'll come back and
start to talk about memory
management, hopefully.
On Wednesday, extensions,
protocols, delegation,
that thing I was telling
you you'll need to know for
your split view thing, if you
wanna do that extra credit.
And we'll start talking
about scroll view,
more complicated object.
On Friday,
important one on Friday,
if you want to do
the extra credit,
about performance in
the calculator graph.
So you definitely wanna
show up for that one.
And then next week we'll
start into multi threading,
table view,
a whole bunch of cool stuff.
Alright, so
let's do this demo here.
I'm gonna go to our face view,
same thing we were just in,
this face it app.
And I'm gonna drag in a little
piece of code I wrote,
which I'm gonna show you here.
Let's get out navigator back
here, put this in here.
So I'm just gonna
drop this in here.
By the way when
you drag in code,
you probably want to do
copy items, if needed.
Otherwise, it's gonna be kind
of linked to the other one,
if you change it in
the other place,
it's gonna be changing here.
Can be kinda causing
unexpected results often.
I put this in here.
Let's look at this little
class I just dropped in here,
it's called
VCLLoggingViewController.
It's a subclass of
UIViewController.
Logging view controller and
it logs the VCL methods.
View controller
life cycle methods.
So it basically just
overrides every single one.
View will appear, view layout
subviews away from nib.
It even tells you when
it left the heap.
It's overriding init here, and
it just prints out where it,
what happened.
So it just sits there
on the console,
printing out everything
that happened.
It's a little bit cool,
because it shows you
the instance of each of them.
So you can see instances
coming and going,
as they get segued to,
and then come off.
It also kinda indents it over
time, so you can, when you
click some, you can see
a bunch that happen together.
Now the way we're gonna use
this is we're just gonna make
this class be the super class
of both of our controllers.
So we're gonna make that into
a VCL login view controller.
And we're gonna make this into
And right there, you can see
why we always wanna call super
in all of our view
control methods.
Cuz if we did any of
these view controller
life cycle methods, and
we were subclassing from
VCL login view controller,
if we don't call super,
it not gonna get logged.
And it's not unusual to
come along later and
pop the different kind of view
controller in between you and
UI view controller.
Some view controller that does
something like logging or
something else.
All right, so that's it.
That's all we need to
do to make this work.
So I'm gonna go ahead and
run, we'll stick
with iPhone 7 plus.
Let's go ahead and
get the console up here.
Here we go.
This came up, and
we're already seeing a lot of
view controller lifecycle
stuff happening here.
All right, we have our
EmotionsViewController and
our FaceViewController,
these two view
controllers get emitted.
They come out of
the storyboard, and
they initialize with
this init with coder.
And that's the one that things
come out the interface
builder.
They both get awakeFromNib,
you see that?
And then the emotions one,
first, gets viewDidLoad.
Then it gets
viewwillAppear(animated =
That's because we're just
starting up our app, so it's
false).
not sliding in on a navigation
controller or something.
It's just appearing,
so it's not animated.
Then notice, it gets laid out
twice, both at the same size,
295 x 414,
which is this size right here.
It gets look, done twice.
Some animation,
I don't know wha's going on,
Again, Why?
why i's doing that.
But you don't care,
just be careful that those
layouts can happen repeatedly.
Now here is face view
controller, it gets loaded.
It's told it's going to
appear, it will appear.
And it gets laid out once.
Then they both get DidAppear,
and now they're on screen.
So this is kind of exactly
what you'd expect.
Now let's rotate this thing,
so
that we go to portrait mode.
And we're not gonna
see the master.
We're only gonna see
the details here.
So here,
the master disappears.
So this is, see the dash?
That's what happened
when I did that rotation.
So this is all the new stuff.
Now notice that
the EmotionViewController
immediately is
told that there's going to
be a rotation animation.
And it gets a chance to
participate in the animation.
The FaceView gets re-laid
out in its new size.
It's tall now, so
it gets laid out, so
it gets
viewWillLayoutSubviews.
The Emotions Controller is
told that it will disappear.
So it's going to disappear.
Notice the animated faults,
that's cuz the animation in
that rotation case is handled
by the rotation animation.
So it's not sliding in or
out but it is getting animated
out of there but
by the rotation animation.
Then we have
the face view controller
being laid out again.
Now we're getting
the EmotionsViewControllers
being getting it's chance to
animate alongside
the rotation, right here.
We've got a couple of
spurious things here from
the iOS new UIKit,
we can get rid of those.
And then the animation ends
for both of those controllers.
Make sense?
Now I'm gonna click this
emotions thing, and
go back to the master and
watch what happens.
Okay, so
we go back to the master.
FaceViewController was
told it would disappear,
of course, cuz it did,
does disappear.
The emotions one is told
that it will appear,
it's laid out in this
new tall arrangement.
And then the face view
controller told it,
was disappeared and
the emotion view controller
was told it disappeared.
Now let's go, bring one back.
You can see, look,
FaceViewController(2).
A new FaceViewController
was created,
because we segued to it,
so it created it.
You see that?
And in fact, if we go back and
forth, we'll see that we're
getting new
FaceViewControllers each time,
FaceView three.
And look at the old one's,
FaceViewController
3 left heap, they're
gonna thrown out beneath.
So I'll be posting
all this code.
You can drop this
logging view controller.
Actually you can drop it
into your calculator,
if you wanted, and try and
watch it bring things on and
off screen etc.
Let's go back to
the slides here.
Let's talk about
our next topic,
which is memory management.
We've kind of avoided
this topic so far but
i's an important
topping topic.
If you have a reference
counted data structure,
a class tha's
the only reference,
well i's not the only data
counting reference structure
as you'll see in a second.
But if you have a reference
counting thing, and it lives
in the heap, how do you
know when to get rid of it?
We saw in that demo I just
did the faceview controller
left the heap.
How did it know to
leave the heap?
Because we don't do anything
to tell it to leave the heap.
We just are using it, and
when we're not using it
anymore it goes away.
Well, of course, you know
one way to make things leave
the heap, it's called
garbage collection.
How many people know what
garbage collection is,
have heard that phrase before?
So, more than half of you,
so that's good.
Runtimes like Java,
do garbage collection.
It's a perfectly
fine way to do it.
It involves going
through the heap and
kind of marking the use
of everything and
then sweeping through and
getting rid of stuff
that's not used.
Swift doesn't do any of that,
it uses a totally different
mechanism called
Automatic Reference Counting.
Basically every time
you create a var or
a let that points to
something in a heap,
Swift goes over somewhere and
makes a mark.
And another one,
there's another one.
And it keeps track of it until
there aren't anymore of those
lets and vars.
It erases them as
those vars go away.
Like, maybe they're
a var in another object
that leaves the heap.
So now that var is no longer
pointing to this other object.
So it's basically keeping
track of all the vars unless
they point to
something in the heap.
And when no one
points to any more,
it lets it out of the heap.
Now why is this good?
It's very predictable
memory usage.
You know exactly when things
are gonna leave the heap.
They leave the heap as soon as
nobody points to them anymore.
What's also great about it,
is that you almost have to
do nothing in your
code to make this work.
It's just automatic.
That's why it's called
automatic reference counting.
You can get involved however.
And the way you can get
involved is by influencing
the way that arc works.
And you do that with
three keywords in Swift
called strong,
weak and unowned.
And I actually told you and I
was gonna tell you about these
back in the very first
lecture, you remember when we
made the outlet for
display, it was weak.
Remember that?
That's this weak right here.
So the strong,
weak and unknown.
So let's talk about
each of those.
Strong, this is normal
reference counting.
If you have a strong var or
strong let to something in
the heap, then that thing
will stay in the heap,
as long as that var exists,
it's strongly holding
that thing in the heap.
This is the default.
You don't even ever type this
keyword, cuz it's the default.
Every var, unless you say it's
weak, is going to be strong.
So it's simple.
Works magically.
Then there's weak.
Now weak is a really
interesting keyword in Swift.
When you put weak
on top of a var,
it says, well I'm looking at
this thing in the heap but
if no one else is
interested in the heap then
you can throw it out of
the heap and set me to nil.
So weak only works
with what type?
>> Optional.
>> Optional, exactly,
cuz you have to be
able to set it to nil.
So only optionals can be weak.
So the display outlet
in your calculator,
it was a weak UI label
exclamation point,
which means it was
an optional UI label.
And so it was weak.
So what does that mean?
That means if
that UI label for
some reason ever,
everyone else threw it out,
then that display var would
be set to nil, automatically.
Now, why does that display
var set itself weak?
Why does it say weak?
Well, because the thing it's
pointing to is that view
hierarchy.
The view hierarchy that has
all the calculator buttons and
the display and all in there.
And if that view hierarchy
stops pointing to it,
that means it's gone, and
so the display outlet is no
longer interested in trying
to set numbers in it, and
things like that,
because it's gone.
So, when you have a var that
points into a very strongly
held data structure that you
completely depend on for
your semantic meaning
to mean anything
then you can make it weak.
And so we're perfectly fine if
that display gets at the nil
if the view hierarchy no
longer points to that UI label
because it's probably
meaningless at that point.
So we don't usually
use weak that much.
A lot of times we'll use
it to keep from having
one object pointing to
another strongly and
having that object point
back to this one strongly.
That's very bad situation.
That's called a memory cycle.
That's gonna keep both of
those objects in the heap
forever, because there's
always gonna be a strong
pointer to each of them.
Cuz they each point
to each other.
So either of them can
leave the heap and
free up their pointer
to the other one.
Unless you set one,
like they're optionally set
one to nil or something.
So if you had
a situation like that,
you could use weak to break
that cycle by having one
of the pointers be
a weak pointer.
That would allow it
possibly to happen.
And I'm gonna show you
an example here of another
case where making that kind of
memory cycle is super easy.
And that's bad that it's easy.
Because you can get the cycles
where things are being
held in memory.
The last one is unowned.
Unowned means, "Hey, automatic
reference counter, Don't worry
about this one, I'll take care
of it, I'll make sure I never
use it when it's not pointing
to something in the heap".
This one can be
quite dangerous.
We almost never use this.
It would really only be used
to break one of these memory
cycles, and it can only be
used to make a memory cycle
when you're 100% sure
that you know who's
using that pointer, because
automatic reference counting
is not going to be counting
it as a strong reference, and
it's also not going to check.
And so if you use it, and
that thing you're pointing to
has left the heap,
it will crash your program.
So that's what unowned is.
Now, since unowned just
crashes your program if you
try to use it and
it's not in the heap,
it's not an optional.
There is no setting to nil,
it's always assumed
to not be nil.
And if it's ever nil and
that code executes,
bam, it crashes.
So unowned,
I will show you how we
use unowned in a moment.
It's only to break cycles.
Now, closures have
an interesting attribute
about them, which hopefully
you read about in your reading
assignment, that really has
a lot to do with this strong,
weak, and unowned business.
And then what goes on inside
of a closure is that a closure
captures all the references
inside of it.
It captures them, and makes
a strong pointer to them.
So, if you reference
something inside a closure,
remember what closures are.
Open curly braces, and
we have some code in
there like we had in our
operations table of
our calculator brain.
So inside that closure,
inside those curly braces you
reference some reference type,
something that's in the heap.
That closure is itself
a reference type.
It lives in the heap and
it's going to keep a strong
pointer to the other thing.
And the problem comes if that
other thing has a strong
pointer back to that closure.
Because now you have
a memory cycle.
The closure is keeping that
object in and that object that
has a pointer to the closure
is keeping the closure in.
They are keeping each
other in memory.
Now neither of them
can ever leave.
It's called a memory cycle and
it's really easier memory
cycle in a closure,
as you'll see.
So, here is an example
with our calculator.
Let's say I added a new method
to my calculator brain called
addUnaryOperation where
I allow people to
add new operations to
my operations table.
Right now we don't allow that
because it's all private.
But let's say I had a public
method, addUnaryOperation.
You could add a new operation.
Wouldn't that be cool?
Yeah, that would be cool.
Let's see what it
would like for
a view controller
that wanted to, for
example, add a unary operation
which is square root, but
it turns the display green.
I call it green square root.
So, what will it look like to
write something like that?
Well, I would call
addUnaryOperation,
give it some symbol.
I'm gonna have it look like
a green square root but
it's pushing it there but it's
kind of what it looks like.
And it would pass in
the operation for
green square root.
Now just a couple of cleanup
things before that here.
This is that operation
argument to addUnary
operation.
And as we know,
we could use trailing
closure syntax here to get
rid of that operation colon.
We just close it, and
since the closure is the last
argument, we just put it after
the end of the parenthesis.
Remember that from when I
talked about filter and map?
So we could do that here,
so that cleans it up.
Also, of course,
we could let Swift infer the
types here and just use $0.
Everyone understand
this code up here?
Could not be simpler, right?
I'm just adding this Unary
operation, green square root.
And all it's doing is setting,
this, I'm doing this from
my view controller, so it's
setting the displays color to
green And
returning square roots,
the same as square root, but
the display is just green.
Now, this will not compile.
Why will this not compile?
Let us look and see why not.
It's because it's gonna say
you have to explicitly say
self dot there because I want
you to understand that you
are capturing a strong pointer
to yourself In this closure.
So that in case somehow
you point to this closure,
which our view
controller does,
because our view controller
has the calculator brain,
calculator brain has
the operations table,
the operations table
has this closure in it.
So I'm pointing to
that indirectly
from my View Controller, and
it's pointing now back at me.
Self dot,
it's gonna capture self.
Self is a pointer to myself,
my own View Controller.
Now I've created
a memory cycle.
Yep.
Everyone understand
what's going on there?
The closure lives in the heap.
The View Controller
lives in the heap.
They're now pointing
to each other.
The closure's pointing
directly to the view
controller and the view
controller's indirectly
pointing to the closure
through the calculator brain,
through the operations table.
This operation
they've gotta add in.
So let's talk about how
we break this cycle
because since it's so
easy to do we need to be able
to break it easily as well.
Well first thing
we're going to do,
is we're going to create
a special local variable.
So closures allow you
to before the word in,
put open square bracket,
a list of special variables.
These are just little local
variables that just live for
this closure only.
Now these variables
can have any name.
And you can set them to any
value you want that's in
the scope here.
So I've created a local
variable called me and
I've set it equal to self.
So that's fine,
"me" is a local variable,
it's going to be of
type view controller,
it's added to myself and so
now I can use me in there and
you already used self so
I've replaced self with me.
That doesn't help break
our cycle at all.
However, what if I
made that me variable,
not self but me, be unowned?
If I make that
thing be unowned,
now it's not going to
create that strong pointer.
Because me It lives
in the heap, but
automatic reference counting
doesn't reference count it, so
it pays no attention to it.
Now what that
would mean though,
is that if this code
were executed, and me,
which is the view controller
cuz I set it equal to self, if
the view controller were out
of the heap, this would crash.
But that's perfectly
fine here.
Do you see why that's fine?
When would a calculator
operation ever be executed
if the view controller
is not even in the heap?
It's impossible.
The view controller provides
all the UI that causes this
thing to be executed.
There's absolutely no
way that can happen, so
it's perfectly fine
to say unowned here.
And that would break
the cycle nicely.
But let's talk about
another way to do it.
By the way, it doesn't
have to be called 'me',
I could say 'unknown
self' equals 'self'.
In other words, the local
variable can shadow or
have the same name as the more
global variable 'self'.
So I could say unknown
self equals self, and
in fact if I just say unknown
self that's the same as
saying 'unknown
self equals self.
So this is a lot of times
how we'll break a cycle,
we'll say unknown self and
that basically means inside
this enclosure, you can assume
that self is in the heap.
Now let's talk about
breaking it with weak.
So I can also say weak self.
And that means that self is
now a local variable in this
closure that's an optional
view controller.
And if it's not, if that view
controller is not in the heap,
this variable self, which is
different from the global cell
is going to be nil.
So this is a safe
way to do it.
But of course since
it's an optional,
we can't just say
self.display,
right there we have to say
optional chained self.display.
So that if this
closure executes and
the view controller is not in
the heap, self question mark
will be nil and it will not
execute the rest of that line.
It'll still return
the square root,
but it won't turn
the thing green because
this view controller's
not even there.
So that's how we can
use weak to do it.
And sometimes we use weak,
and we could create anther
variable, and
often we'll do this.
This might be the most common
way to do it right here,
is to say weak
weakself equals self.
And so,
weakself is this Argument,
is this local variable
inside the closure only
that is a weak
version of Self.
Okay, that's kind of clearer
what's going on than if
you just say weakSelf.
Then it's like self is
an optional, it's weird.
Now at least you have
a different variable called
weakSelf, all right.
Okay, so let's go in
the last couple minutes and
just do this in
the Calculator.
Let's do exactly what I talked
about, this green square root.
I'm just gonna go back
to our calculator here.
Where is our calculator?
Here somewhere.
There it is.
We haven't seen this
code in a while.
You've seen it a lot.
I haven't seen it
in a long time.
All right, so
here's our calculator, and
I told you I'm just going
to add this new func.
Add unary operation.
And it's going to take
the symbol that we
want to have it be this in
there, so it's gonna be like
the green square root, or
whatever we call it there.
And actually, probably we
wanna say something like named
symbol, that's probably be
a little better naming there,
and that's a string.
And it's going to
take an argument,
let's make more space here,
which is the operation.
We don't really need to have
an external name because we're
probably gonna use trailing
closure syntax there to do it.
But this is just a Double,
returns a Double function.
Hopefully, you're all very
familiar by now with using
a function just as
a type right there.
So we have this
UnaryOperation.
And all we need to do
to make this work is
we have our operations
table down here.
I'm just gonna say
operations sub that symbol =
Operation.unary operation,
where this operation
is the argument.
I mean,
it couldn't be simpler.
Really, that was so simple
because we built such a good
data structure here to store
all of our operations.
Now notice we have
an error here.
You see this has an error.
What's it saying?
Mark this method mutating.
Okay, why is that?
Well that's because we're
changing this operations table
so of course that
has to be mutating.
But that's not the only error,
we've got another error.
What's this saying?
It's saying here that
this parameter operation
Is "escaping".
What that does that mean,
it's escaping?
Let's go ahead and fix it.
It puts this word in here,
@escaping.
Escaping means that
this function,
is escaping these
curly braces.
It is in fact escaping.
Where is it escaping?
It's jumping into here.
Anytime you have a function
that you pass in, and
it gets put in some other data
structure, in other words,
it escapes out of the curly
braces of the method it's in,
you have to mark it escaping
so that you understand and
swift understands that you
are storing that somewhere.
And that's because it might
create a memory cycle
if you do that.
So fix it will automatically
remind you about this so
you don't have to
remember that so much.
We've got this nice
cool new feature and
let's go to our view
controller and add it.
Hey how about we
use view did load.
Here's view did load,
super dot view did load.
I never want to forget that.
So that's going to happen
we're all initialized,
our outlets are set.
Let's just go ahead and call
that addUnaryOperation here.
Let's call it brain
addUnaryOperation.
Is that what I called it?
addUnaryOperation, I don't
know why that's not,
there it did it.
It's just a little slow.
addUnaryOperation takes
the symbol which is named.
And I'm gonna go ahead and
do that green exclamation
point if I can find it here.
Where is that thing?
It's probably pictograph,
maybe, no.
Anyone know where
that would be?
Let's try, what's it called,
checkmark or something.
There it is.
There's our nice
symbol right there.
And let's go and
add that to our UI as well.
Let's go over here
to our story board,
we'll add it instead of Pi.
So, we'll get rid of Pi
instead we'll put that
operation in there.
What was it called again?
Check.
Oops, two of them.
We've got this new
green square root.
We still have the old
square root as well.
But we have to add
this operation and
I'm gonna use that trailing
closure syntax right there.
And of course we know this is,
it's a double takes a double.
And this would be where
the stuff goes in there.
But we can let Swift infer
this, and just use $0,
square root of $0.
So we've done everything
except for the green.
Does everyone agree with this?
I'm adding the unary Operation
named this symbol and here is
the second argument put on
the trailing closure there.
So how do we turn it green?
Well, we just say
display.textColor.
Turns out UILabel has a text
color = UIColor.green.
Now, when we put this
in here like this,
it's gonna complain.
Why?
Because, reference to
property display and
closure requires
an explicit self dot
to make the capture
semantics explicit.
This is Swift
saying watch out.
If you do this, you're going
to capture self right here.
And that is going to
create a memory cycle.
This closure right here,
which lives in the heap,
is pointing to self.
This addUnary operation
is going to cause it,
this closure, to be put in
the operations table which is
pointed to by
the View Controller.
Now they point at each other.
Let's see,
what else did I forget here.
Missing return.
Yes.
Return square root.
Everybody cool with that?
Now, to break that cycle,
we could say, unowned self in.
That's one way to
break the cycle.
We could say, weakSelf = self,
if we do this
one though we're gonna have
to go here and say weakSelf?
Either of those will
break this cycle.
In your homework, I've updated
your homework to say you
cannot have any of these
cycles in your homework.
Okay, in assignment three.
It's in the evaluation
criteria down there.
So I put, posted it on
the forum for that too.
So let's go see if this works.
By the way, what happens if
we don't break that cycle,
view controllers will just
start accumulating in memory.
Because they'll be keeping,
these closures will be
keeping them on our memory.
If you, for example,
had a CalculatorViewController
that was being pushed on
to you know segue two and
then segue away from, it would
not go into out of the heap,
it would stay in
heap in that case.
Right here is our calculator.
So 81 square root is
9 green square root?
Woo hoo.
Square root and
turned to green.
Okay, that's it,
see you next time.
If you guys have any
questions, I'm here as always.
>> For more, please visit
us at stanford.edu.