翻译：默默熊
Stanford University.
斯坦福大学
>> All right, well,
welcome to Stanford CS193P,
欢迎
Developing Applications for
iOS, winter of 2017.
This is Lecture number 9.
这堂课是第九讲
And today we have only one
topic which is Table View.
今天我们只有一个主题，就是 Table View
And I'm gonna go through a
bunch of slides to talk about
我们先过几页幻灯片
the concepts of it.
And then we're gonna
have a humongous demo
然后我们会有一个很长的演示
that we're gonna build
a Twitter client and
我们会使用Table View
it's gonna use Table View and
来创建一个 Twitter 的客户端
some other things that we've
learned, like Text Field.
我们还会学些别的，像 Text Field
And Table View, what is it?
什么是 Table View?
You've seen a Table View
in all sorts of iOS apps.
我们在许多iOS应用中都见过Table View
It's just this UI where
there's a list of things.
就像这样，是一个事物的列表
There's really two different
kinds of looks to Table View.
Table View 有两种样式
There's the kind
on the left there,
左边这种
which we call plain style.
我们称之为简单样式
Plain style is just
a list of things.
就是一个项目的列表
And it might be collected into
groups like little sections.
它还可能包含一些分组
But it's mostly just
a big long list.
但大部分时候就是一个长长的列表
On the right side,
is called a grouped style.
右边我们称之为分组样式
Where the sections
in the table,
表里的这些区段
you're more obviously
disconnected from each other.
很显然，相互是分开的
They have you know,
big gaps in between.
相互之间有很大的缝隙
Normally the plain style
we use for dynamic data.
通常，简单样式用于动态数据
Data that might have any
number of items in there.
就是其中可能包含任意的条目数
The group style we tend
to use for static data,
对于静态数据我们倾向于使用分组样式
where we know exactly what
rows are gonna be in there,
这种情况下，我们清楚地知道会包含多少行
and exactly what's
gonna be in them.
以及每一行的具体内容
So let's talk about the names
of all the parts of
好，让我们谈谈Table View各个部分的名称
a Table View, so that as
I'm explaining all this,
这样我讲解的时候
you'll know what
the terminology is.
你知道我在讲什么
First we have a table header.
首先，我们有一个表头
That's a UIView.
那是一个 UIView
There's only one of them.
表头只有一个
It sits at the very
top of the table.
它位于Table的最顶端
This is where,
as you'll see in the demo,
you might put a search field
or something that searches
to find what's in your table
or something like that.
And similarly,
there's a footer view.
类似的，这儿还有一个 footer view
Rarely see this used.
这个很少见到
But it's just a UIView
that sits at the bottom
但这就是一个在底部的UIView
And in between, there are
these things called sections.
中间这些被称为表的区段
of the table.
So a section is just
a combination of a header and
a footer,
which are usually strings, but
also could be UIViews, and
then any number of rows.
That's what we call a section.
So that's a section
right there.
This is the section header for
the two sections that I have
showing in this table, right,
where it says Header 0.
And these are sections
footers for
the two sections that I have.
These two sections happen to
both have the same numbers of
rows in each which is two but
a section, one section have
a 100 rows, and one could have
just 1, it's perfectly fine.
This right in here,
we call a table cell.
C-E-L-L, cell, and
it's the UIView,
actually UITableViewCell,
it's the name of the subclass
that's in there.
And this is the thing that's
gonna draw the data that's at
a particular row.
And we're gonna see
how that works.
By the way, along the bottom
you're seeing source code that
kind of corresponds
with these things.
Don't worry I'm gonna get back
to showing you all that stuff
in later slides.
So this is the naming we use
to name all the parts of
a table view.
And this is in plain style.
All the same names
work in group style.
Everything just kinda
looks a little different.
All right,
still have a header, footer,
sections, all the same.
Just a little
different UI look.
Now, tables can have
sections or not.
You don't have to
have any sections, so
the table on the left is just
a whole list of cities and
the countries they're in and
just a big long list.
On the right is kind of
the same kind of list but
you can see that they're
grouped into sections there by
country, right.
So Japan there, Mexico, etc.
So sections are optional,
not optional in the case
of an option, but
sections you can have them or
not, it's totally up to you.
The type of the cell,
like each row, there are four
kinda pre-defined types and
then there's a custom type.
The four pre-defined types are
subtitle where you just got
like a title and
a little smaller text
subtitle under it.
There's default which
is the same except
there's no little
subtitle thing.
There's value 1 and value 2,
which is just like subtitle,
it's just that the little
thing underneath is in
a different spot,
it's either blue and
to the left or it's kind of
grayed off into the right but
i's just how its laying out
the basic information there.
Now a custom cell can
have arbitrary UI
in it as you will see.
So how do we use a table view?
Okay, a table
view is a UIView,
i's actually subclass
UIScrollView because i's
scrolling through
all those rows.
Well 99% of the time, we use
the special ViewController
So how do we do it?
called UITableViewController
in UIKit.
And UITableViewController is
just a convenient package to
use UITableView in and its
self.view is a UITableView.
Okay, so you would only use
a UITableViewController
when your entire self.view
is going to be filled
with a table view.
And you can add one into your
storyboard just by dragging it
out as we always do.
There's a thing called
Table View Controller and
it's just gonna drag it out.
Now it's a controller,
so when you drag it out,
it looks like an MVC.
But inside of that MVC,
there is a table view
sitting there, okay?
And so what you see
here the controller,
is a UITableViewController,
and the self.view of
it is a UITableView.
Okay, subclass
of UIScrollView.
Now like any other
ViewController,
if you're going to do
anything with this thing,
you need to subclass it,
right?
Just like you create a
calculator view controller or
graph view controller,
you need to subclass, your
UITableViewController as well.
And you do it the same way,
right?
New files are created.
It's gonna be
a Cocoa Touch Class of course.
It's gonna be a subclass
of UITableViewController.
Make sure you pick that.
Don't say it's a subclass
of UIViewController.
It has to be a subclass
UITableViewController if you
want it to work.
And then you just set it
in the identity inspector
Just exactly like any other
controllers, just that it has
to be your class.
to be subclass
UITableViewController.
This UITableViewController
subclass
is also going to serve as
the data source and delegates.
Okay, the data source is just
a special kind of delegate for
getting the data in the table.
For the table view
that's inside of it.
So, we're gonna talk
a lot more about that
down the road here.
By the way, if you right click
on the view controller and
you get that black window to
come up, you can actually see
it, if you look down
towards the bottom there,
you see data source and
delegate.
Their properties and
they're pre wired up for you.
If you use this
UITableViewController thing,
just pre-wires it up.
That the controller
is the delegate and
data source of the table view.
If you don't use
UITableViewController,
by the way,
this kinda pre-packaged one?
Then you'll have to wire
up the data source and
delegate, you know,
either in code by saying
tableView.delegate = self or
something like that.
You'll have to do it yourself
but 99% of the time you're
just gonna use this
UITableViewController.
Cuz usually the best UI for
a table view, is for
it to take over
the whole screen.
For it to fill the whole
screen, it's rare that you can
have a table view in
part of your screen.
So you can edit the attributes
of the table view itself,
of course,
by just clicking on it and
bringing up
the attributes inspector.
One thing that's a little
frustrating about a table view
is you've got the table view
cells, which are UIViews.
And then you've got the table
view kind of that they're
contained in.
That's a UIView also.
And then you've got the table
view controller behind it.
And you wanna set attributes
on all of these things.
So don't forget you can do
Ctrl+Shift+Left-click, and
it'll put up a little menu.
Says, okay, what thing under
the mouse do you want?
Do you want the cell, the
table view, or the controller?
And so that'll help you dig
down to the thing you want.
All right, but
once you have it selected,
whichever one you want,
like the TableView or
the Controller or the Cell,
you can inspect it of course.
Now, one important thing is
this grouped versus plain that
I showed you at
the very beginning.
So here I'm gonna switch
this one which is plain
over to grouped.
So I'm just picking grouped
in the style there,
in the inspector.
Another important attribute
is dynamic versus static.
So dynamic is all the contents
are coming from some database.
And static is, I'm gonna put
all the content right here in
the story board, okay?
So here we'll switch
this one over to static.
So this is now a static,
grouped table view.
And I told you that
usually static table views
are grouped, and usually only
grouped ones are static.
So usually these
kinda go together.
They don't have to, they're
separate properties, but
they generally go together.
Now the UI for these rows,
most of the time you're
just going to build
by dragging UI in.
So here I'm just dragging the
label in here, and you know,
maybe I'll change the name of
the label, dragging the UI
switch in there, cuz I want
to set up some settings.
Often times, by the way, this
thing is used for settings and
things like that.
And then if I want to talk
to these switches and
labels that I brought in
there, I'm actually gonna
create outlets to my
UITableViewController.
And since what's in
this table is fixed for
all time in the storyboard.
I'm building it
in a storyboard,
that's perfectly fine.
So I would just Ctrl + drag
from them to my controller,
which will work, and then
I can create an outlet for
example, my feature
enabled switch outlet and
it'll create an outlet here.
And then in my code and
my controller,
I can obviously do whatever
I want to that switch.
So, it's almost like when you
have a static table view, it's
almost just like a normal view
that you would build UI in.
It's just that it's
divided into these rows.
Which is nice for something
like settings, right?
If you think about
the settings app, right,
on your phone.
It's got a lot of UI that's
kind of in rows right, and
in tables.
So, if you really wanna see
how static table view works,
get your phone out, go to
the general settings app and
just look around in there.
That is table view after table
view after table view where
the rows are static built in
some storyboard somewhere by
Apple.
All right, so that's pretty
much it for static table.
These are pretty
straightforward to do.
So I'm gonna clear
this UI out of here,
this featured enabled out of
there, then we're gonna talk
about a different kind of
table view, which is dynamic.
So a dynamic table view, you
set it here by picking dynamic
property, prototypes, rather,
there instead of static cells,
really is a totally different
kind of animal, and
I'm gonna switch back to plain
style because usually dynamic
tables are plain style.
These rows now instead of
being something you're
gonna build the UI and
they're static,
instead they're prototypes.
They're things that are gonna
be copied for every row.
So whatever UI you would
build in one of these rows.
And you can build
customize UI,
like we saw with
the static one.
It's gonna be copied for
every single row.
So these are prototypes.
You see what I
mean by prototype?
It's like a template that's
gonna be copied over and
over and
over to make your table.
So that's a really
different kind of
way of looking at things.
Because this data that's
gonna go into these rows is
coming from some database
somewhere probably and
filling out all
this information.
So it's a little more
complicated to build
a table like this,
but not a lot more.
So you can click on any
one of the cells and
you can inspect it, right?
The prototypes that you want.
For example you could change
its type from being custom
to being subtitle.
All right, so here's what
a subtitle cell looks like.
Remember I showed you in
the very second slide,
it's one of
the pre-canned types.
And it just has, you know,
a text field, like a little
smaller text field.
So that's a subtitle.
You can also set with
accessory there,
a little thing that can
appear on the right.
It could be a little check
mark that you turn on and off.
It could be
a disclosure indicator,
which you want to put there if
clicking on this row is going
to segue.
Okay, that little disclosure
indicator is just a little,
kind of gray arrow thing
that lets the user know,
hey if I click on this row,
it's going to segue.
There's also kind of a special
one called detail disclosure.
And the detail disclosure
looks like this,
it's a little "i" in a circle.
And what's really cool about
that is you can segue by
clicking on the row, but if
you click on the little blue
I, it does a different segue.
Okay, so you kind of have
your row doing two different
segues, depending on whether
they touch on the little i or
touch somewhere else.
You see the little gray
arrow next to the i?
That's the disclosure
indicator.
So if I click on this row,
it's going to segue.
If I click on the little i,
it's gonna do some
different segue.
Maybe bring up some modal
panel with some information or
something like that.
We'll talk about how
that works in a second.
All right, so I'm gonna
go back to non-details,
go ahead and
get rid of that thing.
But another style besides
the four pre-canned
ones I talked about in
the beginning of this lecture
that you can pick is custom.
So custom means that,
that's just a UIView,
that you can build
any UI you want.
Again similar to
that feature-enabled
with the switch that I showed.
But again, this UI is going
to get copied over and
over and over for
Notice, by the way,
there are multiple prototypes.
That means you can have
different setups of UI
that you could use for
different rows, okay?
And we're gonna name each
of these prototypes so
that in our code, we can pick
which prototype we want for
a certain row.
It will copy that prototype.
Now, these custom cells,
you can resize them.
You can drag stuff into them,
build UI you want.
Here, I've built this
complicated UI with text
fields and an image.
This is very similar to a UI
that I'm gonna build in
All right, now when you build
this UI you're gonna want
the demo.
to use proper layout.
So stack views and hooking it
to the edges just like you did
with the calculator or
even stuff on the inside.
I'll show you a little
bit of that today,
a little more auto layout.
Because if you do that, then
the table view will be able to
figure out the size this thing
needs to be dynamically.
Okay, if you don't do
the right auto layout then you
kind of just have to fix
the height of the rows, and
I'm going to talk about
that in a minute as well.
So generally you want to
do auto layout properly
in there if you can.
Now ther's no way I
could wire up these
elements directly
to my controller.
Do you see why?
Because ther's only one
outlet in my controller for
one of these labels.
But there
are hundreds of rows.
So how is my one outlet gonna?
It can't be hooked up
to 100 at once, okay.
But I still need outlets
because how am I gonna
set these things?
All right, and so
the way we're gonna deal with
that is we're gonna wire these
things up to outlets in
the UITableViewCell.
The UIView that contains them.
So I told you that
this cell is a UIView,
a UITableViewCell, and it
contains all of these things,
these labels and stuff.
So, we're gonna have
outlets in that.
Now this is the first
time you've ever seen
outlet in anything but
a controller and pretty much
this is the only other time
you're gonna have outlets.
You can't have outlets
in a regular view, but
you can have outlets in these
special table view cells.
All right, so let's see a
little bit of how that works.
So, one thing,
if you're gonna have outlets,
you know you're gonna need
to have subclass, right?
Just like you have
a controller, you can't use
a generic UIViewController,
can't put any outlets in that;
you have to subclass it so you
can wire out, same thing here.
You're gonna have to
make a custom subclass,
a UITableViewCell.
You do that with New File.
It is still a Cocoa Touch
Class, but here you're going
to choose UITableViewCell
as the super class,
not UITableViewController.
UITableViewCell.
And again UITableViewCell is
a subclass of UIView also,
All right, so you're going
to pick a UITableViewCell,
by the way.
call it something like
MyTableViewCell or whatever.
And then you're gonna do the
exact same thing where you're
gonna have that cell selected.
And you're gonna go to
the identity inspector.
And you're gonna change
it from being a generic
UITableViewCell to
being MyTableViewCell.
And this is gonna allow
you to create outlets
In MyTableViewCell to these
things that are contained
inside MyTableViewCell.
Okay, so
now we can wire them up.
So remember that
static elements,
those things I showed
you at the beginning,
those are wired up
to the controller.
Dynamic elements, where
we have these prototypes,
those are wired up to
the TableViewCell outlets.
So what does it look
like to wire them up?
I'm gonna have to do the same
thing with the controller
where I'm gonna get the UI and
the code on screen
at the same time with
the assistant editor.
By the way, when you do that,
if you're in automatic mode,
there, see where
it says automatic?
It's pointing at automatic.
It's not going to bring up the
UITableViewCell, even if you
have the TableViewCell
selected in the UI.
It's still gonna bring
up the controller, okay?
So if you want to wire up
outlets to a TableViewCell,
you have to manually or
forcibly get that
TableViewCell- not
the TableViewController-
TableViewCell, on this side.
So one way you can do it is
by switching from Automatic
to Manual and then navigating
over to finding your
TableViewCell.swift class,
right?
And then choosing that.
And now you're in manual mode,
you've got the TableViewCell
on the right, and
you've got your
storyboard on the left.
So, now you can Ctrl+drag,
right?
You just need to be
able to Ctrl+drag
between them is the problem.
So you gotta have
them both on screen.
All right, so then,
once I have them on screen,
I Ctrl+drag,
just absolutely normally.
And it's gonna do all the
things that an outlet does,
it's gonna ask me,
an outlet or action.
By the way, you can do
outlet or action here.
And it's gonna ask.
So here, I've picked that
photo, the blue thing.
Let's say it's a photo.
And I'm calling this
my photoImageView.
And it creates an outlet here.
Okay, so that's great.
Now this TableViewCell code
can talk to that photo.
The ImageView could for
example set the image or
whatever.
But of course it needs to
know what information to put
in that photo for
that row, right?
This thing is gonna be
repeated 100 times, and
each one needs to know
what its row's photo is.
So you're also gonna need
some public API on your
TableViewCell which gives it
the data it needs to fill up
all its outlets.
Okay, so you're gonna
have some var, which I've
called infoShownByThisCell,
could be of any type you want.
And somebody is gonna set it,
you'll see soon who sets it.
And once it sets it,
now we can update the UI and
put all this information
into the outlets.
Okay, so this is how
the information at each row in
the table is going to be
put into these UI elements.
You all following me so far?
All right, let's talk
about these two protocols,
the dataSource and
the delegate, okay.
They're critical to
making UITableView work.
UITableView is a class that
literally cannot function
without its dataSource and
delegate.
It's not really like split
view controller where, eh, you
don't have to do anything with
a delegate if you don't want,
it'll still work.
This, you really
have to do it.
Especially the dataSource.
If you don't give it
a dataSource, the only
way a table view would work
without its delegate and
dataSource is if it were
purely static table.
Like the table that had
the feature enabled with
the switch.
That you could deal
without the dataSource.
But otherwise, if it's
providing dynamic data,
obviously it needs the data.
And the only way
it can get data is
through its dataSource.
So, as I already told you,
UITableViewController
automatically sets itself as
its delegate and dataSource.
So you can just put your code
for these delegate methods
right in your subclass of
UITableViewController, right.
MyTableViewController, or
whatever, and put it in there.
Also, there's a cool var in
TableViewController called
tableView, which is basically
gonna return self.view, but
as a UITableView.
And that way you can talk to
the UITableView that your
UITableViewController is
controlling.
So when do we need to
implement the dataSource?
Anytime we have dynamic data,
non-static.
There are three really
important methods in this
One is, how many sections
are in my table?
protocol.
Could be one section if
the whole thing is just
a bunch of rows.
How many sections, and
then how many rows
are in each section?
You're gonna be
asked one by one.
How many rows in this section?
How many are in this section?
So it knows how many rows
are in every section.
And then most importantly,
give me one of those
UITableViewCells to
draw this row.
Okay, so for each row that
the TableView wants to draw,
i's going to ask you, okay,
give me a UITableViewCell now,
cuz I'm going to
draw this row.
Okay, so that's how it works,
that's fundamentally
how this works.
Now, all these methods are in
the UITableViewDataSource
protocol.
So let's look at the last one,
the give me a UITableViewCell,
cuz it's the most complicated.
The other ones are super,
super simple.
So the way that you are going
to give a UITableViewCell
back to the TableView when
it's time to draw a certain
row is by a method
being called.
Now, you might be worried
here, it's like woah,
I'm gonna have this big UI
with all these labels and
image views in it, and I have,
what if I have 100,000 rows?
I'm going to make
100,000 views.
Surely that's going to
be terrible performance.
And in fact, that would be
terrible performance, okay.
Views are not cheap.
But no worries, because
all your UITableViewCells,
these UIViews that draw
the rows, they're reused.
So only the visible ones
have UITableViewCells.
As you scroll around, the ones
that scroll off the top
get picked up and put around
and used on the bottom, okay?
And the new data keeps
getting pumped into them.
Do you see what I'm saying?
So those cells, only the,
maybe the ones on
the screen plus two or
three on either side
are actually getting created.
They're just getting reused.
As you scroll up and down,
they keep getting reused.
Now, the thing
about that reuse,
I want you to be
very careful of.
I put it in red.
When I put it in red, you
know that means wake up and
watch out, cuz your homework.
When you're doing
multithreaded things,
you've got to be careful,
because by the time you come
back from something you asked
to do on another thread, your
cell might be reused, okay.
And so you've got to
be prepared for that.
You gotta understand whether
you're still the cell you
thought you were when you
sent something off to go in
another thread.
Okay, so I'm warning you.
So what does this method look
like that the UITableView is
gonna send to its
data source to say,
give me a UITableViewCell?
It's called
cellForRowAt indexPath.
You see it right there.
That's its signature.
It really only has that
one argument, indexPath.
The indexPath is just
a little container of
the section and row.
You could imagine this is
even called cellForRowAt
section and row.
But it just puts them
in one argument called
an indexPath, okay.
And then all you return
is a UITableViewCell.
And it's gonna use that
UITableViewCell to draw
that row.
So it really couldn't
be a simpler API.
It's at the heart of exactly
what it's asking you to do.
Now, what are you gonna
do inside this method?
Well, first you're going to
have to get the data from your
model that you want
to show in that row.
Okay.
And you can do this
any way you want.
I have a very convenient
data structure here called
myInternalDataStructure that
happens to be divided
in sections and rows.
So I can just index into it.
But you might have
a different data structure.
But you've gotta take
the section and row so
that you know which row
you're talking about, and
get the data out
of your model.
Maybe you're doing
a database query.
Maybe you're even doing
a network query in another
thread and it's gonna return
and fill this out, whatever.
You need to figure out
how to get your data.
Now, once you have your data,
you're gonna create a cell.
I'm gonna show you how
to do that in a second.
And then you're just
gonna load up that cell
with the data.
So let's talk about how
we create that cell and
So I'm gonna take this
little piece of code, and
load it up.
I'm gonna keep it on screen
while I go back to showing you
what's happening
in the UI here.
So first let's talk about a
cell that's not a custom cell.
It's just a regular
cell like subtitle.
You see subtitle up there?
Okay, so we're gonna use
this method here called
dequeueReusableCell(withIdent-
ifier: for: indexPath).
And that's just gonna return
us a UITableViewCell.
Now, again, this is
a reused UITableViewCell.
Okay, being reused,
now if this cell, if there's
not enough been created yet,
then it will create one
based on your prototype.
Whatever your prototype
you pick in there.
And you pick which
prototype with this string,
the identifier string
which you set in
the inspector for the cell.
So, it's just in there,
it's called identifier,
the utilities inspector on the
right is inspecting that cell,
that top cell that says title,
subtitle,
it's inspecting that.
And I'm just setting
the identifier of my cell, so
now in my code when I say,
dequeueReuseableCellwithIdent-
ifier of MyCell, it's gonna
make a copy of that prototype.
Unless there's
some to be reused,
then it'll just reuse them.
But until it gets
enough to reuse,
it uses that prototype and
just makes copies
of it as necessary.
Now, this is
a non-custom cell, so
the only, well there's
a few fields you can set.
You can go look at the API for
UITableViewCell to find out.
But the cell, set those two
pieces of text, title and
subtitle there.
You just,
you use textlabel.text and
detailtextlabel.text.
Those are optional,
so they could be nil,
because if there's
a custom cell, for
example, it might be nil.
So anyway that's it,
you just set those,
those are just UILabels.
And so you just set the text,
it couldn't be easier.
And that's true for
all the pre-canned ones,
you're gonna set these.
There is actually, I can show
it, but there's an image also,
that you can set,
a little image in the cell.
And that's also in
the pre-canned ones,
so you could do that as well,
okay?
So that's it,
that's just simple,
that's all you need to
do to provide your data
to the TableViewCell is just
dequeue one of these cells.
Just load it up and
return it, and
now the tableView will
use that to draw.
But let's talk about
a custom cell, so
now I'm talking about
the second row down.
And look at its type,
it's custom- it's not
subtitle- it's custom.
Little different for
a custom cell.
You're still gonna do
dequeueReusableCellwithIdenti-
fier for index path, okay?
But of course you're going to
use a different identifier,
cuz now I'm talking about
the second cell down which I'm
calling my custom cell.
Now here there's no title and
subtitle in that second row.
Presumably there's
that image and
the thing under text under
it and text on the side.
All the things,
whatever your UI switch,
whatever you built
in this custom cell.
And all that stuff has
got outlets hooked up to
the UITableViewCell containing
it, remember all that we did?
So you need to just pass the
data to that UITableViewCell
and it's responsible for
loading up all the UI.
Now how do you do that?
First thing you need to
do is take that dequeued
thing that came back, which
is of type UITableViewCell.
And cast it with "as" to be of
the type of your subclass
of UITableViewCell.
Otherwise you won't be able
to call any of this API.
Okay, so you're just gonna do,
if I can let this cell equal
the dequeued thing
as MyTableViewCell.
Then I'm going to talk to
MyTableViewCell using its API
and set, for example,
infoShownByThisCell to be
the data that's app
that section in row.
Okay, so to go back to
the code I was showing before,
that info shown by the cell
is that var right there.
The var that I made public
in MyTableViewCell.
And then it's gonna update UI
and set all of its outlets and
all of that.
Okay, so that's it,
that how it works.
Those are the two cases,
the kind of pre-canned one and
the custom one.
They're almost identical,
you're still dequeuing cells,
you just set the data
a little bit differently.
Okay, the data source also has
to know how many sections and
rows.
It's really simple,
there's a method called
numberOfSections in tableView.
And that's going
to return int,
how many sections there are.
By the way that
one is optional;
you don't have to
implement that one.
If you don't, it will
assume there's one section,
that all the rows are in
this one big section.
The other one though, which is
numberOfRowsInSection where it
passes you a section number,
and
you have to say how many
rows are in the section.
That is not optional,
that is mandatory, and you
must answer this question for
every single section that you
claim that your table has
with numberOfSections
in table, okay?
So that's it, that's simple,
why does it need to know how
many rows and all of
the sections, by the way?
Cuz it's a scroll view and it
needs to know how big a thing,
it needs to set it's content
size basically, right?
It needs to know how big a
thing it's scrolling over, so
it needs to know.
But it also needs to know when
to ask you for the data and
all that, so it's pretty
obvious it needs to know that.
In a static table by the way,
it's not gonna ask
you these questions.
So don't even
worry about that.
The static table is fixed
in the StoryBoard, so
it's never asking you for
the data.
So it's never gonna ask you
how many rows and sections and
all that stuff there is.
So the summary is you set
the tableView's data source.
That's automatic if you're
using UITableViewController.
You implement numberOfSections
and numberOfRowsInSection.
And then you implement
cellForRowAt.
And give back
a tableView cell,
either a custom subclass
if you're doing custom,
or just setting
the detailed text label and
then the normal text label
if you're not, question?
Okay, so the question is,
what do I answer for
that number of sections
thing if, over time,
my tableView is growing,
right?
Maybe data is coming in
from the network, or
the user is clicking on things
that makes more table happen.
You can answer it that
differently in any time, but
what you're basically saying
is, what if my model changes?
I need my UI, right,
to keep up with it.
If my model gets bigger,
then I need more rows.
Well, you're gonna see that
it's really important to,
every time your model changes,
you need to tell
the tableView about it.
And you're gonna
tell it things like
I've added a new section.
And then it will come back and
ask you all these
questions again, all right.
So, that's how it works.
It might come back and ask
you these questions including
cellForRowAt over and
over and over.
As you tell it that you've
changed your model.
But of course, your model
can change over time.
By the way,
the titles of the sections,
remember when I showed you the
countries and it had Japan and
Mexico as titles.
Those are considered
part of the data.
So, those are part of
the UITableViewDataSource
protocol as well.
This method title for header
or footer in section, and
you pass the section number
and it gives you the thing.
You can also do it with
a view, using the delegate.
But if you want to
just do it as a string,
you'd use the data source.
There's a lot of other
methods in the protocol.
I'm not gonna really
talk about them,
they have to do with things
like deleting rows or
rearranging the rows,
things like that.
If your model allows
those things to happen,
like things being deleted.
Then you're gonna have
to teach yourself this.
Most of you will probably
end up doing this for
your final project.
I'm not gonna ask you to
do it in the homework, but
you'll probably do it for
your final project.
It's extra credit
in the homework,
if you wanna get
a head start on that.
All right let's talk
about seguing from a row.
So I've got a row there, okay,
this one actually has a detail
disclosure in there as well.
And I wanna segue out of that
thing, how do I do that?
Very simple,
I do it just like any other
segueing from the button.
I'm just gonna Ctrl+drag from
the row to the MVC I want to
segue to.
And it's going to put
up this black window.
Now, this black window
is a little different
than other segues.
Because you see it has two
sections, Selection Segue and
Accessory Action, okay?
So the Selection Segue is if
they click on the row and
the Accessory Action
is if they click on
the little accessory button.
But it's just a normal segue,
once you create the segue,
you can click on it and
inspect it.
Just like any other segue,
you can set its identifier
up there to something.
And then you're gonna
have prepare for segue.
So, here I've set
the identifier to be AbcSegue.
So lets take a look
at what prepare for
segue looks like when you're
doing this kinda segue.
It looks almost
exactly the same,
here I've got a prepare for
segue.
I've noticed that
the sender there is Any.
And when you're segueing
into tableView,
what do you think
that Any is gonna be?
UITableViewCell, okay, that
view that contains the row.
So that is going
to be the sender.
Just like a button
is the sender
if you click on a button
to segue, the row,
the UITableViewCell,
is the sender in that case.
So the first thing
you're gonna wanna
do is convert the sender
to a TableViewCell.
And specifically to your
subclass or table view cell.
If you have a custom
cell in case you wanna
do anything that's specific
to your TableView cell.
If not then you can just
do it to UITableViewCell.
And then you wanna get
the index path of that cell so
that you know what row
where you're segueing from.
Because every row, you can
click on it, it will segue.
So, you need to
know which row.
And you do that by
And you can't pass any to
that, you have to pass
UITableViewCell or subclass
thereof, indexPath(for: cell).
Now, I'm gonna give you
one of those index path
things remember?
and row.
Then, you're gonna get
your seguedToMVC as usual.
And you're going to prepare
your Segue to public API, and
you're going to do it using
the data in your model based
on the section and
row that was clicked on.
Got it?
So pretty easy segue from it.
So yes you're gonna use
your public API of your
segue to MVC.
What about the table
view's delegate?
We talked about the data
source; what about
the table view's delegate?
It's got a kind of
a miscellaneous
bunch of stuff in there but
generally the delegate
is talking about how the table
view is displayed, and
the data source is what data
is actually in the table.
Okay so that's the difference.
So the delegate we're
talking about things,
yeah they're usually
the same object.
So the delegate also has all
the will, did, should things.
That you could watch what's
happening in the table view.
This row did get selected,
things like that.
For example, here's table
view target action, so
if when you click on a row,
if you don't want a segue, but
you just want to be target
action like a button,
well you can't really do that.
You can't do target action
because a row is not
a UIButton.
But you can implement this
delegate method tableView
didSelectRowAt indexPath.
And when someone
touches on that row,
this is gonna get called.
So, it's just like
target action right.
It told you what happened.
So, now you can look at the
index path row in section to
know which row was selected so
we call that target action.
You did the same thing
with that detail
disclosure by the way.
So I'm gonna click on the
detail disclosure we're gonna
get this method in
your delegate called
accessoryButtonTappedForRow-
With indexPath.
Okay, so now you know
which row is that.
So when things are clicked on,
you can use segue or
you can use these to find out
things were clicked on and
do whatever you want.
So yeah, a lot of wills and
dids and all those things.
You can look at
the documentation for
UITableViewDelegate.
Now back to what this
guy was asking before.
What happens if
my model changes?
It gets bigger?
Or even gets smaller or
whatever?
One thing you can do
that's kind of a hammer is
reloadData.
If you go reloadData on your
table view it's going to call
all of your data
source methods again.
How many sections you got,
how many rows in each section?
Give me a cell for
every single visible row.
You see what I mean?
It's going to do the whole
thing all over again.
It's kind of a hammer because
if you know that you only
changed one section okay?
Then you can call something
like reloadRows (at
indexPaths...).
And indexPaths would tell
the sections and rows.
With some animation.
And animations can
be like fade in or
slide from the bottom or
things like that.
So there are lighter
weight ones you can call.
And I'm actually gonna
show you in the demo,
we're gonna call one where
we're just gonna tell
the table view that we
inserted a section and
it's going to
immediately just ask me
the data source message about
that section and nothing else.
So you do need to
tell the table view
every time you
change your model.
If you change your model in
any way that would change the
number of sections and rows.
Or even the display of a row,
you need to tell
the table view.
So, just always think
about that when you're
writing table view code.
Change my model,
tell the table view.
Right away.
You want to tell the table
view right away.
And change your model first,
then change your table view.
Because when you
tell your table view
things have changed, it's
gonna go back and ask you, so
for IndexPath,
number of sections,
it'll ask you those questions,
some of them again.
So make sure your models
are already changed and
ready to answer
those questions.
Le's talk about
the height of rows.
The height of the row
generally set in
the Storyboard.
So you could resize it and set
it and tha's what it is but
you can also ask the delegate.
You can also implement
a method in the delegate and
it'll ask the delegate, what
height should this row be?
This might be very useful in
your homework, by the way.
But this is for when you have
the rows that change height
in some calculated way.
Maybe you have
an image in there, and
it's got different aspect
ratios, for example.
And so it's different
heights sometimes, whatever.
So you can answer it this way.
Of course, the other way
you can control the height
is by doing auto layout, and
setting your height to
be automatic dimension.
If you set your height to be
UITableViewAutomaticDimension,
that means go figure it out
from the auto layout please.
So those are the three was
you can set the height.
Set it fixed in the story
board, answer this delegate
method here,
heightForRowAt indexPath,
or set it to
the automatic dimension.
If you do the automatic ways
then you also probably want to
set the estimated row height.
That just tells the table view
calculate from auto layout but
for all those cells
the 100,000 cells that aren't
on screen please don't do auto
layout for 100,000 cells.
Just estimate them to be about
this and as they start to come
on screen then it's gonna
do the auto layout and
pick the exact
right height okay.
So that's why you
need to estimate.
And there's also
a delicate method,
estimated height per
row at whatever.
So there's dozens of methods
also, in table view itself.
Not in its delegates, but
in table view itself.
You can scroll to a row
cuz it's a scroll view.
It knows how to do scrolling.
You can control the look,
the separators between rows.
All those kind of things.
So you're definitely want
to familiarize yourself
with the table
view API itself.
Don't forget about that.
All right, so I'm not
coming back to this slide.
So just give you
a quick coming up here.
We have collection
view on Friday.
So collection view is very
similar to table view,
but the layout doesn't have
to be in a strict table.
It can be kind of laid
out any way you want.
But it's the same kind of
thing where there's data and
it's gonna ask you how many
sections there, how many row,
not rows but items in that
section, then it's gonna have
this little extra mechanism
for doing a lay out.
So it's really awesome.
I'd love to have time to
teach it in lecture not in
the optional section but I've
got so much to teach in this
course and you really need to
understand TableView first,
which is a little simpler,
before you can move onto
CollectionView- but
really don't miss Friday.
It will be a good way to
really it much more powerful
kind of data presentation UI.
And then next week we gonna
talk about Core Data,
which is the object-oriented
database in iOS,
really powerful mechanism.
Right now, I'm gonna be
doing a big demo that shows
how to do all this
TableView stuff and
also TextField and
some other things.
And your Assignment 4 is out,
and it's due in one week,
on Wednesday and it's
basically to take what I do
today and build a better one.
More feature-full.
So that's why you
always want to understand what
I'm doing in lecture, because
I'm almost always just asking
you to do the same thing.
Okay so
I'm gonna build a completely
fresh app from scratch.
Like I said before it's
gonna be a Twitter client.
We're gonna be doing
Twitter searches.
It's gonna be
a single view app.
i'm gonna call it Smashtag,
kind of like hashtag.
As always,
This is gonna be
an iPhone-only app.
And that's true for
your homework as well.
Okay, iPhone-only, we're
not gonna do an iPad thing.
You already learned that
with assignment three.
Trying to keep what
you're learning
as new as possible
with each one.
I'm gonna put this where
I always put everything.
Here we go, I'm gonna get rid
of some of these things over
here that we don't
really use very much.
Actually I'm gonna leave
plist as you'll see.
New group, we'll do
Supporting Files here, and
I will move that down.
Now I'm gonna start by taking
my Storyboard here and
just totally wiping it out.
Okay, I'm just gonna take
the one controller that I got,
the free one, and
just delete it.
I'm even gonna go over to
this code right here and
delete that, same thing
I did in the last demo.
Cuz I don't need any of that,
I'm gonna start
from scratch here.
So, we're building
a table view app, so
let's grab a table view,
I'm gonna scroll down here.
Here's a table view right
here, I just drag it out.
Now this table view if we
wanna use it as a delegate and
data source, or if we wanna
have outlets to it, we,
of course,
need a subclass of it.
So let's go ahead and
do that, New > File, okay.
It's gonna be
a Cocoa Touch subclass,
namely a
UITableViewController.
And I'm gonna call this my
TweetTableViewController,
because it's gonna
show tweets.
All right, and I'm gonna be
very careful to put it here,
not at the top level
of my project there.
And here we go,
here's our code right here.
I'm gonna delete this
View Controller Lifecycle
stuff, as usual.
But you'll notice
the TableViewController
also has some extra stuff.
You recognize those methods,
numberOfSections, okay,
numberOfRowsInSection, and
cellForRowAt indexPath.
These are the key
UITableViewDataSource
methods here.
Now there's some other
UITableViewDataSource
methods here as well,
these are for
things like deleting rows,
moving rows.
So when you're doing
your extra credit, or
when you're doing
your final project,
you'll be wanting to
not delete those.
But I will delete those just
to make our code a little bit
cleaner here.
So that's our
UITableViewController
subclass, we'll have to
implement these in a second.
But let's go back
to our Storyboard.
We also obviously wanna set
our identity here to instead
of being just generic
UITableViewController,
we want it to be
a TweetTableViewController.
Also, where's our
arrow coming in?
There's no arrow, so
let's select it again and
go back to attributes and pick
is initial view controller, so
we get this arrow coming in.
Okay, otherwise,
when we launch our app,
it's not gonna know what MVC
to start with, all right?
Now whenever we
have a new MVC,
what's one of the first
things we always wanna do?
Define its model.
Understand what this
MVC is all about.
What does it show or do?
And I'm going to pick my model
to be an array of tweets.
Okay, I'm gonna
call it tweets.
But I'm actually gonna
make it be an array
of array of tweets.
Okay, why am I making an array
of an array of tweets?
Because I'm going to be able
to put some tweets in my table
and then go fetch some
more and put more in.
And every time I put more in,
I'm gonna put it as a new
section, okay,
table view section.
So each array on
the inside of this array
is another batch of tweets.
And the outer array is
all of my sections.
So I have a really nice
data structure here.
It really matches up
nicely with table view.
And it's kind of nice to have
that kind of data structure.
And I kind of recommend that
in the homework if you can
make your data structure
match up with sections and
rows, then it makes
the implementation
of all these methods
down here a lot simpler.
All right, so, I've got
another part of my model,
though, which is
some searchText.
So the searchText
is like #stanford,
that's what I
wanna search for.
So this searchText is
what I'm searching for
to find my tweets.
And I'm making
this one public,
this is gonna be a public
part of my model.
So anyone using my MVC,
they set the search text.
I will show those tweets.
That's what I do.
All right, and I'm gonna do
that by populating this part
of my model over
here to show them.
So what do I need to do
if the searchText is set?
So I need to do some didSet
here, so the public model,
if something sets it,
I have to react well to it.
I mean, one thing that I'm
gonna wanna do is remove
all the tweets that
are already in my table.
And when I remove those
from my model up here,
I need to tell the table
view about it.
So I'm gonna have the
tableView.reloadData(), which
is the hammer, which is okay,
because I removed everything,
so the hammer's gonna
be pretty light,
a little ball-peen hammer.
Okay, just going to
clear the table out, so
tha's perfectly
fine in this case.
What else do I need to do?
Well, I, now I need
to search for tweets.
So I have to write a function
to do that to search for
some tweet.
I'm also gonna set my title
equal to the searchText.
That way if I happen to be in
a navigation controller or
something like that, it'll
show whatever I'm searching
for, #stanford or
whatever at the top, so
I'll just make my
UI look nice there.
All right, so
we got to do this private
func searchForTweets.
Okay, so this is the thing
that needs to go off and
find these tweets, and so
we'll do that in a moment.
One thing I'm also gonna do
is I'm gonna do viewDidLoad,
just for testing purposes.
You notice I do this a lot
when I'm developing, and
I wanna have some testing,
I'm gonna just set my
model to something.
So we'll do #stanford,
okay, just for testing.
Once we're got
our MVC working,
its public API is working,
then we will remove this code.
It's just testing code.
Okay, now,
we have an error here.
And this error is Swift
saying excuse me.
What is tweet?
What is that type?
And I didn't really want you
to be wasting your time in
your homework figuring
out how to go fetch
a tweet from Twitter and
do a request and all that.
So I wrote a framework
that did it for you.
And by framework,
I mean a framework like this.
Like UIKit, right, UIKit is
this like library of a whole
bunch of data structures that
you can use to build your app.
Well, I wrote one for you that
will do Twitter stuff for it.
And it has something
in it called tweet.
And it also has something
called request that lets
you make a Twitter request.
All right, so
that thing is right over here.
Now, how do frameworks work?
How do you use them when
they're not built into
the system like Apple?
And the answer is, you need to
build a higher level structure
for Xcode to work with
called a workspace.
So I'm actually gonna
close this project.
I'm closing this project.
And I'm going to Xcode, and
I'm gonna create a new thing,
which you've never seen
before, called a workspace.
Now when I create
this workspace,
it wants to know
where to put it.
Be careful here, look,
it's trying to put it
inside my Smashtag project,
which I don't wanna do that.
I wanna put it up the top
of my Developer level here,
same place I put all
of my projects, okay,
so really be
careful about that.
So I'm gonna call this L9,
this is lecture 9, so
we'll call it L9.
And I hit Save, and
this created this workspace.
But notice in the navigator,
there's nothing there.
So what do we put
in a workspace?
Well, what we put in a
workspace are other projects.
And this workspace is just
gonna collect all those
projects, because they
kind of go together.
And obviously, this Twitter
framework that I'm providing
to you right here goes
together with Smashtag,
which is this thing we've
been working on so far.
Now what you drag down in
here is the .xcodeproj,
because it's the project
itself that you wanna put in
this workspace.
So you just drag that in for
both of them, so
I'm gonna open
this one as well.
Here's the Xcode project for
this Twitter thing.
Drag in, now be careful
not to put it inside,
see how that's trying to put
it inside Smashtag there?
Put it outside, so
that they're siblings.
Now I have this workspace
right here that has two
projects in it, and you even
go here and hide others.
And if we look in the Smashtag
one, woo, looks familiar.
This is the code we were
just working on, right?
If we look in the Twitter one,
this is the code I
am providing you.
Now, what's in here?
Here's tweet which
is this struct and
it's got all the things you
would expect in a tweet.
The text of the tweet,
the user who created it,
which is another thing,
user right here,
and the user has a screen name
that's at sign something,
the actual name, a unique
identifier for the user.
Back to tweet, it's also
got a unique identifier.
It's also got things that
are embedded in the tweet like
other hashtags and
other users that are
referenced inside the tweet.
And even media cuz you
know a lot of times
tweets have an image
with them too.
And the other thing that's of
importance in this Twitter
framework that I'm giving
you is this class Request,
Twitter Request right here.
And this Request class is the
thing you use to make requests
for Twitter.
Now, you don't need to look
at any of the implementation
of any of this, and
in fact, you can go and
do assistant editor.
And if you do assistant editor
on something like this,
you're actually gonna
see its public API here.
See all those public,
public public, public,
public; now we have not seen
this public keyword before,
all we've seen is private or
fileprivate.
So what does this
public thing mean?
Look, I put public in all
this these things over here.
Public means that not only
is it not private but
you can see it even if this
framework is being used by
some other project.
So public means public outside
of this framework, right,
make sense?
So in UIKit a lot of
things are marked public.
All the things you can use
have to be marked public cuz
it's in a different
framework than your app.
Your app is kind of
a framework, in a sense, so
that's public.
And then,
also notice farther down,
these methods are marked
internal; that means I can
only use them inside my
framework, so I can't call any
of these methods from
Smashtag, they're internal.
This actually, you haven't
seen this keyword because
it's the default, all the
methods you've ever created
that you didn't mark private
or fileprivate are internal.
It's the default, so
you haven't put the word
internal there, okay.
So, let's look at
the public API.
Let's not even pay any
attention to that, and
look at the public API.
This public API of Request,
for making requests,
we're only going to
use three things.
One is this convenience
initializer
where you just give it
something to search for and
how many results you want.
And then this method
fetchTweets where you just
give it this closure which
it will call when it's done.
It's gonna go off and
do it on another thread and
when it's done it will call.
And that's going to have an
array of the tweets it found
that match your search.
what we're gonna use is this
one down here, newer where if
And then last,
you ask it a request,
give me a newer request.
It'll give your request that
you can use to get newer
tweets.
Tweets that have
been tweeted after
the previous one
that you've got.
So, that's all we're
gonna use here.
We're not really gonna
use any of the other API
in this request.
In your homework, you'll have
to know this API here of
Tweet cause you'll have to
be able to get the text and
the user information and
also MediaItems so
you can get the URLs of images
that are in there, etc.
But you never have to look at
the private implementation of
this framework so don't even
waste your time looking there.
Just look at things
marked public,
there's not a lot of things
marked public- that's the only
thing you're going
to look for.
Now how do I use
this framework,
this Twitter framework
in Smashtag?
Well, you have to do one step.
You can't just put them
in the same workspace and
start working.
Well, two steps, one is I
need to say import Twitter.
Just like I say import UIKit,
if I want to use this Twitter
framework up here I have
to say import Twitter.
That's gonna cause this
tweet to start being
recognized as a type
because it's gonna see this
tweet type right over here.
But the other important thing,
don't forget,
is you need to tell Xcode that
when you build Smashtag that
app includes Twitter in it.
And you do that by going to
the Smashtag project, okay,
the project settings.
And go all the way to
the bottom where it says
Embedded Binaries.
And just pick up the product
of your Twitter framework.
You see where it says
Products right here?
Just pick that up and drag
it in here, and that says,
please put Twitter
framework into my Smashtag,
because my Smashtag uses it.
If you don't do this step,
then it'll all compile but
then when Smashtag runs,
Twitter won't be there, and
so it will fail.
Now, I'm gonna make you
do that step as part of
your homework.
I will post this code for
Smashtag, but
I'm not gonna post
the workspace, so
you're gonna have to build
the workspace on your own.
All right, so let's continue.
Now that we've got
this array of tweets,
what are we gonna do with
this array of tweets?
Let's start by doing a fetch
for our search text.
So we got our search text,
we wanna go fetch all
those things on there.
That's what we're supposed
to do in search for tweets.
Let's make another
function here,
another little private func.
I'm gonna call it
twitterRequest,
which is gonna return
a Twitter.Request.
But yeah,
here's another thing.
This I can call tweet because
I'm importing this Twitter
framework and there's no
other class called tweet, so
i just have to call it tweet.
Its full name is
actually Twitter.Tweet.
Just like, you know,
UITableViewController,
it's full name is
UIKit.UITableViewController.
use Twitter.Tweet because I
think in Assignment 5, you
Now i'm gonna
might end up wanting to have
you own local tweet class.
So I'm gonna use
Twitter.Tweet and
Twitter.Request everywhere but
I wouldn't have to as long as
I didn't have a class called
Tweet or Request otherwise.
But this is a pretty generic
name request so putting
the Twitter dot on front might
be kind of a good idea anyway.
All right so
the Twitter.Request function
here is just going to return
a Twitter request that
matches this search text.
And that's really,
really simple,
I'm just gonna say,
if I can let the query for
the search term equal
the search text.
And I wanna make sure that
that query is not empty.
So I don't wanna search for
nil or for the empty string.
So I'm just keeping that
out of it right here.
And otherwise I'm just gonna
return a Twitter request using
that convenient initializer I
told you about called Search.
And I'm just gonna
pass that query and,
well let's get 100 of them.
Okay, so we're gonna, we'll
grab 100 tweets at a time.
And if that's not true,
if the search term is nil or
it's empty, then I'm gonna
return nil from this.
So let's make this be,
you know, optional.
Okay, so everyone understand
what this function does?
It just makes a Twitter
request that will search for
our searchText,
that's all it does.
So now down here in
searchForTweets,
I can say if I can let request
equal the twitterRequest,
which hopefully it can make.
Okay, now I have a request.
Now I just need to cause
that request to happen.
So I'm just gonna say this
Twitter request.fetchTweets.
So this fetchTweets function
right there, you see it?
The top one, okay,
it takes this closure
right here as an argument.
I'm gonna double click on it,
to show what it does here.
I'm going to use trailing
closure syntax to get rid of
the parentheses there.
Now what's this?
This is the only
argument in my closure.
Those are the tweets
that it fetched.
See it's an array of tweets.
I'll call this newTweets.
Okay, so that's going to
be an array of tweets,
I don't even need the
parentheses here by the way.
So I have newTweets.
So newTweets is gonna be
an array of Tweet that it
fetched; now, of course,
it's doing this off
the main queue, right?
It's gotta go do that
Twitter request,
what if it's a really
slow network?
Or Twitter is really slow
that time or whatever.
I finally got these new tweets
back, what do I wanna do?
So inside here,
Well I just want to add them
on to the end of my model,
Here's my model, it's
an array of array of tweets.
right?
Here's an array, so I'm just
going to take my model, and
append onto it this
array of tweets.
And actually, I'm not gonna
append it on the end because
I want all my new tweets to
show up at the beginning,
so in section zero
at the beginning, so
I'm gonna insert these new
tweets at 0 in my array.
So right at the top.
So my new tweets are gonna
come in at the top.
Make sense?
Now, we have an error there.
Can anyone guess why this
error is here before I
open it?
>> Mutating.
>> What?
>> Yeah, mutating.
>> Mutating.
That's a good guess but no.
It's because self, it's
the old closure cycle problem,
right?
Since we're
accessing self here,
these tweets as
part of our self.
We need to explicitly
say that so
that we can notice,
we might have a memory cycle.
And do we have
a memory cycle here?
In fact we do.
Because what if this view
controller goes off to
fetch some tweets and
it takes forever.
And so the person says, I'll
search for something else.
Now they said the search
text is on the else and
another fetch goes off.
And now here comes the first
fetch and it's irrelevant now
because I already looked for
something else.
So we do here,
want to be careful to ignore
this when it comes back and we
also, if someone searches and
it's taking forever and they
hit back, we want our view
controllers to be able
to leave memory as well.
So we don't want the closure,
the cycle here,
we don't want this closure
holding our self in memory.
So we don't want this to
be a strong pointer and
we need to check to make
sure that when we get back,
it's still what
we're interested in.
So how can we
break this cycle?
We're just gonna use our
friend weak self, okay?
That's easy.
And that turns this
into an optional.
So we added a question mark.
Boom, we broke that cycle.
So even if this fetch is
sitting out there fetching,
it's not gonna be keeping our
view controller in memory.
Our view control can
leave memory, and
if it comes back and
it's gone, then this line
of code will not execute.
How about dealing with the
fact that our request might
have changed?
Well, to do that,
I'm gonna have to keep track
of our lastTwitterRequest,
actually we've got to
put it inside here.
Okay, I'm gonna keep
track of it, and
then in here I'm not going
to do this unless our
request equals
the lastTwitterRequest.
So if this request that came
back is not the last one we
issued, then I'm
not gonna do it.
And so let me go up here and
say private var
lastTwitterRequest and
that's going to be
a Twitter.Request of course.
Request, optional,
is not always set.
Everyone kinda see
what I'm doing there?
And of course this is saying
self again, so we'll put self
in there and of course self
is weak so we'll do that.
So that's all good.
Any other problems you
can see with this?
I don't see any so far.
So it's all good.
So,
before we go hooking
up our table view,
let's just make sure that our
Twitter fetches are working.
And I'm gonna do that
by putting a didSet
up here on my model, and
every time my model changes,
I'm just gonna print
the tweets out.
Now luckily I've made it so
the tweet is
CustomStringConvertible,
it implements description.
It can print itself
as a string so
this is an array of those.
So this will print out
an array, actually an array
of an array of this tweet
printed out as a string.
So we're just gonna
print it out there.
Just seems like
it should work?
Let's go give it a try and
find out.
We'll do this on iPhone 7.
Pay attention right
now because this
is not in fact going to work.
And this won't work for you
either and you're gonna need
to do a couple of things to
make a Twitter fetch work.
By the way you see we have
these prototype cells that
have to have reuse
identifiers; gotta remember to
fix that later.
Alright, so we run, and look
at this thing it puts up here,
Smashtag would like to
access Twitter accounts.
So you're not allowed to
write an app that just starts
posting things for people on
Twitter behind the scenes.
Okay, when you write an app
it is always going to ask,
the first time you try to use
Twitter, whether it's allowed.
So I'll click okay, and let's
go look in our console and
see if it printed.
It didn't, all it printed out
here is, couldn't discover
Twitter account type, hm,
why would it say that?
Well, that's because your
simulator, it's just a device,
it needs to have Twitter,
a Twitter account, basically,
your device needs
a Twitter account, so
where do we set that?
So let's go back
to our simulator,
here it is, I'm gonna go
hardware, home button, okay,
you can also do command,
shift, F.
Is hardware home button.
And I'm gonna go over to the
Settings app on my simulator.
But you can do it on
your device as well.
And if you go down in
settings, here's Twitter.
Look at that.
Twitter right there.
And here's where
you type in your
Twitter username and password.
And if you don't type this in,
then no apps on your
system can access Twitter.
Cuz how would they- they'd
have to know who you are.
So I'm gonna type this here,
I'm gonna do it off screen cuz
I don't want you to
see my password.
So now I am logged
in on Twitter.
So now if I go back and
start my app
It will both be in allowed
because I clicked OK.
And I'll be logged in so
it'll have an actual Twitter
user that can do it.
And sure enough,
look down here at the bottom.
We're getting all kinds of
tweets being printed out here.
So here's a tweet.
Here's its unique ID.
Here's the person
who tweeted it.
Here's when it was tweeted.
Here is the text of the tweet.
This one's got
an embedded URL, etc.
So we're doing well.
We've got our
tweets coming in.
So now all we need to do
is load them up into our
table view.
So what do we need to do
to load this thing up in
the table view?
Now, surprisingly simple
actually, the two pieces we
have to do, one is every time
we change our model we have
to tell the table view that
it changed and then we have
to implement those table
view data source methods.
So let's start with
the first one.
Actually we have already
changed our model once.
Right here,
we changed our model and
we told the table view
about it, so that's good.
Here we're changing our model.
So we need to tell
the table view about it.
So self?.tableView.
And what did I do
here to my model?
I just inserted a section
at the beginning.
So there happens to be
a tableView method called
insertSection.
And it just says,
you inserted some sections.
Which ones?
ask you about those and
put the rows in there for you.
I will go and
And this sections
is an index set,
which you can give
it an array literal.
So I just inserted
section zero.
So I'll just put an array
with just zero in it.
And I'm gonna use
the fade animation
to show that fading in.
So, insertSections.
So, this is me telling the
tableView, I changed my model,
so ask me again.
Ask me those tableView
data source.
Now, since I told it exactly
what I did it's only gonna ask
me about that section, which
is nice, higher performance.
Then reloadData,
the hammer reloadData,
in which case it would ask me
for all rows in all sections
again; so here I know
exactly what I did.
Now this actually is
dangerous code here.
This is really easy to
add this line of code and
now your app just acts weird.
It just acts weird
all the time.
Can anyone, want,
guess why this
adding this line of code would
cause my app to go all weird?
It's because this
is a UI call.
And what queue are we on here?
Some queue,
not the main queue.
Whatever queue we fetched
those tweets on, okay?
So we're not on
the main queue.
So we can't make
a UI call here.
Right, so we have to dispatch
this back to the main queue.
So this is something that,
will just take some
getting used to for
you guys with this
multithreading,
cuz you're gonna do these
things in this other queue,
and you're gonna update
your table view, and then
it's like what's going on my
app is just acting so strange.
And that's why-
because you can do
UI stuff on the main queue.
And it's not gonna warn you or
necessarily crash,
it might eventually crash,
it's just gonna act all weird.
So, fixed that.
This is good.
We've got the table view
updating our model and we've
got the table view knowing
about change to the model.
So now all we need to
do is implement this
UITableViewDataSource protocol
so
that it can get
the data from us.
So let's do it.
Number of sections, how many
sections are in our table?
Anyone know?
Yeah.
Exactly, candy thrown at you
cuz that's exactly right.
tweets.count.
It's just the number of arrays
that we have in our model here
because each of this arrays
inside here are a section, so
perfect.
And then what about this one?
Here we're being asked how
many rows are there in tweets
subsection?
That's just count also.
So we've designed our
data structure so
that these are super
easy to implement,
which I highly recommend
if you can do it.
You can't always do it.
But if you can it's nice.
So now a little more
difficult, only a little
though, is cellForRowAt
index path right here.
So here's where we have to
return the UITableViewCell
that we're gonna use to draw.
Now, let's go back to
our Storyboard here and
let's just start out
with something simple.
Let's try using here
a subtitle cell.
So I'm gonna click
on this cell.
And will change its
style from being custom
to being subtitle.
So there's title and subtitle.
And I'm gonna set the title to
be the text with the tweet.
And I'm gonna set the subtitle
to be the person
who tweeted it.
So let's try that and
see how that looks.
So how am I gonna do that?
Two things I need to do here.
One is I need to dequeue
a reusable cell, and
I to tell iOS which
prototype to use,
which prototype in
the Storyboard.
So lets go back to
our Storyboard.
And I only have one prototype.
It's this one.
That's the one I wanna use.
So I need to give
it an identifier.
I'm gonna call it Tweet,
because that's what
this cell shows.
It shows a tweet.
Notice that caused my
warning to go away.
Because all these
prototype cells
always need an identifier.
And now when I go back here,
I can change this from
reuseIdentifier to Tweet.
Okay, so now, I am able
to dequeueReusableCell
that will be a copy of that
prototype that's subtitled.
So all my rows are gonna
be subtitle rows.
So now I've got this cell,
it's of type
UITableViewCell by the way,
since it's a standard
type not a custom type.
How do I configure it?
Well, for me to configure the
cells, to set the title and
I need to know which Tweet
it's asking me for here.
the subtitle,
And I know which Tweet
it's asking because it's
saying cellForRowAt.
This is the row that's
the tweet that is asking
me to give it
a UITableViewCell for.
So I'm gonna let tweet equal
my model sub
indexPath.section and
indexPath.row.
So I'm just getting this
row in this section,
this gets the first array,
the section,
I'm just getting
the row out of it.
So now I got the tweet, so
now I can just update the cell
really easily, cell.textLabel.
It might be an optional
?.text equals,
let's have that be
the tweet's text.
This is something that
you'll see in here, we go to
the Twitter, and look for the
Twitter framework at Tweet,
and you'll see that the very
first one in fact, is text.
And then we'll make this
cell detailTextLabel,
its text will be the tweet's
user's name, let's say.
So again, Tweet,
user, username.
So, that's why I'm
getting that information.
Do you understand that?
Part of it, okay?
So, that I'll came
out of this Tweet.
This is of type Tweet.
Everybody got that?
All right, so is that it?
Do we need to do anything else
to hook this thing up and
make it work?
Turns out no.
So let's just run.
Okay, there it is.
The world's greatest
Twitter client.
Look at that.
It looks beautiful.
No, of course, in fact,
this is the world's ugliest
Twitter client right here.
But it is working.
These are tweets.
But anyway, you can see
here's the tweets and
here are the person
who tweeted it.
Now obviously,
this is awful UI.
Just absolutely horrendous UI.
You would never have
a Twitter client like this.
We want our UI in these
cells to look much nicer,
much more customized
to a tweet.
So we're gonna go back
to our Storyboard here.
And instead of using this
awful subtitle style cell,
we're gonna build
a custom cell.
And this custom cell is gonna
have more good looking and
more of the data that
comes with a Tweet.
So let's just build it.
Let's go here and make this a
little bigger, make some room.
All right, I'm gonna grab
some labels out of here.
There's a label,
this will maybe be,
let's say this is the Tweeter.
This is the person
who's doing the Tweet.
By the way, this is a case
where we're showing user
content really.
These tweets are content.
They're not like the title
of a button or something,
it's actually the content that
the user has requested to see.
So I'm gonna use a font here.
You see this font?
I'm not gonna use
the system font.
I'm going to go down and
start using this text styles.
So the Tweeter is going
to be at the top.
I'm gonna have that
be a headline font.
So this is gonna be
the headline font and
this could change over time,
okay, whatever the system
thinks headline font is and
it'll be true in every app.
The headline will always be
using this font in every app
and users could even
go into settings and
change the size
of their fonts.
If they're like me and
they're visions going
they can set them bigger.
And the fonts will get
bigger automatically so
ther's big advantage to
using these font styles.
So there's that one.
There is the text of
the tweet itself, so
we'll just call that text.
maybe a good font is body font
because this is really, this
For this one,
is the heart of what we're
doing here, this body thing.
One thing that's kinda cool
with UILabel, the text
in the tweet is probably
gonna be multiple lines, and
it's gonna wrap.
When you have a UI
label like that,
you wanna set this
property lines to be zero.
If you have zero predefined
lines then the UILabel
will be however many
lines it needs to be fit
the information with wrapping.
Whereas this one is line
one this all one line.
And if it's too long it just
gets dot dot dot at the end,
all right?
What else do I wanna do here?
Let's do another
label here for
when the tweet was tweeted
out, when it was created.
That one is probably something
like a caption, we'll say.
Small little text
at the bottom.
We'll go ahead and
center than right there.
Let's also get an image.
Let's go down and
find the image view down here.
Where is our image view?
Here it is.
Drag it out here.
This is gonna be the profile
image of the Tweeter.
So whoever tweeted this will
have their little image here.
This one, by the way,
I don't know how big profile
images are on Twitter.
And I don't care because
I'm gonna make this thing
always be a fixed size.
So how do we make an image
like this be a fixed size
using auto layout?
And it turns out what you do
is you Ctrl+Drag to itself.
And when you do,
you'll see that you have
the option to fix its width.
And you can Ctrl+Drag,
and fix its height.
You can also to both
at the same time.
And, so what width and
height has it fixed it to?
Well, we can look over here
in the size inspector,
and see that it's
fixed it to 71 by 67.
That doesn't sound very
computer science-y,
I'm gonna fix it to 64 by 64.
So I've made it so
this image view is always
gonna be 64 by 64.
I don't care how big the
person's actual profile image
is, I always want
it to be that way.
Okay, so there's another
little auto layout
tidbit for you.
speaking of auto layouts,
I need to lay this stuff out.
All right, so
I kinda want it to look,
eh, something like this.
See what I mean?
Approximately, and so
I'm just gonna use stack view.
So we'll stack those two
things together, like that.
Look at our things here,
fill and fill.
That's perfectly fine.
Let's go over here.
Let's stack those together.
That's fill and fill.
One thing about these two,
by the way, they're gonna be
sharing the space in
this stack view equally.
But I don't want them
sharing equally.
I actually want the text
to get more of this space.
So I'm gonna click
on the Tweeter.
And I'm gonna go over
to this size inspector.
And I'm gonna do
something cool,
which is set its content
hugging priority.
I'm gonna set its
vertical content
hugging priority to be
higher than the other one.
So they're both 251.
You see, that one's 251,
that one's 251.
So I'm gonna set
this one to be 300,
just anything higher than 251.
And that means that when
the space is being allocated
between this tweeter and
the text, it's gonna hug
the tweeter's content.
And the text is gonna
get all the rest.
So that's a way
that you can kinda,
when you're sharing space
between two things.
All right, so now let's
put these two in a stack.
Maybe we'll put some spacing
here, something like that.
Alignment here, top is good,
I want them both at the top.
I think that's good,
lined up at the top.
If I like that and
fill is fine, I've got this.
Now I'm gonna do the same
thing we did before,
which is I'm gonna put
this in the corner.
And I'm gonna Ctrl
drag to the top.
I'm gonna Ctrl drag
to the leading edge.
to the trailing edge.
And I'm gonna Ctrl drag
to the bottom edge.
So I want that out there.
And again, the same thing.
I'm gonna take this and change
it to standard if I can.
I can't, so we'll go 0.
And same thing here.
Standard if I can,
can't, we'll do 0.
So I've made this stock
view that contains all
the stuff fit in there.
So I basically done the auto
layout necessary to make this
thing use the space properly.
And I can still change the
size of the cell, all right?
I can click on it and I can
make it a little bit smaller
and all that stuff is
going to, you know,
stick to the edges,
so that'll be fine.
Now, this is great,
in fact if we go back to our
table view controller and
if I comment out this cell
configuration because we don't
have a subtitle so these don't
make any sense any more.
And we run, then we gonna
see that our UI hopefully,
if we didn't forget anything.
It's going to look in some
ways a little better.
Yeah, so
it kinda looks better.
Now, the only thing that's not
better is we lost our data
because I commented out
the data loading right here.
So this is what we want UI
to look like basically with
an image here and that there.
But we need to set
all this data.
So how do we that?
Since this is a custom
cell over here.
We have to do with
a custom subclass
of this UI table view
cell right here.
So, I'm gonna create
one of those, New File.
Let's go here and New File.
Again, Cocoa Touch Class;
this time though,
it's not a TableViewController
it's a TableViewCell.
I'm gonna call it
TweetTableViewCell cuz
it shows the tweet,
put in the same place as all
the rest of my stuff there.
Here's my table table view
cell, it gives me awakeFromNib
which is kinda nice but I
don't need it and setSelected
I don't do anything special
when my table view cell is
selected but I could, I could
draw a blue background or
something like that if
I wanted, but I don't.
So, I have this
TableViewCell subclass.
I'm gonna go back to
my Storyboard and
make sure that I
set the identity,
don't forget this step.
Set the identity to be
a TweetTableViewCell.
If you forget this step,
you won't be able to do any
outlets or anything like that.
Now, I wanna wire outlets
up to this new class I
just created, so I need to
get them both on screen,
I'll show you kind of
a cool way to do that.
Let's get the assistant
editor up here,
remember I could do manual,
blah, blah, blah,
but another way is to hold
down the option key, and
just click on the thing that
you want to be on the right,
I think I showed this before,
but option
clicking in the navigator will
put that thing on the right.
All right so let's move this
over more, some space there.
All right, so I need to wire
up outlets to these four
things, right, the tweet or
the text or the image.
So let's just do that.
We'll go here, Ctrl+drag,
screen out, I'll call this my
tweet, what did I call this,
my tweetProfileImageView.
Cuz it's gonna be
a UIImageView that shows
the Tweeter's profile.
Let's do the little
create down here,
Ctrl+Drag, from that.
We'll call that
tweetCreatedLabel.
To label it.
Shows when it was created;
let's do out little tweeter
right here and we call
that our tweetUserLabel,
this is gonna show
the label of the tweet
user and then we have the text
right here that's gonna show
the actual tweetText,
tweetTextLabel.
So I've got these nice
little outlets right here.
Now of course I need to be
able to set these outlets with
something and here's where
I need public API in my
table view cell, that gives me
the data I need to do that.
And I'm just going to have
my public API be tweet,
give me the Twitter.Tweet
that you want and
I'll load these babies up.
That's what it's saying here.
Of course we need
to import Twitter.
Cuz we're using
it in this class.
And when you set this Tweet
I'm just going to on didSet.
Update my UI just like
I was a controller but
I'm not, I'm not a controller,
I'm a view actually.
It's the only time a view
can have these outlets.
So I need some private
func to do that updateUI.
Now, time is running
a little bit short here, so
I'm just going to type
this in real quick
I believe I have tweet cell.
There it is, okay?
But you can look
at this later.
But I'm just basically
setting all the outlets here.
See how I'm just setting these
outlets like setting the tweet
label, text to be
the tweet's text,
setting the user label to
be the user description.
Notice by the way I'm blocking
the main thread here.
If this was my homework,
bam I just got dinged.
So make sure you fix this,
okay?
If you're gonna use my code
in any way in your homework,
which you probably want to,
then you're gonna
wanna fix this.
Don't do this on
the main thread.
Don't block the main thread.
But, does anyone understand
what updateUI is doing here?
It's just taking this
Tweet that I was giving,
and loading this up.
And this is happening over and
over for
every row in the table
that gets displayed.
This is happening, the copy of
this class has been made and
this is happening.
Now, how do we set this?
We set this back over here and
our TweetTableViewController.
In the same place that we
configured the cell here for
the subtitle one.
And in fact, I still need the
tweet, but I don't need that.
I'll leave those there, so
you can remember that code
when you look at it later.
But instead of setting
those things, I just want
to set that tweet, I wanna
set this var right here.
But for
me to set the var right here,
I need to get my table
view to be one of these.
So, I need to use an as.
So, I'm gonna say,
if I can let the tweetCell
equal the cell,
this reusable cell that I got,
as a TweetTableViewCell,
then, I can say, cell set
your tweet to be my tweet.
That goes in this row,
section, and row.
Now, we set the, what,
sorry, tweetCell.tweet.
We set the class of these,
of this prototype right here,
the prototype for this cell.
We set it with the identity
inspector to be
a TweetTableViewCell.
So, when we come in here,
it will, in fact,
this as will work.
Okay, it will be a
TweetTableViewCell cuz we said
that in the Storyboard, so,
it created that kind of thing,
all right?
So, let see if this works.
Okay, it is working.
Look, we've got the time
the person tweeted this,
it's got the person
who tweeted it,
it's got the text of the
tweeting, but we get no image.
Why didn't we get
people's images here?
Okay, why do you think
we didn't get these,
these images?
Well, let's go look
at our console.
What does it say?
No!
App Transport Security.
You recognize that
from last time?
It's because these profiles
are http something not
https something.
So, we know how to fix that.
We'll just go back to
Info.plist right here.
And add a row for
App Transport Security.
We'll open that up, we'll
add Arbitrary Loads here,
we'll make that be, yes,
we allow arbitrary loads.
There's another
problem here though.
Look at all these tweets.
Look how they're cut off,
you see?
Every row is the same size and
it's not big enough for
most of the tweets.
It's just dot, dot,
dot, dot, dot, dot.
Wouldn't it be cool if these
rows could be different sizes
depending on how
big the tweet is?
Well, of course
we can do that.
Let's do it.
Let's go see how this size
is being said right now.
Right now, it's being said,
if we go and
inspect this cell in its
size inspector, look,
the row height is 96, so,
every single row is 96.
What we wanna do is in our
viewDidLoad right here,
we wanna say that our
tableView's row height is not
96, it's
UITableViewAutomaticDimension.
But as I said before, we also
want to give it a little help
by setting its estimated
row height to something.
And I'll tell you what,
let's set it to what's
in the Storyboard.
tableView.rowHeight, okay?
So, I'm getting the rowHeight
out of the Storyboard,
using it as the estimate.
And then, I'm resetting
the rowHeight to be
the AutomaticDimension.
And sure enough, see, look,
this tall tweet is
getting extra space and
some of the smaller tweets,
I don't know if we have any,
you can probably see
it if we go like this.
The smaller tweets
get less space, okay?
So, that's good.
We're out of time, so,
if you have to go, feel free.
The last thing I'm gonna do
here in a little over time is
add a text field at the top
that lets us type in what
we wanna search for instead of
always looking for Stanford.
So, we're gonna get Stanford
out of there, okay?
So, how do we do that?
It's real easy.
We have, if you remember,
the table view, it's got this
little header view at the top.
So, I'm just gonna
take a UITextField.
Remember this editable text
field we learned about in
the last lecture?
And I'm gonna put
it on the top.
It's a little hard, sometimes,
to see where it's going,
but when it looks like this,
the width of the table, then,
you've got it,
it's dropping it in there.
It's also a little hard
to select and click on.
So, you're gonna wanna use
that Ctrl + Shift + Click.
And that way, you can pick
either the controller, or
the table view, or
in this case, the text field.
I'm gonna inspect it and
change it a little bit.
I'm just gonna make the font
a little bit bigger,
we'll say 22.
Now, notice I can also set all
those text field things I was
talking about.
Like, I don't want
it auto-correcting.
I don't wanna say, search for
hashtag SuperBowl and
change it hashtag
SuperSpaceBowl, okay?
So, I don't want any
correction going on.
Keyboard type, ooh, look,
there's a Twitter
keyboard type.
It's probably got # and
@ sign, things like that.
The return key,
that's just the key on
the things says return.
I'm searching here, so,
I wanted to say search.
So, that means the return
keys gonna say, I'd search.
Also, a little clear
button would be cool,
button you can press the clear
out what's going on.
So, you can kinda configure
this in any way you want
to make it work in there.
Now, normally I would run this
and show you that it's there,
let's wire it up first, so,
it actually does something.
but of course,
It's real easy to wire up
a text field if you just
wanna hook it up to an outlet
and set its delegate, and
then, you can find out when
the return key is pressed.
So, let's do that.
We'll go here, let's get our
TweetTableViewController on
screen at the same time.
We just wanna create
an outlet to that thing.
I'll put it, right in here.
So, I'm just,
again, I will probably wanna
Shift + Click to select it.
I, oops, picked the wrong one.
So, let's Shift + Click,
click this, select this,
and Ctrl + Drag from it, and
see it's a UITextField, and
I'm gonna call this
my searchTextField.
Simple as that.
When it's set, I'm going to
set myself as its delegates.
searchTextField.delegate =
self.
Of course, for me to be
its delegate, I have to go
up here and say yes,
I am a UITextFieldDelegate.
Okay, they're all the methods
are optional in there, so,
I have now successfully
implemented that protocol.
Ooh, what happened here?
Yes, okay, so that's so
I've set the delegate.
Now, I'm gonna implement
the delegate method I want,
which is that should return.
It get sent to me when
the return button is sent.
So that is textField,
notice as I type textField
it shows me them all,
and it is this one right
here textFieldShouldReturn.
Let me make this bigger,
bigger so
you can see it better.
Okay, so here should return.
If I get return, I'm
actually gonna check to make
sure I'm getting this
from my searchTextField,
because someday I might have
other text fields and I wanna
make sure I'm getting, I know
which one I'm talking about.
So textField is this
argument right here, and
I'm just checking to
make sure it's me.
And if that is true then
I'm just gonna set my
searchText =
searchTextFields.text, okay?
Makes sense and
when I set my searchText,
that's immediately going
to start it going.
Notice that ShouldReturn
also returns a Bool which is
whether to do what it normally
does when return is pressed.
Which in this case is nothing,
cuz we don't have
any target action or
anything else, but
we'll return true.
Sure do what you normally do,
now the only other thing
here is now that we have
the searchTextField,
up here when we set
our searchText.
We wanna update our
searchTextField.
And I'll be careful here in
case I'm doing it in prepare.
We'll set it to the searchText
that we just set it to.
Also I'm going to have
my searchTextField
resignFirstResponder here.
That's if somebody types
something and hits go search,
and we search for
something and put it in there.
I'm gonna take
the keyboard away.
Cuz I just don't wanna
have the keyboard blocking
the results that
they just asked for.
And also someone
sets it in code.
I'm gonna get rid of keyboard.
Someone might be in
the middle of typing but
if someone sets it in
code rather than typing.
Let's get that keyboard
out of the way, all right?
So let's go do that.
Leave this code on the screen
so you can see it.
All right, so here is our text
field, it's kinda of hard to
see under this carrier,
we'll fix that in a second.
Let's go and search for
#stanford again.
Oops, I'm not gonna do this,
watch this.
Okay that looked easy to type,
didn't it?
Well let's go here and
say Keyboard, turn off
the hardware keyboard.
Now when we click in here,
ooh, it's a lot
harder to type.
#stanford, okay so
now you're getting into what
I'm saying about learn to
type like your users will be.
So here I'm going to search,
goes in stanford and
search for it.
Let's go and search for
something else here.
Maybe we'll search for,
this is kind of dangerous
because people might say, but
Trump
>> Okay,
there's some Trump ones.
Now, we've done all this.
I wanna fix this thing though,
where this looks really
bad at the top here.
And there's this really
easy fix to that.
Which is I'm just going to,
this is the fix.
The fix is everything in
the UI as you've learned.
I'm just gonna embed this
in a navigation controller.
Okay, when you embed this in a
navigation controller and run,
you can see that it makes
a nice title at the top,
it moves the text field down,
it's just much
nicer all around.
Okay, see how it has done
that from a bit down here.
One other thing I'm gonna do
is put placeholder text in
there, I meant to
show you that.
Sorry, let's do that, if I
go back to here click this.
That thing in here,
swipe this guide.
You can put a placeholder text
like this, Twitter Search and
see it shows it in there,
kinda like gray.
So that when you run,
it's more obvious to the user,
what is that big white space,
all right?
Be clear to them that
it's a Twitter search.
You know all you need to
know to do your homework.
Good luck with it.
>> For more, please visit
us at Stanford.edu.